Welcome to the iOS Lead Essentials
program
we're so excited to have you with us and
you may be excited to join as well
hopefully or you may be wondering if you
made
the right choice what I want to say for
sure
is that this program works you will see
and interact with
lead iOS developers working in exciting
apps and companies
so seeing their success will inspire you
to get there
too so don't forget to say hi and
present yourself
in the Slack community exactly
in our community there are bootcamp and
university graduates
self-taught developers, juniors, mid-level
seniors, lead developers so
regardless your current level there is
space for you to thrive in the program
definitely so before you jump right in
the lectures
we'd like to get you ready for what's to
come so this dev program is designed to
get your dev skills
to the next level your goal in this
program is to achieve
technical excellence as an iOS developer
and position yourself as a leader
in the software industry so there are
over 60 lectures
here plus mentoring sessions and live
sessions
lots and lots of detail but just like
you don't learn
to ride a bike by watching videos you
don't master software development
by watching videos you master it by
doing it
exactly and this program is all about
getting you doing the right things
hundreds of developers have taken this
course because it works
but you need to do the work so just
watching a lecture and watching it with
intention
is 100% different it's a completely
different thing
so do it with the intention to learn
take notes and practice
so you need to complete all lectures
all of them all of them and it is your
practice
so follow the instructions and complete
all challenges as well
Mike and I will review all your
challenges one by one
and will provide feedback to you exactly
and every time you complete a lecture
don't forget to press
the complete button and also to submit
your challenge solutions to GitHub
exactly if you complete the lectures in
order
and you solve the challenges you will
get invited to mentoring sessions with
us
we are here to help you but we cannot do
the work for you
so if you do the work you get the
results
exactly and of course during the
lectures a lot of questions will come up
so you need to ask questions about the
lectures that's how you're gonna get the
most
of this program you need to interact
with us because we're here to help you
so you'll find guidelines to ask
questions to ask good questions
so don't skip this section you need to
go one by one and you need to read it
exactly one by one in order
so you get the most of this program
you'll also learn
from answers to thousands of questions
from the students
you have access to all of them so you'll
see how people
like you are leveling up for example
let's search for Core Data we have
lectures about Core Data
and there are threads and threads and
threads about Core Data
from other students from questions
that's it so you can find here by
keyword
the topics you want to learn about but
you need to follow the lectures in order
you need to complete
all of them yes so your next step
is to read all the information in the
Start here module
in this first section read all of them
in order to make the most
of this program and of course we're here
to help
but you need to do the work we cannot do
the work for you
no so that's it it starts now
keep doing the work go through the
lectures one by one
complete them practice take notes ask
questions
and we are here to help that's it we'll
see you
in the next lecture see ya