Hi everyone, let me know in the chat if you can hear me, hey.
Ok, Mukesh, thanks.
Thanks Dan.
This time we'll cover a bigger topic, which is Crashes and Crash reports.
It's a very important and essential topic.
First we'll take a look at what app terminations are and why they happen.
We'll see what is a Crash and what is a Crash report.
We'll look at the structure of a Crash report and we'll learn how to lead such a report.
So we'll cover the theoretical part of Crashes and Crash reports today and leave the door
open for a lecture dedicated on practical examples.
So app terminations.
Well, we all strive to create beautiful and interactive apps that run smoothly on the
devices of our users.
We do our best to test them, but it's such a complex task, given the number of OS versions
we support, the different devices with different sizes and even odd features like the Mac Catalyst,
which allows running iOS apps on Macs.
And we then release these apps to our users and we realize that sometimes these apps behave
differently than what we expected or what we tested.
One major class of events where the app behaves differently or in an unpredicted way is represented
by terminations, where the operating system just comes in and stops the process that runs
our app.
And this can happen while our app is in the foreground or is the currently active app
and a Crash occurs during the execution of the AppCode.
From the user's point of View, this sounds like I was doing X and the app suddenly closed.
That's how they see this.
Terminations can also happen when the app, our app is in the background.
So another app is the active app.
And this can happen for a number of reasons.
Again, if we look at it from the user's point of View, it will look like this.
I was running an app, I switched to another app and when I switched back, all my input
was lost and the app reset to the home screen or whatever the Main screen is.
That's how users see it.
What we know, behind doors, the operating system just killed our app.
And this is worse, especially if, like I said here, input is lost.
So if the user was entering some text or note or something else and that data is lost, that's
pretty bad.
So these terminations are a part of the app life cycle.
When the system stops your process, you can significantly reduce terminations by fixing
bugs and lowering the overall app Resource consumption.
However, terminations are expected and you cannot fully eliminate them.
The system uses terminations to prioritize the resources needed to keep the foreground
user experience fluid.
When the system terminates your app, your app must relaunch the next time a user activates.
And since a relaunch is much slower than just bringing an app from background to foreground
or reactivating it, it results in a worse user experience.
That's why we try to avoid terminations as much as possible.
Let's see what the Main reasons for app terminations.
First, aborts.
An abort happens when your process calls the abort function.
This commonly occurs when your app encounters uncut exceptions or failed assert calls, often
to a framework that your app uses.
An abort makes use of the SIGABORT signal and please note that aborts are Crashes.
Another type of app termination are memory limit terminations.
On iOS, the system attempts to provide foreground apps with as much memory as possible.
If your app attempts to use more memory than the system can provide, the system terminates
it.
Next, bad access.
A bad access termination happens when your app attempts to access invalid memory.
For example, by dereferencing Null pointers, as you see here in an Objective-C example,
we were using a property that's weak linked, weak referenced.
If we use it later and that variable was deallocated, when trying to dereference the pointer, so
the MyArray pointer to the Array, we get a Crash.
Another example is accessing an Array's element with an index out of bounds.
Again, we have an Objective-C Array and empty Array and if we try to access the element
with index one, we also get a bad access Crash or termination.
And I mentioned the Crash because bad access terminations are actually Crashes.
Next, illegal instructions happen when your app attempts to execute an instruction that
the system cannot interpret.
An example on Intel CPUs, like Intel Max, watchOS, tvOS, is force unwrapping an optional
with a new value.
This is illegal and the system just cannot recover from this because it cannot execute
this instruction.
So it will Crash and illegal instruction terminations are Crashes.
Another reason for an app termination comes from the watchdog and for those of you who
haven't used or haven't heard of the watchdog before, the watchdog is just a system, a part
of the operating system that monitors launch times and app responsiveness and just terminates
unresponsive apps.
Usually an app timeout happens when your app takes too long to launch, suspend or resume
and it results in a termination with the eight bad foot Error code that you see here.
And that's usually indicative of your app getting stuck at launch.
Currently, the timeout limit is 20 seconds, but it may change in Future OS versions.
And we remember it used to be 10 seconds, a few OS versions back.
So be careful about this.
Also note that many users will not wait these 20 seconds, so they will just quit your app
before the limit is hit and you won't actually see an app timeout.
So just measure your app launch time consistently.
Also note that this happens on iOS.
So for instance, on macOS, there's no app launch limit.
Another type of app termination is memory pressure.
This is very similar to the memory limit termination, just that in this case it happens in the background.
Because as we know on iOS and watchOS as part of the normal app lifecycle, the system terminates
apps when it needs more memory than currently available.
And the system most often terminates apps in the background when the foreground or the
active app needs more memory.
You can reduce the frequency of memory pressure terminations by reducing your memory footprint
when going to background or suspending your app.
And because you cannot remove all memory pressure terminations, it's a very good idea to implement
a proper state restoration as recommended by Apple to provide a fluid user experience.
This is just because if you hit this termination, when the user restarts your app, all their
data will be preserved and ideally they will be restored on the same screen that they used
to be before the app got closed.
So that's very smooth for the user.
Another type of background app termination is a Task timeout.
The system allows your app to continue executing in the background after the user has placed
the app in the background, through the use of the BeginBackgroundTask API.
But if your app does not finish its work in the allocated time, the system will terminate
it with the task timeout reason.
So make sure to finish in the allocated time, whatever that is, it depends on the OS, and
call and BackgroundTask, because if you don't, you'll definitely hit the timeout.
And the last of the most common reasons for app terminations is the File lock, which happens
when your app continues to hold the lock on a shared File held in your app group when
the user puts your app in the background.
The system performs termination to avoid blocking on a lock that your app may never release.
So you can avoid this by using the BeginBackgroundTask API to finish writing in the File and then
just unlocking.
That's very important, so you can complete whatever write operation you began before
going to background, because there's no other way to unlock that File.
For instance, like writing in a CoreData Database.
So you just ask for extra time from the system to the BeginBackgroundTask and BackgroundTask
APIs, and you finish the writing operation, and that's it.
That's how you avoid this type of termination.
So when mentioning these app termination reasons, we mentioned some of them are Crashes.
So now we want to focus on the topic of Crashes and see what is a Crash.
Well, a Crash is a sudden termination of your app when it attempts to do something that's
not allowed.
So what's not allowed?
Well, sometimes it's impossible for the CPU to execute code.
And an example would be like the CPU cannot divide by zero because it just doesn't know
how to do it.
Or sometimes the operating system is enforcing some policy.
The operating system will preserve the user experience by killing your app if it takes
too long to launch or if it's using too much memory.
Sometimes the programming language you're using is trying to prevent a failure and will
trigger a Crash.
For example, when a Swift Array or an NSArray is trying to go outside the arrayed bounds,
like we've shown in the previous example of accessing an index out of bounds, this will
Result in crashing and halting the process.
Or you as a developer might be trying to prevent a failure.
So for instance, if you're designing an API like this do something function with the parameter
and you assert to one of the mechanisms, like assert precondition or fatal Error, that this
parameter cannot be nil.
So your API do something does not know how to handle nil values.
You can mark this to one of the instructions I mentioned and if somebody calls this API
with the nil value, it will Result in a Crash, which is not that bad because you want to
make it clear to your clients that this API cannot be used with the nil.
And I know some of you might wonder, okay, if you don't support nil values, then why
don't you use a non-optional value type?
Well, sometimes if you need to conform to some interface, you might need to support
the optional.
So it's just an example.
Don't take it literally.
Okay.
So we've talked about the reasons why the system will Crash your app and whenever an
app Crashes, the system will generate a report which is called a Crash report describing
the device type, OS and other circumstances of the Crash.
They help us understand how and why the Crash happened.
And a Crash report is just a plain text File with the.Crash extension that contains
a detailed log of an app state when it crashed, making it a crucial Resource to identifying
the problem before attempting to fix it.
So what does a Crash report look like?
Well, the information in the report is grouped in a few sections.
So we'll try to look at each of these sections and see what's in there.
I have a few Crashes here or parts of Crashes, which I'm going to use to the following examples.
So I'll try to explain how I got each one and what's in each of these files.
But if it's unclear, just let me know.
So this first example is an app Crash which I generated by making some changes to the
EssentialFeed use case repository and forcing a Crash in the SceneDelegate will connect
to function by force unwrapping an optional.
So that's the Crash report and we can see a few sections here.
So this first section is called the header and it has various information which we'll
take a look at in a second.
Then we have another section called the exception information.
And there are a few fields here describing the exception.
And by the way, this does not refer to a language exception, so it's not a Swift or an objective
see exception is actually an operating system exception, which is different.
And then we see the culprit.
So the threat that triggered the Crash or crashed on and then we have the backtraces
which will also cover.
The state of the CPU registers.
And the binary Images.
So that's the overall structure and we'll go field by field.
So Crash report begins with the header section that describes the environment Crash occurred
in the fields in the header section.
So this section can't contain the following information, but no single Crash report contains
all the following fields.
First there's the incident identifier.
This is a unique identifier for the Crash report.
So two reports never share the same identifier.
The next field is the Crash reported key.
This is an anonymized per device identifier.
So two reports for the same device contain identical values.
Note that this identifier is reset when erasing the device.
Instead of the Crash reporter key that's available for AppStore builds or AppStore build Crashes
on TestFlight builds, we'll have another ID which is called a beta identifier, which
is again a unique identifier for the combination of the device and vendor of the crashed application.
So you can either have one or the other.
Next there's the hardware Model, which is the specific device Model that the app was
running on.
If you haven't seen this format, there are resources from Apple which contains almost
all the devices and their corresponding hardware Model.
This iPhone 12,8 represents an iPhone SE 2.
Next there's the process and the process field contains the executable name for the process
that crashed and this matches the CF Bundle executable value in the app information List.
The number in the brackets is the process ID.
Then comes the path, which is the location of the executable on disk.
So if we scroll here, we see the path to the EssentialApp binary on our device.
And if this was a macOS Crash, some of the paths, some of the components in the path
might be replaced with placeholders to protect the user's privacy.
Then we have the identifier, which is the CF BundleIdentifier of the process that crashed.
And if the process does not have a CF BundleIdentifier, if the binary does not have a
BundleIdentifier, this field is either the process name or just a placeholder value.
Then the version, which is the version of the process that crashed.
And it's a concatenation of the app's CF Bundle version and CF Bundle short version
String, which both are set to the Info.plist.
On some Crashes, we can have another field called AppStore tools.
And this is just the version of Xcode used to compile your app's Bitcode and to thin
your app to device specific variants.
And for instance, for Xcode 12, 13.1, this would look like this, the build ID.
We can also have an app variant field, which is the specific variant of your app produced
by app thinning.
And one example might look like this.
So it contains three values separated by columns, and the first value, the one, is an internal
system value, which isn't really useful when Debugging a Crash.
The next value, the second value is the name of the thinning variant.
And this variant represents a class of devices with similar characteristics such as screen
scale, memory class, metal GPU, family, and so on.
So the thinning variant's name does not indicate the exact hardware Model.
So you might see a value in the hardware Model and another value in the app variant because
the class might be different.
Actually, more devices can make up the same class.
And in this example, the class is an iPhone 10, 6.
And the third value here is the variant of the OS version.
In this example, this is 12.2, indicating that this variant targets iOS devices running
iOS 12 or higher.
Next we have code type, which is the CPU architecture of the process that crashed.
And this value can be ARM64, as in this example, ARM, or the latest macOS processors, x86
for the Intel-based CPUs.
Next Role is the task Role assigned to the process at the time of termination.
And again, this field is not that useful when analyzing the Crash report.
So I usually skip it.
The parent process, which is the name of the process and the ID that launched the Crash
process, in our case, it was the launchd process.
And the coalition, which is the name of the process coalition containing the app.
Process coalitions track Resource usage among groups of related processes, such as an operating
system process supporting a specific API functionality in the app.
Most processes, including app extensions, form their own coalition.
And we have the Date and time of the Crash and the Date and time of the launch of the
app.
So using these two values, we can compute the duration of the session.
In our case, very short duration, just a few milliseconds.
And finally, the OS version, which is the version of the operating system, including
the build number on which the Crash occurred.
The next section is the exception information section.
Every Crash report contains exception information.
This information section tells you how the process terminated, but it may not fully explain
why.
This information is important, but often overlooked.
And again, as I mentioned, this does not refer to language exceptions thrown by an API, but
rather to OS exceptions.
So the following fields here provide information about the exception, but again, no single
Crash reports will contain all the following fields.
First, there is the exception type, which contains the name of the Mac exception, in
our case, XCBreakpoint, that terminated the process and the name of the BSD termination
signal, in our case, SIGTRAP.
There are multiple values that you can see here for the exception type and for the BSD
signal, and we'll try to cover this in a Future lecture.
Next, we have exception codes, which are processor-specific information about the exception encoded into
one or more 64-bit hexadecimal numbers.
Typically, this field isn't present because the OS presents the information as human-readable
information in the other fields in the section.
But we have it here.
Next, we have an exception subtype and exception Message fields, which, as you can see, are
not part of our Crash report here.
But we have a different example where we can see those.
This is a part of another Crash, and we can see a different exception type, xccrash and
a SIGABORT signal, and this time we have an exception subtype, which is a human-readable
description of the exception codes, which is LaunchHang, and the exception Message contains
additional human-readable information extracted from the exception codes, and in our case,
the extension took too much time to initialize.
This is actually a watchdog Crash from an app extension that took too long to launch,
and that's how it's gonna look.
Back to our Crash here.
The next field is exceptionNode, and this exceptionNode contains additional information
that isn't specific to one exception type.
If this field contains EXC_CORPSE_NOTIFY, as in our example, the Crash didn't originate from
a hardware trap, either because the process was explicitly terminated by the OS or the
process called Abort.
Another value which you might see here is simulated.
The exceptionNode contains simulated, again, this is not a Crash.
The process didn't Crash, but the OS might have subsequently requested the termination
of the process.
And another value which you might see here is non-fatal condition.
Also for cases that are not Crashes, where the process didn't terminate because the issue
that created the Crash report wasn't fatal.
Next the termination reason contains exit reason information specified when the OS terminates
a process.
Key OS components, both inside and outside of a process, terminate a process upon encountering
a fatal Error and record a reason in this field.
Examples of the information you can find in this field are messages about an invalid code
signature, a missing dependent library or accessing privacy sensitive information without
the purpose String in the Info.plist.
And finally, you can either see triggered by Thread, like in our case, or you can see
the crashed Thread and it can be 01.
So either one or the other.
And they basically flag the Thread that caused the Crash or on which the exception originated.
The next section is a diagnostics messages section, which again, our Crash here doesn't
have.
But we can use another Crash.
And we refer to this part.
So the OS sometimes includes additional diagnostic information in the Crash report.
This information uses a variety of formats depending on the reason of the Crash and isn't
present in every Crash report, as you just saw.
In this first example, framework Error messages occurring just before the process terminated
appear in the application specific information field.
In our example, the dispatch framework logged an Error about incorrect use of a DispatchQueue.
Another example, the app specific information reveals an index out of range Error when accessing
a Swift Array.
And another example is a watchdog termination, where the termination
description field contains the reason why the watchdog trigger.
In our case, because our application exhausted real time allowance of the 20 seconds I mentioned,
which is listed at 19.97.
So if we return to our original Crash report, which we used, we can see that this Crash
does not have any diagnostic messages.
And this can happen because sometimes the OS might be protecting privacy sensitive information
and just removing or not adding this part in a Crash report.
We will ignore this kernel triage because it usually does not appear in Crash reports
and does not contain any valuable information.
And we'll look at the backtraces section.
The backtrace section contains the trace for each of the Threads that was running at the
time of the Crash.
So in our case, we had eight Threads.
So from 0 to 7, eight Threads running and we have the backtrace for each of these Threads.
So we basically get the documentation of all the code running when the process terminated.
These backtraces you see here are very similar to what you see when you pause the process
with the debugger.
So let's do that really quickly just to get a feeling.
So if we run the EssentialApp, so I pause the debugger on this entry line in the will
connect to API from the SceneDelegate.
And over here, you see the first Thread, Thread one, which is the Main Thread.
And we see all the backtrace starting from the app start on entry 26 up to our specific
line of code.
So going through the UIApplication Main and all the other calls that were involved, all
the specific function calls that were involved up to the point where we set the breakpoint.
And if you are willing to do the comparison, you'll see that my stack trace here is the
exact same stack trace.
So that's how stack traces are represented in Crash reports.
They contain all the function calls from the entry point.
So from the start function to each of the function it involves up until your, your explicit
code.
So you can see here a bunch of system frameworks and then our own code.
And we get these stack trace for each of the running Threads.
So yeah, I was mentioning this entry point again, like the start function, then we invoke
the Main from the EssentialApp.
Then UIApplication Main, your application run, and then the RunLoop starts.
So it's kind of the, the common entry point for each of the iOS apps or most of the iOS
apps we have.
In this backtrace section, we can have a last exception backtrace, which again in our case
is missing, but we have it in a different Crash.
So before the Thread zero stack trace and the other Threads, we have another stack trace,
which is the last exception backtrace.
Crashes that are caused by a language exception include an additional backtrace, the last
exception backtrace, as I said, located before the first Thread.
The first line of each backtrace with the Thread number and the Thread name.
So if we go back to our initial Crash report, we see the Thread number zero and the name
is missing because for privacy reasons, Crash reports delivered to the Crash organizer in
Xcode don't contain the Thread names, only the Thread number.
So again, in our example, we have the backtraces from Threads zero to seven, so eight Threads
in total.
And the Crash Thread is Thread zero, which is running on the MainQueue and identified
as the app's Main Thread.
After the Thread number, each line here of a backtrace represents a stack frame in it.
Each column represents different information.
First, so zero, one, two are the stack frame numbers.
Stack frames are in calling order where frame zero is the function that was executing at
the time the execution halted and frame one is the function that called the function in
frame zero and frame two is the function that called the function at frame one and so on.
You see the point.
Then there's the binary name containing the binary where that function was coming from.
Then some address, which is the address of the machine instruction that is executing
for frame zero in each backtrace, this is the address of the machine instruction executing
on a Thread when the process terminated.
For other stack frames, this is the address of the first machine instruction that executes
after control returns to that stack frame.
Then we have the name of the function.
So in our case is the SceneDelegate Scene will connect to options.
And since this is a fully symbolicated Crash report, the name of the function appears.
And by the way, we'll talk about symbolication in a Future lecture.
But just to simplify it, symbolication is the process of translating memory addresses
into a human readable or developer readable format that contains File names, line numbers,
function names.
So something we developers can understand as opposed to just the memory addresses that
are written in an unsymbolicated Crash report, which is really unusable for us.
Next we have a byte offset, which in this case is plus 2288.
And that's the offset from the function's entry point to the current instruction in
the function.
And at the end we have the File name SceneDelegate.Swift and the line number 65.
And again, this appears because this is a fully symbolicated Crash report.
In some situations, the File name might be missing and be replaced by compiler generated.
And this happens when the compiler creates the code for that frame and that code isn't
in your source files.
But if this is the top frame in the Crash Thread, look at the preceding stack frames
for clues.
Or another thing you can see here is the line number being zero.
If the line number of a source File is zero, this means that the backtrace doesn't Map
to a specific line of code in the original File.
This is because the compiler optimized the code and one example is inlining functions
and the code executing at the time of the Crash doesn't correspond to an exact line
in the original code.
So when symbolicating, there is no line that corresponds to the current instruction.
So you will see a zero value.
But you can always use the other frames as a reference.
And you can use all these backtraces to understand what your app was doing at the time of the
Crash.
So you see all the functions that called each other or what all the Threads were doing.
If any Thread was doing something interesting or out of the ordinary, you can see it here.
And we'll talk about some strategies about how to analyze these backtraces.
For now, you just need to understand the format of the information here.
And we can look at the remaining sections.
The first section is this Thread state that contains the CP registers and their values
at the time of the Crash.
Identifying the Thread state is an advanced topic that requires understanding of the application
binary interface or ABI for the operating system.
So there's no point in going into this detail for now, as it's very, very complex and you
have a much bigger chance of fixing the Crash by looking at all the other information and
by starting to analyze the values in each CP register and trying to disassemble the
code.
And finally, there's a binary Images section.
This contains all the code loaded in the process at the time of termination, such as your app
executable, which is on the first line, the EssentialApp, or system frameworks like the
UIKit core, core Foundation, graphics services, Foundation, and so on.
This List contains the component from the preceding example.
And each line will contain a different binary.
Let's see what this format is.
And by the way, the format we're looking at is the same for iOS, watchOS, and tvOS.
So first, we have an address range, which is the binary Images address range within
the process.
The first address is the binary's load address.
Then there's the binary name, like EssentialApp, the CPU architecture, ARM64, a build
UUID, like the one I just selected, that uniquely identifies the binary Image.
And we can use these to locate the corresponding DSYM when we symbolicate.
And we'll see how we can do that in another lecture, like I said.
And finally, the path to the binary.
So pretty long path, but in the end, we get the path to our EssentialApp or to the core
Foundation framework under system library frameworks.
So as I mentioned, this is the format used for iOS.
If you want to see a slight variation of the macOS format, I'll use another Crash report.
And we'll see a similar section here.
The format is very similar, so it also has an address range.
Within the name of the binary, a star or a plus, depending on if this binary is a system
binary or not, the identifier and the path which might be obfuscated or just parts of
the path being replaced with placeholders to preserve privacy.
So pretty similar.
And you might have a version information here if that's available, like in this case.
The core Foundation version 6.9.
Back to our Crash.
Let's talk about some general ways on how to read these Crash reports.
So when analyzing a Crash report, read all the information in all the sections.
As you formulate a hypothesis about the cause of a Crash, ask questions about what the data
in each section of the Crash says to refine or disprove the hypothesis.
Some clues are explicitly captured by fields in the Crash report.
But others are subtle and require you to uncover them by noticing small details.
Performing a total analysis of a Crash report and formulating a hypothesis takes time and
practice to develop, but it's a critical tool for making your app more robust.
Find a starting point from the Crash report's information to think about the Crash from
the user's perspective to refine the hypothesis.
For example, look at the frame in the backtrace that may indicate a particular feature of
the app in use.
And you can think about how other information in the Crash report relates to that feature.
Also if you have many Crash reports, try to organize them into groups to clarify the source
of a Crash.
If many Crash reports contain the exact same information, the problem likely is consistently
reproducible and the common details in the Crash reports help you isolate the issue.
If you have Crash reports that all appear different, but you suspect the underlying
cause is the same, pay attention to any detail that looks unusual.
Place any Crash reports with unusual details in their own group.
By grouping Crash reports based on similar and dissimilar details, you sometimes uncover
insights into the cause of a Crash that aren't visible when looking at Crash reports individually.
If you have multiple Crash reports that are similar, use the header information to help
understand the scope of the problem and to target the specific operating system version
and devices, you need to reproduce the problem.
Some questions that can help refine your hypothesis about the Crashes are, does the Crash occur
in multiple versions of the app or just one?
So you look at multiple Crash reports and see what the version says.
Does the Crash occur on multiple versions of the operating system?
So you take a look at the operating system over multiple Crashes and you draw your conclusion.
If it's limited to maybe iOS 15 only, or if it spans across multiple OS versions, that's
useful information.
Other information is, did the Crash originate from your Main app or from one of your app
extensions?
So for this you can use the process and path fields to see where the Crash happened.
Is the Crash from only one type of device, such as an iPad but not an iPhone?
For this you can check the hardware Model and see what the distribution across devices
is.
Is the Crash from a TestFlight beta of your app or from an AppStore version?
Then you look at the Crash reporter key or the beta identifier key and you can immediately
see which type of Crash it is.
What device Model did the app Crash on?
And how much Testing did you do on devices with similar capabilities?
For this you can use the app variant or the hardware Model.
Do multiple users experience the Crash or only a small number of unique users?
For this you can use the Crash reporter key or a beta identifier to see if some users
get more than one Crash or if this is sporadically happening to a user maybe once or twice.
And another important question is, how long was the app running before it crashed?
So you can use the Date of the Crash and the launch time to compute the session duration.
And if you see a long session like a few hours or a few days then you might have a hypothesis
about why the Crash happened.
Or if you see a very short duration again you can draw the conclusion that something
is happening during your app launch.
So that's how we look at the header information.
We also want to take a look at the exception information, because every Crash report records
exception information that shows the exact mechanism by which the app's process terminated.
Termination is always the last step in the Error handling, but it starts when an unrecoverable
condition occurs in the app or the framework it uses.
For example, the app may request termination directly, such as calling abort, so you might
see an abort on the frame 0 of the Crash Thread.
But that's not the cause, that's just the last step.
As a different example, the OS may terminate the process to enforce a system policy, such
as a watchdog, that ensures the app's responsiveness.
Exception information narrows the sources for the Crash you're analyzing and helps
identify the clues you look for in other sections of the Crash report.
So try to answer the following questions.
What is the exception type?
What Thread triggered the Crash?
What's the relationship between the frames of the Crash Thread and the exception type?
For certain types of problems, a Crash report may contain additional diagnostic information
between the exception information section and the backtracing section.
This information is directly related to an exception type.
Based on the exception type, what is the Crash due to an uncut language exception, like in
our case here?
And we can see an uncut NSUnknownKeyException.
If so, what additional information about the API throwing the exception is in the Message?
Well, we can see the extra information that for my class setValueForUndefinedKey, this
class is not keyValueCodingCompliant.
Again, based on the exception type, is the Crash due to a memory access issue?
That's another important question to ask.
And if there is an application-specific information field, what does it contain?
Is there a specific API named in that Message, like we just saw?
And where to use that API in your code?
Or if you got a termination description, is there a termination description field and
that's indicating something?
The backtraces in a Crash report show the exact methods executing at the time of the
Crash.
As a starting point, look at the Crash Thread as well as the last exception backtrace, if
we have one.
And try to answer the following questions.
For the Crash Thread, what function is this Thread serving to the app?
Is it the Main Thread or another Thread with a specific purpose?
Was a language exception thrown?
And what does the last exception backtrace show?
You look at these backtraces.
What parts of the app use this Thread and the function that appear in the backtrace?
And what mix of binaries in your app and the system frameworks are in the backtrace?
Even if the functions in the backtrace aren't ones you directly call, they contain key clues.
So like in this example, you don't see the EssentialApp entry only at the entry level
on AppDelegate and that's it.
And from there, there's only calls to system binaries, but there's still important information.
One example is in another Crash that happened and we got only the last exception backtrace
here.
And again, we can see that except for stack frame 14 with migrate app, all the other binaries
and functions are system functions.
But the Crash is due to an invalid popover configuration.
Frames 3 and 4 provide a clue that this Crash relates to presenting a ViewController, UI
Presentation controller.
And if we look at frame 2, we can see that it's actually a UI popover Presentation controller.
This information narrows down the parts of your app's code to focus on.
So we'll just look for the parts that are using UI popover Controllers.
And even if there's no specific AppCode in the last exception backtrace, we can still
have some idea about where to look.
Back to our original Crash report, which we've shown.
I want to mention that you can frequently determine the purpose of a Thread based on
the bottom frames in the Thread's backtrace.
So an app's Main Thread has NSApplication or UIApplication Main in the bottom frames.
And other Threads created to the dispatch framework have start_wqthread in the bottom frames.
As we look closer at the Crash Thread's backtrace, consider whether your app appears in a coherent
state that matches your expectations about how your app functions.
So again, looking at Thread 0, should the code from the app be running on this specific
Thread?
Is the Crash Thread a background Thread or the Main Thread?
And an important question is, do any of the backtraces show the app manipulating UI elements
on any Thread except the Main Thread?
Because as we know, UIKit is pretty strict about setting UIKit object values from background
Threads.
And in order to test this more thoroughly, you can use the Main Thread checker from the
Scheme Editor to run the app in debug with this Main Thread checker that will signal
every situation where you're trying to set a UIKit property from a background Thread.
So that can be very useful.
And another question is relating to APIs with Completion handlers.
So if you see an API with a Completion handler listed in these backtraces, does the API guarantee
the specific queue of that Completion handler?
So you should be checking that.
And check if the code call is on that expected queue or not.
And in addition to the backtrace for the Crash Thread or the language exception, other Threads
backtraces provide additional but more subtle clues about the Crash.
So in some types of Crashes, the Crash Threads backtrace doesn't contain the source of the
issue, like in the case of the watchdog termination or memory access Crashes, memory access Crashes.
And finally, you should take a look at the binary Images and make sure all the binaries,
at least your binaries, are listed there.
So if you have any frameworks that your app loads, make sure they appear here.
And if you're investigating a watchdog termination and you have a high number of frameworks inside
your app, that can be an indication of why your app's launch time takes longer.
Thank you.
So I know this might sound a bit more theoretical, like I said in the beginning, but it's really
important to have this foundational knowledge before we try to look at more, I know, specific
or concrete examples, just to understand everything or most of the information that's available
through these reports, because sometimes we just don't know how to read them.
So at least for me, this was a big improvement when I started to understand the information
in Crash reports that gave me a lot of room to maneuver when trying to deal with Crashes
and Crash reports.
So we'll continue with another lecture soon.
Thanks everyone.
Bye.