Hi everyone and welcome. We'll continue our series by taking a deep dive into the
Xcode build settings and their hidden secrets. So let's do it. We'll explain why can both project
and target set the same settings and which one to use depending on the case. We'll explore the
available build settings viewer styles. We'll go through the conventions used by the build settings
editor. We'll recap from last time how Xcode resolves build settings and we'll see some
concrete examples. We'll go through the accepted values and features of build settings.
We'll try to explain how to use user-defined build settings.
We'll see how we can access build settings from the CommandLine
and we'll build a few examples of using build settings to our advantage.
And we'll wrap it up with the Q&A.
So, what's a build setting? As we remember from last time, it's a property you can apply to your
Xcode targets to configure aspects of how they are built.
There are many build settings within Xcode. Many are there since older versions like Xcode 4
but with each version, new settings are added while others are deplicated or removed.
You can always find a comprehensive List in Apple Docs at the link I provided.
Some of these settings are also available through a more simplified user-defined build
settings. But in the end, they are still controllable through the build settings editor.
So, changing one will also change the other since they're stored and loaded from the same
place, which is the PBX profile or some configuration File.
Some examples of that are the project and target deployment targets.
So, the project deployment targets. The target deployment targets.
The target identity, like the BundleIdentifier version, the target development assets,
or the target signing. Not the capabilities which are handled through the entitlements.py List File.
There are two ways to manage build settings. One is through the Xcode build settings editor
and the others through configuration settings files, also known as xcconfig.
The Xcode build settings editor is the one that can be used to manage the build settings.
The Xcode build settings editor and the others through configuration settings files, also known as xcconfig.
We'll cover this topic in a separate lecture.
So, why can both project and target set the same settings?
Well, generally, project-level settings are used to share settings between targets and avoid
application. They're not used directly, only when the resolver cannot find explicit target-level
settings, thus falling back to project-level settings. On the other hand, target-level
settings are the most explicit form of settings and are there for us to customize each target
in any way we need. Our recommendation is to avoid setting both with the same value,
because it's unnecessary and confusing. So, if a setting applies to all the target,
that setting at the project level and perhaps override it only on the targets that need a
different value. If the setting applies only to one target, then, of course, you'll set it
on the target level. In the Xcode build settings viewer, there are a few options that change how
this View looks. Let's see what they are. So, the default mode is basic settings,
which means show only the basic settings and the Combined viewer, which shows the
the effective value of build settings for a target or project.
In my opinion, the Combined style doesn't make it clear where does the Result value
for each setting come from, but it has one big advantage. It allows us to inspect really long
values of settings, like, for instance, the run path search paths, which is a bit long.
A clear way is to use the all filter with the level setting.
This way, in my opinion, we can look at all the settings, which can be intimidating, I know,
and we see exactly all the other levels that have a set value for the setting,
so we understand how this Result column is computed.
I'd like to mention that there's another filter which is customized, and this will
filter only the settings that have an explicit value at the current level, but I'll be using
the all for now.
Independent of the View style we use, there are a few conventions that Xcode uses to reflect
the state of the settings and the way we edit them. First of all, a bold setting name and
a box around the bold setting with the bolded value indicates that there's an explicit value.
There's a screenshot here. We can also see it in Xcode,
like these supported platforms.
Another convention is to use spaces to delimit items in String or path lists. For example,
our run path search paths use spaces to delimit between items. We'll see what this inherited
means in a minute.
To specify an item containing white space, you must enclose it with question marks. So,
if I want an app name that has spaces, I need to use the question marks. Quotation marks, sorry.
To inspect a long value, we can hover over it, and we can see that it's a long value.
To inspect a long value, we can hover over it. So, we see the full definition.
Like in this case.
In this case, no matter which viewer we use, each setting will have a collapsible
carrot that shows extra rows for each configuration. By default, if all the
configurations use the same value, these rows are collapsed. If there are differences,
they will be expanded. In our example project, the buildActiveArchitectureOnly has a
different resolve value for the debug and the release configuration. So, by default, you see
these two rows expanded. On the other hand, for the base SDK, since both configurations
use the same value, the rows are collapsed. But we can always go to the base SDK, and we'll see
the carrot here, and we can expand it. To delete settings, explicit settings,
we can use the delete key. This will remove the current level setting. So, if we are looking at
target build settings, it will remove the target explicit setting. If we're looking at the project
build settings, of course it will remove the project level setting. Let's recap how Xcode
resolves build settings. So, before each build or any other action, the system must resolve
all the build settings for each target that is built. Build settings are resolved using
the fallback system where the resolver looks for a value from higher to lower priority levels
until it finds one or ends up with the platform default. In this graphical representation,
as well as in the Xcode build settings tab, priority decreases from left to right.
First, we have the target explicit settings, which override any other setting.
If we were to set a target configuration File, this will override all the settings,
except for the ones we set explicitly on the target. Next to the right is the project explicit
settings that are used when target settings are missing. Otherwise, they are overwritten by
target settings. Again, if we have a project configuration File, it will only override the
platform defaults. And with the lowest priority are the platform defaults. So, if all the other
levels are missing, the resolver will use these values. Now, back to Xcode.
And looking at the build settings for the EssentialFeed target using the levels viewer,
we can see the following columns from left to right. First, there's the setting column.
This is where each setting will appear, usually grouped with similar settings under
a united group. So, in this case, the base SDK is in the architectures group together with
architectures and supported platforms. Next, we have the resolved column,
which shows the value of the setting that's being resolved by Xcode for the selected target.
All the settings will have a value in this column, even if it's an empty value.
Like it's in this case for the excluded architecture.
Next, we have the EssentialFeed project level that shows the settings that have been explicitly
set for the current project. And the last column is macro as default. This is the
platform that's currently set for the selected target. This column contains the default setting
values. Remember, the resolver will go from left to right until it finds an explicit value or
fall back to the platform default. Let's take a few examples.
Let's take a few examples. First of all, base SDK.
The resolved value is macOS. But we can see that the EssentialFeed target
has no set value. So, the resolver moves to the project level setting where it finds macOS
bold and with the box around it. So, it's an explicit value. That's why the resolved value
is macOS. In this case, the platform default value, which is no SDK, is never used.
Next, let's look at the buildActiveArchitectureOnly setting.
We can see that it has different values for the debug and the release configurations.
That's why the rows are expanded. The resolved value for debug is yes, while the resolved value
for release is no. There are no target explicit values. So, the resolver moves to the project
level, where we see that the debug configuration has a setting of the value yes. There's no setting
for the release configuration. So, for the release configuration, the resolver will move to the
platform default, which is no. So, that's how we get the resolved values of yes for the debug and
no for release. Let's also look at supported platforms. We see the resolved value is iOS and
macOS, which is the value that we see set explicitly on the EssentialFeed target.
This overrides the platform default value, which is macOS.
Having a value with multiple elements is possible because this supported platforms
setting uses a String List value. So, we can add more than one platform.
Now, let's do some live editing. Let's edit the supported platforms.
The values displayed are iOS and macOS, but when we try to edit them and use other, we see
a List that contains macOSX, iPhoneOS, and iPhone simulator. These are the values used by Xcode and
written in the project File, while iOS and macOS are just predefined values shown only by the Xcode
UI. Let's add watchOS and watch simulator. You can see the resolved values now, iOS, macOS, and watchOS.
To understand what the actual change on the project level is, let's check the git diff.
So, we see two changes to the supported platforms field. As you might remember from last time,
one for the support platform, and the other for the support platform, and the other for the support
changes to the supported platforms field. As you might remember from last time, one for the debug
configuration of the target and one for the List configuration, where both of the values we added
are changed.
And I've reverted the change, so we can do another one.
Let's edit the deployment target.
Currently, we see there's a project level setting to iOS 14. I want to make an explicit
target level setting of iOS 13. And we immediately notice that the resolved value is now iOS 13,
overriding the project level setting and even the platform default, which is iOS 15.2.
Again, I'm going to check
the git diff. And I notice two values were added because we never had an explicit target level
setting. They were added to the debug and release configurations. Now, back to Xcode,
I mentioned we can use the delete key to delete an explicit target or project level setting. So,
if I hit delete now, I see the resolved value is back to iOS 14. And if I check the git diff,
there's no change. Next up, I want to play with Swift treat warning as Error setting,
which can be really useful.
Really useful. Let's set an explicit project level setting to yes.
Now, I want to make sure that all my targets are using this new value. So, I can use a hidden
feature of Xcode where if I hold command and click multiple targets, I'll get a View where
I see the resolved value for each of the selected targets. So, in this case,
treat warnings as Errors is yes for all my targets inside my project, which is what I wanted.
Also, I want to check the git diff. And I see, as always, two new values added because they were
never set. Now, back to Xcode, if I tap on delete, nothing happens because I have an explicit project
level setting and I'm using the target build settings. So, I'm actually deleting any potential
setting on the target level, which doesn't exist. To delete this explicit project level setting,
I need to go to the project build settings. And now, I hit delete and I see the value goes away.
And if I return to my target, I see the values back to the default. And if I check the git diff,
there are no diffs. So, I'm in the original state. Another example would be to
use the EssentialFeed iOS Tests and play with the code signing.
So, I can see the code signing identity is explicitly set to iOS developer.
As you might do in your projects, I want to set my release configuration to use iOS distribution.
So, I can do that. And now, let's notice a few things. First of all, the Result value
for debug is still iOS developer. But for release, we have a new value, which is iOS distribution,
as I've just explicitly said. The overall setting shows multiple values, which indicates that there
are different values resolved. Again, I'm going to use the git diff. And I see just one change,
because I actually just changed the value for the release configuration. So, I only
impacted one of the sets of settings from the PBX File.
So, let's do another one. So, I'm still going to use the Swift treat warnings as Errors.
I'm going to set the project level setting to yes. And now, let's assume an interesting case where
the essential fit target has a warning when building on the old Intel architectures,
which is I386. So, this results in a build failure. One way to fix this is to add a
different setting value for this architecture only. So, in this case, I'm going to use the
small plus icon here for both configurations and add an extra filter. So, the debug is set to yes.
And I'm going to select Intel and set the value to no. And I'm going to do the same for
my release configuration. Now, again, let's see what the resolved values are.
So, I still have a debug resolved to yes, but for the Intel architecture, the resolved value is no.
And same for the release configuration. If we check the common line, we see
the value set to yes. And then this explicit case where on architecture I386, the value is no.
This is pretty powerful.
So, I'm going to reset it again and do another example.
So, I'm going to set the project level back to yes. And this time, I'll assume that
there's a build Error, but only on the iOS platform or iOS SDK. I can also add a specific filter for
that. We're using the same plus button. This time, instead of architecture, I can choose
one of the SDKs here. And I'm going to choose any iOS SDK. And for this SDK, I'm going to set the
value to no. And I'm going to do the same for the release configuration. Again,
the resolved values are yes, except for the iOS SDK. Let's see what the diff looks like.
The first two are the same. And then we get this filter where SDK equals
iPhone iOS and a wild card. This is because I've selected any iOS platform. You can even
use a specific one. And again, I'm going to reset this.
So, each of the settings we showed and all the others,
they all allow different types of values. The potential types are as following. First, boolean
for settings like build, active architecture only or skip install. Then a String value for
settings like Swift version or code signing style, String List for supported platforms,
preprocessor macros, a path for settings like framework search paths, header search paths,
library search paths, and so on. Or an enumeration for settings like optimization level, Swift
compilation mode, linker mode, and more. Besides these default accepted value types,
we can reference other settings. Like in this example where settings name is computed using
the values of other setting one and other setting two with a space in between them. So, that's why
they are inside quotes. A real case use scenario is for the install path setting
which is computed from the local library directory setting and using the framework subfolder.
Another thing which we can do is reuse values across levels. So, this is where this inherited
variable comes into play. All the settings support the inherited variable which is resolved to any
value set by a lower level including the platform defaults. So, this is used to append rather than
replace existing definitions. For example, we can set setting name equals inherited and some
additional value. An interesting example would be if we have a setting where the platform default
is default value and on the project level we set inherited and then project value and on a target
level we also use inherited and set target value next to it. The Result value would be a merge of
all three values which is pretty useful. Again, a concrete use case is for the framework search paths
where instead of overriding the value we just append our project directory to it.
Referencing values can also provide a default in case the reference doesn't exist. So, in this case
my setting name equals build setting name with a default value in case that
build setting doesn't exist. A concrete, maybe complex example is passing some warn on long
expression type checking to the Swift flags. This is a setting we can pass to allow the compiler to
allow the compiler to highlight any expression that takes longer than the sent value which is in
milliseconds to compile. In this case we have set a default value of 200 milliseconds but we can
override it in the CI where builds are much slower. If we define a max expression checking time
value in an XC config File that would only exist on CI machines. So, for example,
we can generate it directly on the CI. When substituting or replacing a value we
can apply a bunch of transformations. These are the available transformations. We won't go through
all of them but you can see some groups. First there are identifiers. Then quotes. So, wrapping
strings in quotes. Lower or upper case. Standardized path. And some path extraction
where we can get the base name of the path directly to the File or the suffix.
Some concrete examples. First of all, Xcode pre-populates the product name with the
targetName using the C99X identifier. So, basically, what this identifier does is creates
a C identifier representation which supports extended characters.
Another example would be to set the product BundleIdentifier to com.essentialDeveloper product name
and use the Intel 1034 identifier, which is a representation suitable to use in a DNS name.
And also use the lower transformation. So, we can change that. That's the point.
We've already looked at some examples of conditionals, but to recap them,
we can set different settings depending on the SDK, on the architecture, or on the configuration.
What's interesting is we can even Combine these and set some, like, in the only active architecture,
only in the config, in the debug configuration, we can set some explicit SDK and architecture filters.
This will speed up the local builds.
At the bottom of the Build Settings Editor, there's a group called UserDefinedSettings.
Let's see what we can do here. So, we can define our own custom settings. An interesting example
is for PushNotificationsEnvironment. We can define a setting called PushNotificationsEnvironment
and we can set its value to development on the debug configuration and to production on the
release configuration. What this allows us to do is, instead of using two entitlements,
PlistFiles, to set the Apple Push Services environment, we can use just one. And at the
APNS environment key, we set a reference to our PushNotificationsEnvironment setting we just added.
So, that would resolve to development environment when we're building the debug configuration and
for the production APNS environment when we build the release configuration.
By default, when you create an Xcode project, you're going to see these two values,
two settings, MTLEnableDebugInfo and MTLFastMath. What's up with these? Well,
first of all, they are metal settings. So, for the metal framework, which are no longer needed,
but for some reason, they remained in Xcode template File. So, it still generates them.
It's okay to remove them.
If you need to use the CommandLine to access build settings, there's a
minus show build settings option you can pass to any Xcode build command, and it will print
the Xcode build command. So, if you need to use the CommandLine to access build settings,
minus show build settings option, you can pass to any Xcode build command, and it will print
all the build settings and the resolved values, like in my slide. There's an option to pass minus
JSON as well. So, instead of this formatting, you'll get a properly formatted JSON File.
This can be useful, especially on CI when you're trying to inspect and see what the resolved
settings are for one of your schemes. There's also the option to set through the CommandLine. So,
in this case, for our EssentialFeed target, we would set the architectures to arm64 and
Bitcode enable to no. Now, a few examples of how we can use build settings. So,
now, a few examples of how we can use build settings to our advantage. First, I'd like this
example of changing the Bundle name and app icon for different build flavors. So, in most projects,
we have builds that are distributed internally to our testers or maybe to some other folks in
our group and externally a different build that is sent to our AppStore users.
To be able to distinguish on a device which build we have, we can do this interesting trick where
we can set a product name for the debug configuration to be something like targetName
space dev. So, we know it's a dev build. And we can also change the asset catalog compiler,
which is basically the catalog with icons. For the debug configuration, we can set it to a different
catalog. So, the app has a different icon. Pretty useful.
So, another interesting thing to achieve is different code behavior depending on the
configuration. So, as you might know, by default, Xcode sets up a few build settings to help us
distinguish between debug and release configurations. For Swift, this is done through the Swift active
compilation conditions that is set to debug on the debug configuration. This allows our Swift code
to do dash if debug do this, dash else do something else. The equivalent for people that are using
Objective-C is GCC definitions, which, again, by default, when you create a new project with Xcode
is set to debug equals one on the debug. Again, this allows us to do a slight variation where
we use dash if debug do this, dash else do something else. This can be very useful,
but many projects abuse this feature and spread these conditional statements all across the code
base, which makes it hard to test and maintain. Our recommendation is to only use them in the
composition route, which is the most concrete and lowest level component. Make all your other
components abstract of these decisions and inject the decisions using one of the mechanisms we have
already shown in the course, like closures, DependencyInversion, and so on. Let's see
these two examples where first we have a ViewController that needs a duration for an animation,
and, of course, in the debug configuration, we want this duration to be zero because we don't
want to wait for animations. Instead of doing the conditional inside the ViewController,
we just pass this duration through a closure and configure this closure from the composition route
where we can use the conditionals. The other example on the right is creating a UI SceneConfiguration
where if you are on a debug config, we can set the Delegate class to a different
SceneDelegate. In this case, the DebuggingSceneDelegate. Another interesting use case is managing
constants on different environments. If we have different environments for our endpoints, as I'm
sure you do, staging, production, QA, and so on, you can use conditional statements to resolve these
URLs. You can do it through a simple example like I did. So, dash if debug, use this URL, otherwise
use that URL. But there's another approach using build settings. So, we're going to add a new user
defined build setting called API Domain. And for the debug configuration, we're going to set it to
a staging URL, and for the List configuration, we're going to set it to a production URL.
Then in the Info.plist File, we willSet a new key called API base URL, and we're going to use the
API Domain user defined setting we just added. This is because reading these build settings from
code is not easy, but as we remember, Info.plist already processes build settings, for example,
regarding the product name or other settings. So, it will have access to all the build settings.
And to read this API base URL value, we can use the for info dictionary key API on the Bundle class.
It's important to know that any app Bundle is easy to inspect, and the Info.plist inside it is not
encrypted. So, any value set inside can be easily accessible by anyone. So, do not Store any sensitive
data in the Info.plist. If you want to know more about security, we have a mentoring session about
it, but we can also cover it in another session. That's it. Thank you. And now it's time for a Q&A.
Any questions, anyone? Thanks, Pawan.
Hi, everyone. In the priorities, when you set a build setting, in the CommandLine,
you will override everything else, right? When you set it, yes. Let's get back to that slide.
Let's see if I can run this.
Yeah, it just overrides the target settings, and it doesn't even change the project. It's like a standalone.
It's just for that specific build. Exactly. It doesn't change anything.
Thanks for making you go through that, so it's clear now. There's another question from Bartos.
I hope I pronounced it correctly. What does the build for active architecture mean exactly?
What does the build for active architecture mean exactly? Let's look at this setting again.
Basically, it means that instead of building all the architectures that our target supports,
we're just going to build the one that's set to run on. In this case, for the EssentialFeed,
the value is set to ArchStandard, which is another variable, and it's usually ARM64 and 386.
So, those are two architectures. If we enable buildActiveArchitectureOnly
and try to use the simulator, we will only build the one that's needed for the simulator,
which is the 386. So, we're not going to build the ARM64, which we don't need in this case.
This is an optimization and results in a much faster build, because you only build one of the
architectures. As a side note, many of these settings are important and perhaps need some
digging into them. So, we're going to do another lecture on some of these build settings
and go into each one of them and see how they work. Any other questions? If not, we can wrap it up.
Thanks, everyone, and see you soon.