Hi everyone and welcome. We'll continue our series on tooling and our mini series on Crashes and Crash
reports with a practical session. Hopefully this will bring more light to past lectures we did
on a more theoretical part on Crashes and Crash reports. I know this might be a scary topic.
I remember when I was a junior developer he struggled with Crashes a lot and whenever somebody
assigned a Crash to me or I had to deal with that it was kind of an unknown territory. So
to help you with that we add to the curricula where we have already two lectures on the more
theoretical side like what's an app termination, why do they happen, how do you acquire Crash reports,
how do you symbolicate. So you see the full backtrace and this lecture today is on hands on
Crashes which happens on devices most commonly and how to approach this. So let's get into it.
The agenda for today pretty straightforward. We'll talk about a few types of Crashes and
how to approach them and at the end if we have questions we'll do a Q&A.
So the first type of Crash is a Swift runtime Crash now that a lot of apps have Swift code
into them and when it comes to programming Errors that lead to a Crash Swift and Objective-C are
different because in Objective-C different Errors will lead to different Crash types while almost
all the Errors related to Swift programming Errors will follow a similar pattern.
So depending on how much Swift code you have in your app you see more or less of these.
Swift uses memory safety techniques to catch programming Errors early and if you use like a
force unwrap on an optional type that can have a new value of course or if you use the forecasting
so as an exclamation mark to a wrong type then the Swift runtime will catch these Errors and
intentionally Crash the app. And I've simulated such such a Crash actually I've simulated multiple
types of Crashes with our EssentialApp repository and we'll kind of look at them see what's
different what's particular for each type. So for this one we're going to look at the
see what's different what's particular for each type. So for this first type
like I said most of these Crashes follow a pattern which is identifiable in the Crash report
because on ARM processors and ARM processors are on iOS, iPadOS, watchOS and tvOS
the exception type is this XCBreakpoint and the signal is seek trap. So
when we see XCBreakpoint and seek trap we're probably looking at the Swift runtime Crash.
While on inter processors which are the older Macs and the simulators we'll see a different
we'll see a different exception type which is the XC bad instruction and the sigil signal.
So back to our example here.
Additionally the Crash report shows the Thread that encountered the Error
and the first frames at the top of the Thread will indicate the culprit or the the line where
the problem exists. In our case here the first four so zero to three are just exception figures
are just exception figures and the first function call from the stack trace
that's inside the EssentialApp is this Main View body gather
and the Main View Swift line 11 that's where the problem lies.
And yeah like I said the breakpoint exception type this XCBreakpoint indicates a trace trap
that interrupted the process and a trace trap gives an attached debugger the chance to interrupt
the process at a specific point in its execution. The Swift runtime uses trace traps to specific
types of unrecoverable Errors so some lower level libraries such as dispatch or others
trap the process with this exception upon encountering an unrecoverable Error and they
log additional information about the Error in an additional information section of the Crash report.
In our case this is the application application specific information where we find a detailed
Error about the Crash so on line 11 in the Main View.Swift we have a fatal Error unexpectedly
found nil while unwrapping an optional value so this is super explicit we know that we're
force unwrapping an optional which is nil. But this specific explicit information
like I'm showing here is obfuscated from Crash reports that come from iOS, iPadOS,
watchOS and tvOS due to the user's privacy being protected so you won't always see this
extra information. That's why it's useful to try to replicate the Crash in your simulator
because that's when you'll be able to see this extra info.
So a few examples of Swift code that Result in this type of Crash. The first one is the one you
just saw so force unwrapping an optional with a nil value we just have an optional that has nil
and we force unwrap try to print it and it will Crash as you I'm sure you know. Another example
would be accessing an Array element with an out out of bound index so if we have an empty Array
and try to get the element with index one we'll also get a Crash same signature. Another example
would be force trying on an instruction that throws an exception so in this case we use the
JSONDecoder and try to decode into something from an empty data which will most likely fail.
And instructions which instantly generate a Crash or assertion failures or fatal Error.
The takeaway here is that when you see a Crash with the exception type XCBreakpoint and seek
trap as the signal or the XC bad instruction for inter processors there's a high chance it's coming
from a Swift runtime Error. So just inspect the backtrace of the Crash Thread and that should
give you the exact function and line where the Error happened. So depending on the actual code
on that line you should get an idea on how to proceed like for example use an E flat to unwrap
an optional or adding a catch block to avoid a forced try or something like that. So it really
depends on on the Error. Next I want to talk about an Objective-C type of Crash
which is coming from uncaught language exceptions.
So this Crash uses the xccrash Message and the seek abort signal and it indicates the process
terminated because it receives this abort signal. Typically this signal is sent because a function
in the process called abort such as when an app encounters an uncaught Objective-C or C++ language
exception. Again we have an example here. So like I said the exception type xccrash seek abort
and the uncaught exception handler provided by the OS logs the exception Message to the console
before terminating the process. So if you reproduce the Crash resulting from a language exception
with the Xcode debugger attached to your app you can see this Message. So similarly like in the
previous example there's an application specific information that you only get if you're on a
simulator because those are obfuscated on iOS, iPadOS and the other platforms. You'll see the exact
type of problem. So here is terminating with uncaught exception of type XC. So you can see
NSException and it's an NSRangeException where you see exactly like trying to get index one beyond
bounds of empty NSArray. So really explicit again. Also a Crash due to a language exception that
isn't caught has a last exception backtrace. So if you remember our Crash report structure
all of them have this Thread crashed and the stack but for the ones that have an uncaught
exception there's also a last exception backtrace which will show us exactly the trace that led to
the exception. Verify this backtrace is present to confirm the Crash is indeed coming from a language
exception. If we look at the first lines you see exception pre process and obfuscate exception
throw so we really confirm the hypothesis that we're looking at a language exception.
And the lines calling that give us the exact part of our code that called the method which
caused the exception. So in our case from my class.m line 11 we have a function which
I named Crash with index auto bound exception. So it's really clear. And then we see that
the Crash happens inside core Foundation on an NSArray object enumerator.
Enumerator. So again pretty straightforward. An example of code that generated this Crash
is just creating an empty NSArray and again trying to access the element with an index
auto bounds in this case index one. Another example would be to not implement the required
method of a Protocol because Objective-C is such a dynamic language that we can pass an object
using the ID type and then cast it to Protocol type. So if it's missing a required method from
that Protocol then we'll get an exception uncut exception Crash. And the takeaway here is that
Crashes caused by Objective-C or C++ uncut exceptions have this XC Crash and SIGABORT
exception Message. So they're easy to identify.
Next let's talk about watchdog Crashes. I've mentioned this a few times but it's never enough.
So iOS and watchOS employ a watchdog component that is a simple component that just monitors
launch times and app responsiveness and just terminates unresponsive apps.
When this happens the system will generate a Crash report. But please note that neither
Apple's service that collects Crash reports nor a third party service like Firebase Crashlytics,
none of them will collect and display these watchdog Crashes. So you need to get these directly
from the users as I have shown in the lecture about acquiring Crash reports. So they can either
send you the Crash report or but there's no service that will collect these watchdog Crashes. So
Crashes so they are a bit under the radar. To talk about their particularity they use the
XC Crash Message and the SIGKILL this time. So last time it was SIGKILL. This is SIGKILL signal
which indicates the OS terminated the process and the Crash report contains a termination reason
with a code that explains the reason for the Crash. And this code can have multiple values as
we'll see. If this code is 8 bad food then the operating system watchdog has terminated the app.
Let's see how an example looks. So the exception type XC Crash and SIGKILL
and we'll also see a bunch of information coming from the watchdog. So watchdog event,
watchdog visibility, CPU statistics and you also see this code I mentioned so 8 bad food
which is explicit to watchdog Crashes.
The watchdog terminates apps that block the Main Thread for a significant time and there are many
ways to block the Main Thread for an extended time such as synchronous Networking, processing
large amounts of data such as a large JSON File or 3d Model, triggering lightweight migration for
large CoreDataStore synchronously and more. And just to understand why blocking the Main Thread
is an issue consider this most common example. Loading data into the UI from a synchronous
Network call. If the Main Thread is busy with this Network call the system cannot handle UI events
such as multiple scroll events until after completing the Network call. So if this Network
call takes a long time there's a significant time when the user scrolls your UI and until the app
actually responds to those scroll events. And I know you already seen this in practice and you
know this makes the app feel really unresponsive. All the watchdog Crashes contain details about
the slow app state transition that caused the watchdog to close the app. And you can use the
Crash Thread backtrace to see what the culprits are. In our case we see it's the AppDelegate
application did finish launching and once we have this information we can use Instruments and in
this particular case time profiler is perfect to inspect the same app transition and just see why
it's taking so long so what's actually being executed there. And you might find ways to make
these operations faster but in some cases like in case of a Network call you need to make you might
just need to move the heavy work to a background Thread and leave the Main Thread available to
handle UI gestures and UI updates. So that might be the Strategy depending on what you find there.
So a good Strategy is to always return as fast as possible from UI key Delegate methods since
they are executed on the Main Thread and we want to quickly free up the Main Thread to handle these
UI events and updates. And the same goes for SceneDelegate AppDelegate method calls just return
fast and give back the control to the system to avoid any operations that might take a longer time
like a Network call loading from this or writing to this performing heavy computations and so on.
Remember that you will not get these watchdog Crashes in any dashboard so make sure to get
them from your testers if they tell you that it happened. Also you should be periodically
monitoring metrics like your app startup time and just be proactive about it and try to improve it.
Unless you're working on a really large app you should be able to start your app in half a second
that's Apple's recommendation so measure this and try to keep it on the half a second. Next
OS termination which uses the xccrash exception type and the SQL signal
and it indicates the OS terminated the process and the Crash report contains a termination reason
field that explains the reason for the Crash so exactly like before. We've seen the bad food code
8 bad food code previously and there are a few other types of codes which you might see here so
you might see here so let's go through them so you're prepared if you see this.
First there's this code I'm gonna just read the how you're supposed to read it so it's cool off
and the operating system terminates the app with this code due to a thermal event.
This can be an issue with the particular device that this Crash occurred on or the environment
it's operated in. Deadlock. The operating system terminated the app because it held on a File lock
or SQLite Database lock during suspension. You can request additional background execution time
on the Main Thread with the BeginBackgroundTask API. Just make sure you request this before
starting to write to the File. Bad call is when the OS terminated the app for failing to report
the call Kit call in response to a pushkit notification so a pretty explicit scenario.
Bad followed by five twos which is which happens when the OS terminates a voice over IP application
because it resumed too frequently and there are three very similar codes C51 bad 0 1 0 2 0 3 which
are exclusive to watchOS. So in the case of bad 0 1 watchOS terminated the app because it used
too much CPU time while performing a BackgroundTask. The 0 2 and 0 3 codes are also received on
watchOS when the app failed to complete the BackgroundTask within the allocated time.
And the takeaway here is that for each type of code for the exception you can try to reproduce
the issue or just understand why your app is causing that kind of problem. So for example if
you're dealing with a cool off Crash you can check the backtrace and see which functions are using a
lot of CPU time and profile them using time profiler. For a Deadlock Crash you can use the
backtrace to understand which operation is requiring that extra background execution and set it up
and so on. And I just want to mention that all these Crashes are similar to the watchdog Crash
we just talked about so you need to handle them in a similar way. So you need to monitor and acquire
them explicitly. So if you're dealing with a cool off Crash you can try to reproduce the issue or
just manage them explicitly. So the next type of Crash is a process terminated at the request of
another process and it uses the xccrash exception type and the seek quit signal this time.
And it indicates the process terminated at the request of another process with privileges to
lifetime. So seek quit does not mean the process crashed but it likely misbehaved in a detectable
manner. With iOS and iPadOS keyboard extensions the host app terminates the keyboard extension
if it takes too long to load and that's exactly the example I prepared here. So the exception type
xccrash seek quit and this is just a Crash that happens because
of a keyboard extension that takes too long to load.
So the Main app process will kill the extension.
Like you see from launchd.
Another type of Crash is a guarded Resource violation Crash which uses the exception type
XC guard and this indicates the process violated a guarded Resource protection.
Although there are multiple types of guarded system resources, most guarded resources Crashes
are from guarded File descriptors which have the guard type FD value in the exception subtype field.
And if you're unfamiliar with File descriptors, File descriptors are just an abstract handle to
an input or output data Resource such as a File. In other words, it's an abstraction that allows
writing in or reading from a File. The OS marks the File descriptor as guarded so that normal
File descriptor API can't modify them. This is a protection mechanism so whoever opens the File
can protect it from mutation so it's also responsible from closing it. And the guard
File description identifies these problems when they happen making it easier to address.
The exception Message field contains the specific violation which can be closed,
loop, File port, write and so on. I will link in the lecture article a doc page from Apple called
understanding the exception types in a Crash report that details these type of violations.
And let's see an example. This time I selected only the exception information from a Crash report so
it's a partial report because we only care about these four fields. So the exception type,
XC guard, the subtype guard type FD, which tells us that we're dealing with a
FD File descriptor guard issue. Like we said, the exception Message contains the violation
which is closed and we also know the Thread number which triggered this Crash. So we know
where to look because we can consult the backtrace of the Crash Thread and just see where the problem
comes from. Next, another type of Crash coming from a process that exceeded Resource consumption
limits. They use the XC Resource exception type and this is a notification from the OS that the
process exceeded a limit it set on a Resource consumption limit. So the exception type is
a notification from the OS that the process exceeded a limit it set on a Resource consumption.
So we have a few examples here. Again, all the exception types XC Resource
because we have three different sections of Crashes here and if the exception node
like in this case contains non fatal condition, then the process wasn't terminated even though
the OS generated the Crash report. So it's more like a warning. The exception Message field
describes the amount of resources consumed over a specific time interval. So in the first case
is wakeups, a lot of wakeups over a 300 seconds time period or in this case a lot of CPU usage
over a time frame of 180 seconds. And the Crash report List the specific Resource in the exception
subtype as you saw. So wakeups, CPU, memory. So let's see what other values we can have there. So
first, CPU or CPU fatal means a Thread in the process use too much CPU over a short period of time.
Memory happens when the process cross the memory limit imposed by the system
and after we get this warning we might see a termination for excessive memory usage,
but not necessarily. I.O. when the process caused an excessive amount of disk writes over a short
period of time and wakeups where Threads in the process woke up too many times per second which
just consumes battery life. Thread to Thread communication API such as perform on Thread or
async execute or dispatch async caused this when unwittingly called far more often than expected.
Because the communication that triggers this exception is happening so frequently,
there usually are multiple background Threads with very similar backtraces that indicate
the origin of the Thread communication. So the takeaway here is whenever your app is using
one of the resources extensively, you might see this type of Crash. So XC Resource is very specific.
You should probably use the Instruments to inspect your CPU usage, memory usage and try to
improve it. Now memory access issues. A very interesting category of Crashes because you see
that a lot. A Crash due to a memory access issue occurs when an app uses memory in an unexpected
way. Memory access problems have numerous causes such as dereferencing a pointer to an invalid
memory address, writing to read only memory or jumping to an instruction at an invalid
address and so on. A lot of Crashes you will encounter in production especially from Objective-C
are related to memory access issues. These Crashes are most often identified by the XC
bad access exception type and either the SIG SEGV signal which stands for Segment Violation
or the SIG bus signal. Let's see an example. You see the exception type XC bad access segment
violation and the exception subtype field contains a value describing the Error and the address of
memory that was in correct access. So in this case an invalid kernel address at this address
and there are several type of exception subtypes. Let's see what they are. So first the one we just
saw. Invalid address. When the Thread that crashed accessed unmapped memory. Then a protection
failure happens when the Crash Thread tried to use a valid memory address that's protected.
This can be a read only or non executable memory region. Then a memory Error when the
Thread tried to access memory that couldn't return data at the moment such as a memory mapped File
that just became unavailable. And the last is an ARMDA align which happens when the Crash Thread
tried to access memory that isn't aligned properly. Once you've identified that the Crash report
is for a memory access issue, so you've recognized the exception bad access, then you have to
recognize the exception bad access exception type, you can use Xcode to continue your investigation.
Because Xcode contains a suite of Debugging tools you can use to identify memory access
issues as your app runs. So for this let's go into Xcode and I'll use the scheme editor.
Make sure run action is selected and then open the diagnostics panel.
There are a few tools here which are really effective in Testing this. So we have the address
sanitizer, the threat sanitizer or the undefined behavior sanitizer.
I recommend you activate only one sanitizer at a time as they each consume a lot of memory
and CPU to produce their results. And then just run the app with these tools enabled and go
through the scenarios you want to check and try to inspect and fix all the issues they report back to
you. Another option is if you have a lot of objective cc or c++ code there's a static analyzer
which you can run in the product menu analyze action. And again see what issues it discovers
and try to resolve them all, because the static analyzer analyzes your code at build time and
will identify common programming mistakes including some type of memory management issues.
So it's a good verification to be done periodically.
A common type of memory access Crash is a zombie Crash.
Once an Objective-C or Swift object no longer has any strong references to it the object is
deallocated. Attempting to send messages to the object after that as if it were still a valid
object leads to a Crash. The object receiving the Message is called a zombie object. The most likely
cause for a zombie is the use of unsafe references, but any use of unsafe memory could lead to a zombie.
Both Swift and Objective-C support this type of references, so in both languages zombies are
possible. In Swift they are unowned and unowned unsafe. So unowned and unowned unsafe. And in
Objective-C there are properties with the assign specifier or the unsafe unretained specifier.
Let's take an example. Imagine we have a ViewController class and it has a weak Delegate.
Because it's weak the View control is not holding a strong reference to it,
so the Delegate will be deallocated if no other class holds a reference to it. That's why it
needs to be optional, because if the Delegate is deallocated the property will automatically be
set to nil. This is the safest option because the compiler forces us to handle the case where
the Delegate was deallocated, so we need to safely unwrap the optional to make sure it contains a
reference to the Delegate. So far so good. Now let's see another case. A slight variation,
where instead of weak we use unowned. Like weak, unowned won't hold a strong reference,
but it's not optional, so this code is less safe. If no one else holds a reference to the Delegate
it will be deallocated, but in this case if we try to access the deallocated instance it will Crash
immediately. And finally the most unsafe case is using unowned unsafe. This was very common in
Objective-C before automatic reference Count, so you may use old system Objective-C classes that
declare unowned unsafe properties. unowned unsafe is similar to unowned, it doesn't hold a strong
reference, but there's a big difference. Let's explain this. Let's say we allocated my Delegate
at memory address 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, but after a while no one holds a reference to it anymore,
so in this case the instance will be deallocated and this memory address and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5
will be free to be used to allocate other instances because memory is recycled.
But we still have an unowned unsafe property that still references the 1, 2, 3, 4, 5
address and because it's unowned unsafe this will not be automatically cleaned up and set to nil.
Later the system might allocate another object at the same address, let's say an NSString,
and we try to send a Message through that unowned reference to the Delegate, so let's say the my
Delegate method exists in my Delegate, but in reality since my Delegate no longer exists at
1, 2, 3, 4, 5 address, but instead there's an NSString there, the NSString will receive this
my Delegate method Message and that's a big problem because most likely NSString cannot
respond to these messages we send to the Delegate, so it won't behave as we expect and we'll get a
Crash with reason saying NSString cannot respond to my Delegate method selector and you may think
but I never sent this Message to an NSString, how can this be? Well you didn't send it directly,
but because memory is recycled this can happen with unsafe access to memory, so that's kind of
how a zombie Crash happens and if a zombie Crash happens you'll see an exception like this, so you
see a terminating aptitude to onCaughtException and unrecognized selector like I've shown before
and you see the reason like the class and the received Message, but any use of unsafe memory
could lead to a zombie and this is another example of a Crash report from a zombie Crash,
again EXC_BAD_ACCESS with the SIGSEGV signal will also see a segmentation fault as the termination reason
and if you inspect the backtrace of the Crash Thread you'll see that the last line in the
EssentialApp is my class in it and then there's an objcMessageSend, this is a clear indicator
that the Crash is due to a zombie, so if you ever see objcMessageSend or objcRetain
or objcRelease here at the top of the backtrace you're dealing with a zombie object
and to deal with zombie objects in the scheme editor next to the sanitizer I showed there's a
zombie object diagnostic tool, this will help you a lot deal with and find zombies in your app
because what this does is just it will run your app in a different environment where no objects
are deallocated, so instead of being deallocated they just become zombies and they keep living,
so if you send a Message to a zombie which is an object that should be deallocated the app will
Crash and show you exactly where the problem is, because when you're dealing with zombies the
problem is you don't know who allocated the original object, so how does that object no
longer exist, so when you're using this zombies objects option it will be very clear because the
instrument will stop the execution and you can inspect all the references to that object and
see where the memory issue lies and also to diagnose memory access Crashes you can use the
guard malloc option that's also like a sanitizer and this will inspect all the memory allocations
Another type of Crash which I want to cover is a Crash from a missing library, this uses the
exe Crash Message type and the sigaboard signal and if an app Crashes because it's missing a
required framework or library the Crash report contains this exception code, let's see an example
so exe Crash sigaboard
and you'll find a termination description in the Crash report identifying the specific framework
that the dynamic linker couldn't locate, so in our case library not loaded, Cocoa Lumberjack
and in the application specific information as well
so we see that this framework Cocoa Lumberjack could not be found by the system
and to fix this there are a few things you need to do, so first you need to make sure that library
exists and then you need to make sure it's included in the framework search paths and
library search paths and that it contains all the architectures that your app is using
so it can be either one of these problems
yeah I see a question in the chat so vital is asking is as I can understand it concerns
only dynamic libraries, yes so this indeed is a problem related to dynamic loading only because
when you're using static libraries or static frameworks those are linked at compile time so
they won't be loaded at runtime separately from a different module
so yeah if you if you have dynamic libraries then or dynamic frameworks you might see this problem
next another particular type of Crash is the jetsum and jetsum is just related to memory pressure
events iOS iPad OS watchOS and tvOS have a virtual memory system that relies on all apps
releasing memory when the operating system encounters memory pressure
where available memory is low and the system cannot meet the demands of all the running apps
so under memory pressure apps free memory and receive a low memory notification
before running apps release enough total memory to alleviate the pressure your app will continue to
alleviate the pressure your app will continue to run but if memory pressure continues because apps
haven't relinquished enough memory the system frees memory by terminating applications
and reclaims their memory this is what a jetsum event is and the system creates a jetsum event
report with information about why it chose to jettison an app and we can see an example
first you'll notice that jetsum event report different from Crash reports because they contain
the overall memory of all the apps and system processes on the device and they're in JSON format
they don't have any backtrace information but only List all the processes and their memory
footprints and other types of info which we'll see in a second if the system jettisons your app due
to memory pressure while the app is visible it will look like your app crashed to the user
and use jetsum event reports to identify your app's Role in jetsum events even if your app
didn't get jettisoned so it might be another app which did
what's important to keep in mind here is that jetsum events as watchdog Crashes are not collected by
the Apple service or third party services so again you need to make sure you get these directly from
your users so the most reliable ones are your internal users
your testers and your other teams so you need to make sure that you get these directly from your
users your testers and your other teammates back to the structure of this Crash report
you see it has a few information at the beginning like a Crash report a queue like similar Crashes
and some information about the memory pages how many pages how many free pages wired and so on
you also see the largest process which in my case is the webkit web content
if it's your app you need to reduce the memory consumption of your app
a jetsum event also contains an Array of processes as you see here with each item in the Array
describing a single process in the system like this you can search for the reason key to identify
the jettisoned process and why the system terminated it because only the jettisoned process
has the reason key and if it's your app the value of the reason key explains the condition that led
to the jettison event and you can determine the amount of memory each app was using by multiplying
the number of r pages by the size of each page which is visible here base size so over here we're
dealing with pages of 16 kilobytes and for instance this process is using 299 pages so you can do the
math and see how much memory it consumes also i want to mention that each item in this processes
Array has a few keys which will give you some additional information so the UUID which is the
build identifier of the binary the states an Array of the current memory use states such as memory
from the frontmost app suspended or not actively using memory a lifetime max which is the highest
number of memory pages allocated during the lifetime of the process a coalition of memory
usage a coalition this is useful if your app's process is part of a coalition that evolves other
system processes doing work on behalf of your app like an extension in the name which is the process
name and this one matches a binary from your app or belongs to another app or system process
since jetsem events are events of high memory usage it's always a good idea to constantly
and make sure your app uses memory like a good citizen or avoiding spikes of large memory
allocations and freeing the memory once it's no longer needed for this you can use the memory
inspector in Xcode or some of the Instruments like activity monitor which will give you a
high level idea of your app's total memory consumption and then you can use the allocations
tool to deep dive and see exactly how that memory is allocated and why which features or parts are
taking up most memory and more information in addition to lowering your app's memory use ensure
that you're receiving low memory warnings sent by the system and you're acting on these warnings
because that's the only way you can protect yourself from being jettisoned if the system
sends you a Message that there's low memory condition on the device and asking you to free
up memory if you don't free up memory you're most likely be terminated so try to respond to these
events by clearing memory that you can reload from the Cache or any other improvements to the memory
footprint you can do and by the way there's a there's an option in the simulator to simulate
the memory warning so you can see how your app responds to these warnings in the simulator but
just triggering that explicitly and two more types first invalid arithmetic operation which is using
the XC arithmetic exception type and this is just a Crash that happens because an invalid
arithmetic operation such as division by zero or floating point Error so those are very explicit
like in this case divide by zero and XC arithmetic exception type you just use the
Thread backtrace and see where the Error is coming from
and finally Crashes that contain only system functions let's call it the impossible Crash type
this is one of the hardest types of Crashes that you can understand and try to fix because
those are Crashes that contain only system functions in their backtrace there's no AppCode
in the backtrace you cannot reproduce it you have no clear information so what do you do
in these situations first of all you need to read the Crash report really carefully and by this i
mean all the stack traces exception codes to narrow down as much as possible maybe a part of the app
where the Crash is happening or something related to framework or anything that you can find there
sometimes that's not enough that's when third party services like Crash reports are not enough
that's when third party services like Firebase Crashlytics that have an option to register logs
can come in handy so you can add logs and these third party services will deliver the logs along
with the Crash report and this can be really helpful because the Crash report is just like
a Snapshot of what was happening on the device at the time the app crashed what you need is most of
the time some steps to reproduce like a story so if you have these logs you can have more details
like okay the user opened the app and went to search and then did this and that like maybe
maybe that can give you a clue about how to reproduce this Crash because like i said if you
get just a Crash report it's just a Snapshot so it crashed in this function but you have no idea
what other things happened before and i'm not aware of any ways to to get logs with Apple's
report service so if you need this you might be looking into a third party service or not it's
your decision i can't influence it but i cannot underline enough how valuable it is to be able
to reproduce a Crash because when you can reproduce it constantly then you can inspect it with the
different tools i've shown or then you can do the TDD flow and write a test that triggers the Crash
and then fix it and this way you make sure you have no regressions on that Crash in the Future
so i hope i give you some useful tips about these Crash types let me know if you have questions
yeah i already see a question do you know which type of Crash can cause swizzling methods i mean
will it be zombie unrecognized selector or something else i guess it depends because if
you're swizzling with a method that doesn't exist on that object yeah you can get an unrecognized
selector yeah i guess if you if you use the wrong method that swizzling in my experience can lead
to other problems as well so i try to stay away from it as much as possible sure any any other
questions going once going twice
yes no that's it thank you for staying up and see you soon bye