Hi everyone and welcome to another episode of the tooling series.
This time we'll take a look at the build configuration files or XC config as they're
known from their extension. XC config files can be a very elegant way to manage, reuse,
and compose build settings so it's worth dedicating the session to understanding them.
The plan for today is to explain the mechanics of XC config files to see what advantages and
disadvantages they have compared to the standard way of managing settings which is to the build
settings editor, understand when to prefer one approach over the other, explain when and how
to move all the build settings from the Xcode project to separate XC config files, and showcase
the utility of XC config files in some live examples. At the end we'll do a Q&A as always.
First we'll do a very quick recap of the build settings and their mechanics. So a build setting
is a property you can apply to your Xcode projects to configure aspects of how they are built.
There are many settings within Xcode and the comprehensive List as always can be found in
Apple Docs. There are two ways to manage build settings. One is through the build settings
editor which we already covered in the previous lecture and the other is through configuration
settings files or XC config and this is our topic for today.
Also recap how Xcode build settings are resolved. So before each build the system must resolve all
the build settings for each target that is built. Build settings are resolved using a fallback
based system where the resolver looks for a value from higher to lower priority levels until it
finds one or ends up with the platform default. In the graphical representation you see
as well as in Xcode build settings tab, priority increases from right to left.
So the first column would be platform defaults and if there's no other explicit setting at any
other level the resolver will use these defaults. Next is the project configuration File level
and this one can only override platform defaults and is overwritten by defaults.
Next the project level settings are used when target settings are missing. Project settings
override the settings from the project config File if any and the platform defaults. Next if
we have a target configuration File this will override all the project level and platform level
settings. And finally target explicit settings override any other setting as they have the highest
priority. Xcode build configuration files or XC config allow build settings for your app to be
declared and managed without Xcode. They are plain text files which means they are much friendlier
to source control systems and can be modified with any editor. Some of the advantages of using
XC config files are better source control management, sharing settings across targets,
configurations or even projects, composition of build settings and the ability to include additional
configuration setting files based on environment. The second one is that Xcode build configuration
let's see what the mechanics of XC config files are. So as we mentioned a build configuration
File is a text File that has an XC config File name extension that you add to your project.
You can create as many build configuration files as you want and you can configure different
settings in each one. For example you might use one build configuration File for debug settings
and another one for release. To specify a new value for setting the format which you need to use
is setting name equals setting value. At the bottom of the slide you see a short example
of an XC config File that sets three settings. We've mentioned this in our previous lecture
but just to recap each build setting allows a different type of value.
The potential types are boolean, String, String List, path or path List and enumeration.
In the definition of a setting value we can refer to other settings like in this case.
For this we use the dollar and parentheses to reference other values. A clear example is
the install path setting which uses the local library directory setting and its framework subfolder.
Besides this all settings support using the variable dollar inherited which is resolved
to any value set by a lower priority level including platform defaults. To append rather
than replace existing definitions use the dollar inherited variable like in these examples.
First we have setting name equals dollar inherited which means we'll be getting any value
set at the lower priority and the additional value which we want to append. Another example
would be we're setting dollar inherited on every level composes all the values together
and the practical example is where we explicitly set the framework search paths
by using the inherited value and appending our project directory.
When referencing values we can always set the default value in case that reference doesn't
exist. In this example we also use the last time we are passing an extra flag to the Swift compiler
that will issue a warning for expression that take too long to type check. In this case we have set
the default value of 200 milliseconds but we can override it in simple terms.
200 milliseconds but we can override it in CI for example where builds are slower
if we define the max expression checking time setting. This setting would only exist
on the CI and we can generate it with a script.
Also recapping the transformations we can apply to values. The available operators include strings,
operators, paths and replacement operators. In two examples we have here first we apply the C99X
identifier operator on the targetName and in the second example we apply the C99X identifier
and in the second example we compose multiple operators so for the product name build setting
we apply the Intel 1034 identifier and we lowercase.
You can conditionalize build settings according to their SDK architecture and or configuration.
According to the following syntax. In the example at the bottom of the slide
we have the same setting for the debug configuration and any SDK and any architecture.
So a combination.
To understand how composition works let's take a look at this example. First we define
a custom build setting is build setting enabled and we set it to no. Then we define two values
to other build settings. My build setting no which has a use this one value and my build setting yes
which uses use this instead. Then we can create a conditional composed value for my build setting
where we reference both the build settings. This is interesting because build settings are evaluated
inside out so how this expression is resolved. First the resolver will look at the dollar is
build setting enabled and will evaluate it to no. So the new expression will be transformed to dollar
will be transformed to dollar my build setting no. Again evaluating this expression will
transform to the value of use this one. It can be pretty powerful.
Another feature of configuration files is including other configuration files.
Because when you specify the build configuration File in Xcode for a target or project you must
select only one File. But that File can include settings from other configuration files using
the syntax. To import the settings from a different configuration File add a hash include
statement like the first one. So we just need the path to the configuration File. But remember
if Xcode can find the included build configuration File it will generate a build warning. So to
suppress these warnings we can add a question mark next to the include statement as shown in the
second example. This will be helpful in the example we just shown with the CI dedicated config File.
Another feature of config files are they allow comments to include notes or any other information
that's relevant to you. Specify your comments on a single line preceded by two forward slashes.
The build system ignores everything that's after that. So we can have lines with comments only or
we can inline some comments. Let's do a small comparison of the Xcode build settings editor
versus these XC config files. So by default Xcode stores all the build settings inside the
Xcode proj PBX proj File along with references to files frameworks build phases and other settings.
We've seen this in a previous episode. This setUp is automatically done by Xcode and it's easy to
use. It's not trivial to understand but most developers are familiar with the Xcode build
settings editor so that's not a problem. Xcode way of storing settings in the project File
results in the duplication of settings which we also shown by keeping a separate set of settings
for each combination of project and configuration and target and configuration. For many projects
especially small ones this is not a problem as the build settings editor inside Xcode is fine
for doing audio operations. If the theme is not large conflicts will happen occasionally
and they'll be relatively easy to fix. Reviewing diffs on the project File and especially spotting
these changes to build settings is a bit harder. It's not clear when looking at just the diff what
is the level of each setting that's being affected and that's because all the groups of settings in
the project File look the same. Also for developers that don't fully understand how build settings
work and how to manage them having default values preset by Xcode which are pretty optimal is
sufficient and allows them to focus on writing code and delivering products pretty fast.
As always we recommend you start small with the most easy and straightforward approach.
In this case this means keeping your settings within Xcode using the build settings editor
and that should be your default approach.
For large themes where each developer will likely edit the project File with every PR
maintaining all these changes and the implied conflicts to the project File can become a
liability and slow down the development cycle. Also reviewing this on a large project File and
noticing changes to build settings which are at the end of the File can be pretty hard.
This is where exe config files come useful as they are just plain text files they're easy to
write and maintain. You can organize them as you want in a decentralized way and share them between
configuration targets, projects or event repos. Also since they contain only build settings
reviewing changes is much easier. Tracking changes to a particular project File is a lot easier.
Tracking changes to a particular setting over time is also quite easy to do.
So it's not easy to understand a setUp based on exe config files and or setting stored in the
project File it can be done. Using exe config files does not guarantee you avoid the duplication
of settings as we'll show in a minute as this needs to be an intentional process where you
remove this duplication. Also if you need to access more advanced scenarios like conditional
values of build settings, the composition of values or just avoid this duplication and have
a clear separation of concerns in the infrastructure of the project config files are a solution to be
considered. This concludes the theoretical part and now I want to do a few quick demos
to show you how we can work with config files.
So let's work with our EssentialFeed demo project.
First I want to inspect the build settings. So I will select
all the targets in the EssentialFeed project and I want to look at the Swift language version
setting. And we can see that all the targets use the same value.
Also if we look at the development team
setting, we also see the same vrj2 value. So for this first demo I would like to remove
this duplication and move these settings into a centralized exe config File. Let's see how we can
do that. First inside the EssentialFeed project I'm going to add a new File and there's a
configuration settings File template which I'm going to use. I will name it shared because I
want to keep shared settings and I will put it at the root of my repository. An important note
here is I will not include it into any of the targets because that means embedding the File
and exe config files don't need to be embedded into the target. They just need to be visible
inside the project so Xcode can see them and access them. And I do a create.
I have already prepared the two values I will need for my settings. So now I want to set them.
I will go to the project, then also select the project level in the editor and use the info tab.
Here we have this section called configurations. If I open it, I see I can set a File for each
project and each target and there's one set for the debug configuration and one for the release.
And of course for any other configuration I might have. In this case I willSet the shared File I
just createdAt the project level because I want all the targets to use this. So I'll select the
shared File for both the debug configuration and the release. This will propagate the settings as
I said to all the targets. Now let's look at the build settings editor for my target. In this case
EssentialFeed. We immediately notice that there's a new tab which is the config File I just added.
Looking for my Swift language version, I can see the value of the config File is Swift 5 and
the overwritten explicit setting for my target is also Swift 5.
So I'll select all my targets and use the delete key to delete all the explicit settings from the
project level, from the target level. But I immediately see all the values are still
Swift 5.0. Just they are not bold anymore. So this means they're not explicitly set at the target
level. And inspecting one of the targets, I can see that this value is coming from the
configuration File I just set. Let's look at the development team setting.
And we'll notice a similar scenario where the value from the config File and the target is the
same. So I'll select all my targets, hit delete, and re-inspect to make sure. And I can see that
the Result value is still the VRJ one that's coming this time from the config File.
That's coming this time from the config File. And this is what I want. I can even
do a build just to make sure I didn't break anything. And let's commit.
If we look at the diff, we'll see the reference to the File we just added, the group,
the reference for each configuration that we set in Xcode. So the project debug now references this
value. And the same is true for the project release set. And now we see that the development team and
suite version settings have disappeared or been deleted for each of the target explicit settings.
And we have many of these because Xcode actually stores one set for each of the targets. Since we
have five targets and two configurations, that's ten dictionaries from where we actually deleted
those two keys. And we can see that the target is still the same. And we can see that the
target is the same. We can even reference the File we created from the EssentialApp target
by dragging the File. I will also uncheck the target so the File does not get bundled.
I will do the same exercise. So I'll go to the EssentialApp info this time,
use my shared File for both the project debug and release config files.
I'll use the build settings inspector to look at the Swift language.
Delete. Still 3.5. We're good. The same for the test target.
Delete. Development team. And the test target. And the values are still
as they should. I did a build. Everything looks good. So I will commit. And the diff
looks very similar to what we had in our previous commit where the File was added to the project.
We get the references. And all the explicit settings have been removed.
And please note that there's no new XC config File as we are using the same one.
Reference from two projects. This is the first example I wanted to go through. The second example
will continue. So we've done a theoretical example in one of the lectures which I will
make practical right now. And this is the case where we have different environments for our
endpoints. Let's say staging and production. And we want to use user defined build settings to
resolve these endpoints. So I will use my shared config File, which I already setUp.
And I'll prepopulate it with a build setting which I'm calling API Domain. That uses the
conditional syntax I used in the slides. And for the debug configuration, we set the value to
API.staging.example.com. And for the release, we set it to API.example.com.
Just to make sure we use the right syntax, go to one of the projects, build settings editor,
and check the UserDefinedSettings, which show my API Domain setting. And I can see it has
different values for the debug and the release configurations. So we're good. Reading these
values from the exe config files into code is not that easy, but there's one nice way to do it,
and that's through the Info.plist File. This is because the Info.plist File is actually compiled
after the build settings are resolved. So that's a nice way to do it. Now, let's look at the
build settings are resolved. So that's why we can have all these build settings like the dollar
product name set for the Bundle name and more. So I'm going to add a new setting here, which I'm
going to call it API base URL. And I'll set the value to HTTPS dollar API Domain. One of the
reasons I did this is because using the forward slashes required by the HTTPS scheme in the config
File would require some escaping, and I wanted to avoid that. Now, the last piece of the puzzle
is reading these values, this value from the Info.plist in code. So I'm going to go to my
SceneDelegate and just try to read the value and print it around the app. And I see the first line
in the console being URL is HTTP API staging. This is because my project uses the debug
configuration for the run action. I will stop. And to get the project into a clean state,
I'm going to revert everything we've done because in the next example, I want us to go through
an exercise of moving all the settings from Xcode project to config files, and I didn't want to
interfere. I see a question in the chat, so let's see. Seba says, I wonder if we want to
have other configurations like test, UAT, etc. Swift Package manager doesn't work when
there are project configs other than default debug and release. Yeah, that's a known issue
for Swift Package manager. It's also something we recommend so you don't create extra configurations
unless you really need to, as it would just complicate the whole setUp of your project. So,
if you need to have different set of build settings, I just showed you how you can do
this with configuration files, or you can look into other options like duplicating the targets,
which is also not the best solution, but it really depends on your use case. Yeah, that's
a good example, so it's an extra reason to avoid extra configurations.
So, back to our project. Everything is back to the original state.
So, let's see what this process of extracting the settings would look like.
I'm going to use an open source tool, which is called build setting extractor,
and what this open source project does is it allows you to drag an Xcode project
into it, and it will extract all the settings into separated XC config files.
So, I'll drag my EssentialFeed Xcode project, and I need to select a folder, so I select the
EssentialFeed folder, and I can see it immediately created an XC config folder and a bunch of files
inside, which we're going to take a look at in a minute. I will also do the same for the EssentialApp
project, and it also generated the XC config folder. Very useful tool. So, using Finder,
I want to explore the contents of this folder, which can be intimidating at first, but it's
using Finder. I want to explore the contents of this folder, which can be intimidating at first.
First, we notice we have some project files and then some files that have the name of each of
our targets. Since we have five targets, each target has a set of files.
The project files are one for debug, one for release, and a shared. The shared File contains
all the settings that apply to both debug and release. The debug and release files contain the
settings that are specific to that configuration only, and this applies to the project level for
the three project files, and then to each target. So, that's why we have three files for each of
our targets and one for the project. We'll look into those files in a minute. For now, let's
assume they contain the exact same settings we have in our Xcode project, and we'll check this.
Let's see how we can use these files. First, we need to add them into the project. I will
drag and drop the XC config folder from the EssentialFeed folder into my EssentialFeed project.
I will uncheck the target because, as before, I don't want any files being added to the project.
I don't want any files being bundled, and I'll hit Finish. The problem with this approach, and I'm
sure you've seen this, is I get a random order for all the files I just added, and I don't like this.
So, I'll select all the files, hit Delete to remove the references, and then go to my
Finder, and select all the files which are ordered, and drag them back. Same, I'll uncheck the target
and hit Finish. And now, I have all the files in the right order, if you care about this. Now,
let's actually start using them. So, I'll go to my EssentialFeed project, the project level info,
and I want to set these configurations. First, let's do it at the project level. So,
I'll select my project level File, and I'll use project debug for the debug configuration, and
project release for the release configuration. Now, let's inspect the build settings for the project
level because that's what we have just changed. Again, we see the extra column for the config File,
and I can use this customized filter, which will only show me the settings, which are explicit at
the current level. So, my current level being project, then I'll see all the project level
explicit settings. Let's compare my explicit settings for the EssentialFeed project with
the ones from my imported File. So, I'll select all the files, and I'll select all the files,
imported File. And if we take a quick look, we'll see they are the same.
This is where we would catch any potential issues with this generation of the files, but I see
no problem. So, what I'll do is I'll hit command A and select all the customized settings and hit
delete. This deletes all the customizations from the project level from my Xcode project.
Before we commit, we look at the diff again. So, first section, we have all the new added config
files, then there's the exe config group, and of course its files. And then at the bottom,
where we have all the settings, we see that instead of the List of settings we used to have
for the debug and release configurations of each project, they've been replaced with the
base configuration reference to the File I just selected. So, all these settings are now gone from
the project File. And I want to commit. Let's also set the configuration
files for each target because they have some explicit settings of their own. So,
you need to bear with me for this one. We will select for every target the target plus
configuration File that's corresponding. So, first I'm looking at the debug configuration. So,
I have EssentialFeed debug, an EssentialFeedTests debug, an EssentialFeedAPI end-to-end Tests
debug, EssentialFeedCacheIntegration test debug, EssentialFeed iOS debug, and EssentialFeed
iOS Tests debug. And I'll quickly do the same for the release. Notice that we don't include
the shared File explicitly because that's already imported in both the debug and release files.
Done. Now, let's inspect the build settings of my target, which is EssentialFeed at first. Again,
I'll use the customized plus levels. And if we look at all the tabs here, we see the project
level settings and the target level config File as well. If we quickly look at those two columns,
we see they have the same values. So, our import was successful. Again, I will select all the
settings and hit delete. And I'll do this for all the targets. Again, this is the point where you
need to be very careful and make sure that the values you get from the configuration files
are the exact same as the ones you had explicit through Xcode. Okay. I'll do a build.
Everything's okay. So, I will see what the diff looks like.
Since we already imported the File in our previous commit, there's no
changes to the beginning of this File. So, only explicit settings being replaced by the
configurations we just added. As you remember, the structure of this XC build configuration settings
is first the project, so project debug, project release, and then each target. So, we see that
each target has a setting for the base configuration reference to one of the XC configs. And then all
the settings on the right are gone. And we just deleted 200 lines from our project File.
I will also commit this. Let's quickly do the same exercise for the EssentialApp.
So, first, go to the finder, drag the xcconfig folder. But because the order is wrong,
I will remove the references and add them again. Again, making sure we don't Embed them.
That's not a problem. So, if they get embedded, they're extra
files in your app Bundle. No problem. But they shouldn't be there, especially since they're
plain text. This time, I will do just one operation. So, setting my config files for the project
debug. I will use project debug. For the project release, I will use project release. Then for
EssentialApp target, I'll use EssentialApp debug. EssentialApp test debug. EssentialApp
release. EssentialApp test release. Then that's the configuration. Now, we'll inspect the build
settings as before. So, customized. First, for the project level, we compare the two columns.
I see no difference. I'll do command A and delete. And then, at the project, at the target level,
I'll also check out those two columns. So, the target and the config File for the target.
Make sure they're the same. I think they are. So, again, command A, delete. And for the test target
as well. Do a build. And then, for the test target, I'll do a build.
As well. Do a build. Still successful. This doesn't guarantee because I haven't built all
the scenarios, but at least the first build looks fine. So, let's look at the diff.
Again, we have the section with the config files we added. The new exe config group and its files.
And all the settings have been deleted. The first two being the project settings. So, the project
debug and project release. And then, the set of settings for the EssentialApp. And the EssentialApp
test target. And I'll commit.
And I'll commit. We have successfully moved all the settings from the export project File to the
dedicated exe config files. But we haven't edited anything. We just copied over the values from one
side to the other. Now, I want to take a quick look at the files we just generated and see if
we can make further improvements. I'll use the files in the EssentialFeed project because they
are a lot more. So, the EssentialFeed debug, which is the File for the EssentialFeed target
debug configuration, has only one setting, which is the Swift optimization level set to none.
Also, we see the include of the EssentialFeed shared. And if we open that File, we see a bunch
of settings that were explicit for my target. If you look at the release File, we see the File is
empty. And this will be the case for a number of our files here. But since we want the ability to
easily add settings to targets in the Future, we won't delete these files.
If we look at the EssentialFeed shared and all the other shared files, we see
there are a previous example that they all use the Swift version 5.0.
So, this tells me that there is still duplication.
More than that, if we look at the targets from the EssentialApp,
we see that they also use Swift version 5.0. So, okay, let's get rid of this duplication.
This is where XC config files are useful because we can import a File, a configuration File,
from any path. So, since I want to share between those two projects, I will go to finder
go to finder, and I'll create an XC config folder at the root of my repo. So,
instead of creating it inside one of the folders for my projects, I'll create it outside.
I will drag it, and as you can see, it's at the same level as my other projects.
Inside it, I'll create a configuration File, which I'll name Shared.
And because this group doesn't belong to any project, it doesn't, the File doesn't get added
to any of the targets. Since I said I want to move my Swift version to this File,
I will paste the name of the setting and the value here. And now let's remove all the other definitions
of this Swift version. So, I did the command shift F to open the find in all files and pasted this
Swift version setting, and I'll go to each one of them and remove it. So, target, those are all
those are all target shared configs, and I will make sure I import
my new Swift version setting
in my project shared, which will propagate them to all the targets.
So, at the beginning of the project shared, I'll do an include, and the path needs two folders back,
xcconfig and the shared File I just created. And I'll do this for both the EssentialApp
and the EssentialFeed project shared files. I'll do a build, all good, and just to make sure we
haven't broken anything, now I need to use the all filter and say Swift language. And I see the Swift
language is still Swift 5, and it's coming from this project shared config File, which imports it
from the shared File. If we look at the diff, first we have a reference added to the Xcode workspace
to the new XC config group, then in different files for targets shared settings, we see the Swift
version has been removed, then in the project shared, we see this extra line for the import we
added, and the same goes for the EssentialFeed. So, I won't go to all of them, it's the same,
and the import. And we only have one File where Swift version is defined. Now, if I... let's commit
this and show you how easy it is to change the Swift version to all the files and to all the
projects at once. So, if I set this to Swift 4, we'll actually see it. Yeah. So, the config File
the config File sets it to Swift 4, which is not what we wanted, and I'll revert.
At the point, the whole point was to show like the one centralized place controls all the settings
in all the projects. Next, I see there's a project shared with many settings in both the projects.
So, I'm curious to see what are the differences between these files and if I can reuse anything.
So, I'll use one diff tool, in my case, Araxis Merge, and I'll drag the project shared from the
EssentialApp and the project shared from the EssentialFeed projects. And I can immediately
see they are almost identical with a few differences in code signing, current project,
and some versioning, and, of course, the SDK route. In one case is macOS and in the other is iPhone OS.
So, I'll use... I'll copy all the settings here, because they are... they exist in both files,
and I'll move them to my shared File to avoid this duplication. So, I've pasted it in,
pasted it in, and now give it here. Yeah. So, I only kept the settings which were different.
And I moved everything else into my shared File. One of the settings we moved was iPhone
deployment target 14.0. So, to make sure I didn't break anything, I'll take a look at
deployment target. And I see it's still 14.0. Let's check the EssentialFeed project, just to be sure.
Yep. 14.0. So, again, I didn't break anything. Let's look at the diff.
So, all the settings have been moved, or almost all the settings, all the common settings have
been moved from these files into my shared one. So, I'm going to move this to my shared one.
Next, I will use the same diff tool. This time, let's compare project debug from the EssentialFeed
project to the project debug from the EssentialApp project. And we see they're identical. So,
again, more duplication. I will add a new File, which I'm going to call it debug. And I'll move
all my settings here. And then make sure my other files just include this new File. So, again,
make sure my other files just include this new File. So, again, we have removed the application.
So, my new File and new files just contain the imports. Also, look at the
comparison between the release files of each project. And, again, only one difference,
where the EssentialApp has an extra validate product. So, I'll copy these,
create a new File here, config.
Config. Release. And paste the common settings.
And for the project release, for the EssentialApp, we'll keep the validate product setting,
which is not common. And in the release File, we will delete all the settings.
So, just to make sure we didn't break anything,
we need to see the debug information format set to DWARF with DSYM on the release configurations.
So, yes, we are good. We can omit. There's just a few more things which I want to point out
at this point, since we have this sharing of settings. First of all, there's this always Embed
Swift standard libraries setting, which is no longer required, as Swift is ABI stable now.
So, what we can do is use the default value and just delete these old values where they're set to
yes. And we'll see that the setting is set to yes in our shared File we just created,
which means all the targets automatically get it. So, we can go ahead and remove it,
since it's already set to yes from all the target explicit files.
Next, Swift optimization level. It's already set. So, our shared debug sets it to none,
and our release sets it to optimize for I think it's for speed. So, we can delete any explicit ones,
especially these debug ones that were set to none because none was already inherited.
Again, in the case of the diff, we just removed it.
Development team. We see that it's used in all the target shared files and it's the same value.
So, again, as in our first demo, I think this can be moved to the shared File.
So, I'll just paste it here and remove it
remove it from all the other files. And to be super careful,
we just check the development team setting, and we see it's still resolved to the same value.
So, again, we didn't break anything.
Commit. And just the new setting being added to the shared File.
Now, a more interesting example is code sign style. So, if we search for this setting, we see that
almost all the targets set it to automatic, except for the EssentialApp release config that uses the
manual. We can still avoid the duplication by moving the code sign automatically to the
shared File. But, instead of removing all the cases, we are just going to remove
the places where it was set to automatic.
So, we will keep the explicit setting for the EssentialApp release config, and we're going to
check this in a second, just to be moving the code sign automatically to the shared File.
And now, if we use the build settings editor,
we see that the
style is set to automatic for the debug configuration and to manual for the release, because we have an
explicit manual value in the config File for the target, which overrides the value from the
default settings. So, we can see that the style is set to automatic for the debug configuration,
which overrides the value from the project config File. So, let's commit this.
If we look at the product name setting, we see it almost uses the same value in all the targets
with the difference that in Tests, it's set to $targetName, while in like the EssentialFeed
or EssentialFeed iOS targets, which are framework targets or in the app target,
it's using the C99X identifier transformation.
Now, since this doesn't change the value of the targetName, we can extract all of them
using the C99X identifier and move that to the shared File.
And again, we can delete all the explicit ones because
the value will still be resolved to the same value before.
Now, it's just in one place. And again, to make sure, let's look at the EssentialFeed project this time
and say product name.
And the product name is still
correct. So, EssentialFeed, EssentialFeedTests, EssentialFeed iOS, and so on. So, again, we did
not break anything. Commit this one as well. So, again, just one place and then removing it from
all the other files. Let's look at the targeted device family, which as you remember, is the
setting that's basically describing which devices are allowed to run our app. In the EssentialFeed
project, there's not much sharing of this setting as it's only set for the EssentialFeed iOS target
and the Tests. But we see that for the EssentialApp, the setting is shared between
the EssentialApp and the EssentialAppTests. So, my proposal is to remove it
and put it at the project level. So, it's going to be in the project shared.
Again, checking. It's still resolved to iPhone and iPad. And same here.
And the last one I want to look at is the product BundleIdentifier.
So, we see that this is different for each target because it composes
com.essentialDeveloper and the name of the target.
But we already know the targetName is resolvable to our variable. So, we can take
use of that. The only case where the setting doesn't match the targetName is the EssentialApp,
where instead of using the EssentialApp targetName, we use a different String,
which is EssentialAppCaseStudy. So, we will move this into the shared File.
Replace with targetName. And we will delete all the settings, except for the one that doesn't
match, which is the EssentialApp. So, we will delete all the settings except for the one that
doesn't match, which is the EssentialApp. So, we are removing these.
We'll keep this one. And we can also delete this. So, now we only have two entries. One is shared,
where we use the variable targetName, and the other is an explicit different value just for the
EssentialApp target. To make sure everything works, we'll use product BundleIdentifier.
And we see the Result value on EssentialDeveloper EssentialAppTests.
On EssentialDeveloper EssentialAppTests.
For the EssentialApp, it's still EssentialAppCaseStudy. So, this is exactly what we wanted.
And for our EssentialFeed targets, we'll see that the values are correct.
For EssentialFeed, EssentialFeed Test, and so on. So, again, I will commit this.
And the diff is, again, very, very simple. Now, I hope these examples clarify a bit how you can
use xcconfig files, and especially how to detect the application and how to resolve it.
Thank you. And now, if anyone still has questions,
are there any drawbacks with this approach you've ever experienced?
Like I mentioned in the comparison section, it can be cumbersome for people that weren't exposed to
using xcconfig files to understand how they work, especially when they reference other files, like
I've shown, and stuff like that. But I think every use case is different. So, depending on the
needs of the projects you have, they might or might not come in handy. I've used them in projects
where, I don't know, we were many developers, like 50, 60 developers, and they were super helpful
because sometimes somebody would just, I don't know, change a build setting by mistake, and we
would only see it very late, especially if the project File is too big, then some diffs will not
work. So, even GitHub will show you that the File is too big and cannot show you the diffs.
So, we ended up with xcconfig files and some CI rules, where if you change the build setting,
you'd have to add some explanation about why you changed the setting.
So, yeah, like drawbacks, like I said, probably setting it up and understanding how it works.
But I didn't have any problems, or once you understand the syntax, which is pretty simple.
And again, this is not like a recommendation of everybody should start using xcconfig files.
It's just understand their power and when it suits you to use them. Another question. Sorry,
I can't read the name because it's acrylic. Do you know how to automatically sort files when we add
them to a project? Unfortunately, I don't, but if I'm not mistaken, yeah, there's a sort by name. So,
that probably, yeah, should work. So, you can just use this one. I probably got the habit of
re-adding them from back when this setting wasn't available. So, yeah, you can use because if I try
to, I don't know, put them out of order here and then sort, yeah, they're back in order. So.
Okay. I see another question in the chat. If I use different DB, like CoreData on test target
and debug, can I configure which File to use on debug and on Testing with xcconfig? It can be done,
but I really, I'm not sure why would you have like a different DB depending on configuration.
You can Embed them all and you can use the composition rule to compose differently.
Another question, is it possible to pass all these build settings via CommandLine build? Yes,
it's possible, but I still recommend you keep them somewhere. So, it's even the Xcode project
or xcconfig files, but they're stored in source control. So, if I check out your project, it should
be ready to, and I should be able to build it pretty quickly. So, having the Xcode project setUp
properly is very important and that's why passing them to the CommandLine doesn't really
help. I think what you want is to have all the settings configured in Xcode and from the CommandLine
you just invoke the action you want, like Xcode build or archive. Those were all the questions.
Thank you for tuning in and being available at the end for the Q&A section. Thank you and see you soon.
Bye.