Hi everyone, and welcome back to the iOS tooling series.
I'm very excited to be here today with you, as I've been really waiting for this lecture
to happen.
Why?
Because it's one of my favorite topics regarding Xcode and iOS, which is talking about the
Xcode build process.
I really know how frustrating it is to spend hours understanding and fixing build failures
or just trying to get Xcode to do the things you want it to do.
Or having to constantly wait for Xcode to finish indexing or building, where you struggle
to hold to your idea until you can put it into code.
Understanding how the Xcode build process works and how you can help it be more efficient
is a fundamental piece of information for a senior developer.
This will allow you to be more productive in Xcode, create faster builds, fix issues
quicker, not to mention stand out in interviews.
So stay tuned.
We'll explain the steps from source code to executable code, which apply to most programming
languages and see how compilers work in general.
We'll see what the Xcode build process consists of and try to explain what happens when we
press build or command B.
We'll dive into what the build system considers to be dependencies.
And we'll see how we can help it by providing extra dependency information to speed it up.
The linker is this less known part of the build system, but really important.
To put it simply, the linker's job is to merge all the outputs created by the compiler into
a single output.
We'll explain how the linker works and why it's important to the build system.
And we'll wrap it up with the Q&A.
Programming has evolved a lot during time.
In the beginning, programmers were just a handful of people that knew how to write code,
which was directly executed by machines, known as machine code, as the one you can see.
But reading and writing such code is really hard, slow, and Error prone.
So the programmers invested time into creating programming languages.
As I mentioned, this piece of machine code is actually taken from the Xcode executable,
a small part of it, of course.
Programming languages are just abstractions that allow us to express better in code.
Like the one you see on the left is a Swift hello word.
Modern languages allow us to write code that reads like a story, making it a lot easier
to understand and create.
So while on the left of the slide you see some one line of Swift code, on the right
you see a part of the 33 kilobytes of machine code that's generated after compiling this
Swift code.
It's really easy today to create apps with the help of an advanced IDE like Xcode, advanced
programming languages like Swift, and a large number of frameworks which have out of the
box solutions to most problems.
Here you can see the CPU instructions that are part of the hello word example we saw
on the previous slide.
Also pretty difficult to understand and to follow.
To be able to write code in a human readable programming language and translate it into
valid machine code, we needed a tool, preferably automated, that could do that.
This tool is called Compiler and it automates translating high level source code into low
level executable machine code.
So the developers can focus on writing the source code.
The number of existing compilers is large and it grows by the day.
There are compilers for very simple programming languages to very advanced compilers like
the Swift compiler, which is actually made of many sub components.
This Domain of compilers is a very complex one.
I remember I took a one year course during university and only got to stretch its surface.
So today, in the interest of time, we'll try to cover the essence of the compilation process
and dig deeper into the particularities of the compilers we use when programming for
Apple platforms.
But independent of the language or the compiler, there are a few components which are part
of the compilation process, which, as I said, transform source code into executable machine
code.
There's a component called pre compiler, which is a program that runs just before the compiler
and processes the input data, which is code to produce output data, which is again code
for the compiler to use as input.
Not all the compilers have a pre compiler, but the C based languages like C or Objective-C
do.
To be more precise, the pre compiler is actually a sub component of the compiler.
The name compiler is primarily used for programs that translate source code from a high level
programming language to a lower level language like assembly language, object code or machine
code to create an executable program.
A compiler is likely to perform some or all of the following operations, often called
phases pre processing, also known as pre compiling, lexical analysis, parsing, semantic analysis,
conversions of input programs to their intermediate representation, code optimization, code generation.
Compilers generally implement these phases as modular components, promoting efficient
design and correctness of transformations of source input to target output.
Finally, the linker is a program that takes one or more object files generated by a compiler
or an Assembler and combines them into a single executable File, library File, or just another
object File.
This is just the general theory of compilers.
Now let's dig into the particularities of the Xcode build process.
There are a number of actions that you can do in Xcode, run, test, profile, analyze,
archive, build, runs SwiftUI previews and more.
Behind doors, all these actions rely on building one or more of the targets in your project.
You already know Xcode uses workspaces and projects to organize files and tasks into
targets.
Since you want to build different products from your project, you have the ability to
group them into different targets and share code, resources, settings, and more between
these targets.
A target specifies a product to build, like an app in the case of the EssentialApp.
A framework like the EssentialFeed framework, a Bundle or a unit test Bundle like the EssentialFeedTests.
Xcode uses a build process composed of many tasks, which are created based on the type
of target being built to basically translate from resources like Swift files, Objective-C
headers and source files, storyboards, asset catalogs, and more into the final executable.
This is basically what happens when you press command B. Apple ships two different compilers
which are embedded in Xcode, Clang for compiling C-based languages like C, C++, Objective-C,
Objective-C++, and a Swift compiler for compiling Swift code.
They both translate source code files into object files.
Object files contain pieces of executable code, but are not executable on their own
as they have missing information.
At the end, the output files from both compilers are used by the linker to create a single
executable for each target.
This time, there's no missing information.
So this is real executable that the system can run.
We'll see in a few minutes how the linker does this.
Some of the tasks which I mentioned executed during the build process are compiling sources
like Swift sources, Objective-C files, C++, and more.
Generating headers or files like the Swift interface header here, compiling storyboards
and asset catalogs which are catalogs that contain your assets.
Run strips, processing plists like the Info.plist, linking other modules, code signing,
and more.
Now most of these tasks in the build process are performed by running command-line tools
like Clang, LD, AC tool, IB tool, code sign, and so on.
These tools have to be executed with a very specific set of arguments in a particular
order based on the configuration of your Xcode project.
So what the build system does for you is to automate the execution of these tasks each
time you perform a build.
Since there can be many tasks involved in a build process, it's definitely not something
you want to be manually typing into the terminal as we'll see in a few seconds.
Let the build system do that for you by using the Xcode actions we mentioned earlier like
build or archive or the Xcode build command from command-line.
Remember we can inspect the results and tasks of a build log using the report navigator.
Let's do that.
I'll select my last build here and first of all, we notice that this report navigator
has a filter at the top with two controls.
The first control allows the all or recent options.
All means all the messages from the past builds, while recent will only show the messages executed
for the last build.
The other filter controls which types of messages you see, all the messages, all the issues
including Errors or Errors only.
If I use these filters on my successful build, there's no Errors, but if I use an older build
that had Errors, I can see just the Errors.
I'm going to use my last build here and show you that each of these tasks which are listed
for each target can be expanded by using a small icon at each task line has at its right.
So let's look at the command for building some Swift like this one.
As you can see, the CommandLine is pretty huge.
Let's use a command for compiling a Storyboard, this time a bit shorter, and we can also take
a look at one link command which is linking the EssentialFeed iOS in this case, which
uses the LD command.
As you can see, these commands are usually very long and have many arguments, some of
which are directly controlled through build settings.
When the build fails, when the build is slow or just doesn't do exactly what we want, we
can inspect the details of each task and understand it better.
The tasks in a build process are executed in a particular order.
The order in which tasks are executed is determined from the dependency information that is the
task, the input that a Task consumes, and the output that it produces.
The compilation task consumes a source File like the SceneDelegate Swift File as input
and produces an object File like the SceneDelegate.o as output.
Similarly, for Objective-C, the compilation takes a myfile.m as input and produces
myfile.o object File as output.
A linker task is more interesting because it takes multiple entries or inputs.
In this case, it takes all the object files from the target that are the Result of previous
compilation tasks like the myfile.o, AppDelegate.o, FeedUIComposer.o, and
so on.
But also the EssentialFeed framework that is linked to my target and produces an executable.
This is the EssentialApp executable that will go into the EssentialApp Bundle.
Compilation tasks are usually independent from each other, so they can run in parallel.
The linker task needs all the outputs from the compilation tasks in the same target,
so it will have to wait for all of them to complete before it can run.
The build system uses dependency information to determine the order in which tasks should
be run and which tasks can be run in parallel, and we call this dependency order.
So what happens when you press build?
Well, the first step is for the build system to read the build description from your Xcode
project File.
It takes into account all the files in the project, the targets, the dependency relationship,
and the build settings, which we talked about in previous lectures.
And it turns everything into a tree-like structure called a directed graph.
Let's see how this graph looks like.
In our case, building the EssentialApp depends on compiling assets and storyboards and processing
the Info.plist File, but also on linking the EssentialApp executable.
To link the executable, of course, we need to compile the Objective-C files first, if
there are any.
Objective-C files compilation depends on generating the Swift header interface.
To generate the Swift header interface, we need to compile the Swift files.
So this task depends on compiling the Swift files.
I just mentioned a few of them.
What we can notice here is between these build tasks that there can be direct dependencies,
like in the case of the SceneDelegate Swift File that uses the FeedUIComposer.
Also, some of these files use entities from the EssentialFeed Framework.
So they depend on that task, too.
Why?
Because the EssentialFeed Framework is listed into the build phases of the EssentialApp
under link binary with libraries.
Finally, compiling the Swift files depends on compiling the bridging header.
While this is just a simplified representation of a build graph, the full graph, which has
more tasks, represents all the dependencies between the inputs and output files in the
project and the tasks that will be executed to process them.
Next, the low-level execution process, since this graph, looks at the dependency specifications
and figures out which tasks to execute, the sequence or order in which they must run,
and which tasks can be run in parallel, then proceeds to execute.
But the bigger your project, the longer it will take for the build process to finish.
So you don't want to run all of these tasks every time you build.
Instead, the build system might only execute a subset of the tasks in the graph, depending
on the changes you've made to your project since the last build.
We refer to this as an incremental build, and having accurate dependency information
is very important in order for incremental builds to work correctly and efficiently.
If we just made a change to the FeedUIComposer since the last build, the build system will
detect this and only execute the compile FeedUIComposer task and all the tasks that depend
on it, skipping the rest of the tasks, which can definitely speed up the build.
But how does the build system actually detect changes?
Well, each task has a signature, which is the sort of hash that's computed from various
information related to the task.
This information includes the task's inputs, like File paths, modification timestamps,
the CommandLine used to actually perform the command, and other task-specific metadata,
such as the version of the compiler.
The build system keeps track of the signatures of tasks in both the current and the previous
build so that it knows whether to rerun a Task each time a build is performed.
Even the signature of any given task is different than the signature it had in the previous
build, then the build system reruns that task.
If they are the same, then it's skipped.
Let's go back to the Xcode build log and do a clean.
Now I'm going to do a build, which usually a build after a clean is a clean build.
And we see this build took around 3.8 seconds on my pretty fast machine and had quite a
few tasks.
Now if I build again, I see my build just took half a second, and the number of tasks
listed are much fewer than the tasks we executed for a clean build.
Again, I think this is pretty obvious.
There's something interesting here which I'm not entirely sure why.
Even without the change in the EssentialFeed, we still got the system to recompile all the
Swift files, but that might be just a glimpse of the compiler.
The essential thing here is that we got a much faster build and much fewer build tasks.
Now that we see this, we ask ourselves, how can we help the build system?
Well, to understand this, we need to think about the build system in terms of dependencies
and not about order of tasks.
The order of tasks is the job of the system.
To understand this, we need to understand where do dependencies come from.
So I'm using the project editor and opening the build rules tab.
Because under build rules, we have the first set of dependencies, which are built-in dependencies.
For certain tasks, dependency information comes from knowledge built into the build
system.
The build system ships with rules for the compiler, the linker, the asset catalog and
Storyboard pre-processor and so on.
These rules define what kind of files are accepted as input, as well as the outputs
that are produced.
These build rules you see here are out of the box.
You don't need to do anything to use them.
This is just a reminder that Xcode uses build rules to determine how to handle each type
of File.
This is why, for instance, the system can use the Swift compiler when compiling a.
Swift File, or use Clang for C files, or a Storyboard compiler to compile storyboards.
Other type of dependencies are target dependencies.
To see these, I'm going to move to the build phases tab and check out the first entry here,
which is dependencies.
Target dependencies roughly determine the order in which targets are built.
In some cases, the build system can compile sources of different targets in parallel.
Previously in older versions of Xcode, when a target was built, it required the compilation
of all the dependent targets to be completed before it could start.
Since Xcode 10 and its new build system, targets can start building sooner.
This means that your compile sources phase can start earlier, providing you with some
parallelization for free.
Now, if you try to add a dependency, we see that only the targets from the current project
are listed here.
This is because in our current setUp, the EssentialApp workspace contains the EssentialFeed
and EssentialApp projects at the same level.
So the targets from the EssentialFeed project are NotVisible in my dependencies selector.
But there's something we can do about that.
We can move the EssentialFeed project inside the EssentialApp project, and then the dependencies
will become visible so we can set our explicit dependencies to EssentialFeed and EssentialFeed
framework.
Let's do that as an exercise.
I'm going to draw drag and drop the EssentialFeed on the EssentialApp, uncheck the add
to target because it's already there, and hit finish.
If I expand the EssentialApp project, I see that the EssentialFeed project is embedded
inside it.
So I can delete this reference here as it's duplicated now.
Now, if I go back to my EssentialApp dependencies and use the plus button, I can see all the
targets from the EssentialFeed project.
If I can set my explicit dependencies to EssentialFeed and EssentialFeed iOS frameworks, I'll
do a clean just to make sure and then a build and hopefully everything will still work.
But as we've noticed before, we already had the EssentialFeed framework and the EssentialFeed
iOS framework listed on the link binary with libraries.
This is another type of dependency called implicit dependency and coupled with an option
that's available on a scheme.
So if I open the scheme editor and check out build options, find implicit dependencies,
if this option is enabled and it is enabled by default, the build system will establish
an implicit dependency on the target even if it's not listed in the target dependencies.
So again, since we had EssentialFeed and EssentialFeed iOS frameworks listed on the
link binary with libraries for the EssentialApp, they were already implicit dependencies.
So we actually did not gain anything by making that dependency explicit.
Because of that, I will revert my changes.
Let me reopen the project, clean, build, and we're back as we were.
With the two frameworks I mentioned linked implicitly.
The next type of dependency is also derived from the build phases tab.
You can see here a number of sections, sometimes like copy headers, we have compiled sources,
copy Bundle resources, and more.
The tasks associated with each of these phases are usually running in groups according to
the order in which the phases are listed here.
But there's a catch.
The build system might ignore that order if it knows better and knows that there are cases
when just having the wrong build phase order can cause build issues or failures.
So make sure to understand your dependencies and verify that the build phases are in the
right sequence.
Another type of dependencies are scheme order dependencies.
So again, I'm going to select my current scheme EssentialApp, edit scheme.
And under the build tab, we can see all the targets that are going to be built.
At the top, there's the build order option, which has two variants.
The default one is the dependency order, which means the target listed here will be built
in parallel depending on the dependency information.
So you get better build performance and this order of targets does not matter.
However, if you set it to manual order, which by the way is now deprecated, Xcode will attempt
to build your targets in the order you listed them in the build action of the scheme one
by one.
Target dependencies still have higher priority in determining which targets build first,
but otherwise Xcode will respect that ordering.
So it might be tempting to use this as it gives you a predictable build order even if
you haven't set your dependencies correctly, but you're sacrificing a lot of parallelization
when you do this and slowing down your build.
Apple recommends that you leave the build order setting set to dependency order, setUp
your targets correctly and don't rely on ordering.
So how can we as developers help the build system by providing valuable dependency information?
Well, first of all, if you're using any run streets, I'll just create an empty one.
Make sure to tell the build system what its inputs, like input files or input File lists
and outputs files or File lists are.
This lets the build system avoid rerunning the script tasks unnecessarily and can help
make sure that they are executed in the right order.
You can define the inputs and outputs in the run script phase editor.
Note that if you don't define any input or output files, the task will be executed with
every build, so make sure that's what you want.
Another thing we can do is avoid auto linking for project dependencies.
This is actually a build setting that's available for the Clang compiler.
And as you can see, this is on by default.
Being a setting on the Clang compiler means this applies to C based languages only.
What this setting does is it allows the compiler to automatically link the frameworks responding
to any modules you import without having to explicitly link them in your link library's
build phase.
However, it's important to note that auto link does not establish dependencies on that
framework at the build system level.
So it won't guarantee that the target you depend on is actually built before you try
to link against it.
Google recommends you disable this setting and instead make sure you link all the frameworks
you use explicitly.
I also recommend that.
Another thing we can do, and we've already discussed, is add explicit dependencies.
However, for targets in your own projects, make sure you add these explicit dependencies.
Or you might need to do an exercise like the one we did, where you drag and drop another
Xcode project in your project's File navigator in order to reveal the targets of other projects
you depend on, like we did when we dragged the essential feeds into the EssentialApp
project.
In conclusion, with accurate dependency information, the build system can better parallelize your
build and help ensure that you get consistent results every time so you can spend less time
building and more time developing.
Now let's talk about the linker.
The linker is a program that takes one or more object files generated by a compiler
and combines them into a single executable File or a library.
In the case of the Xcode build process, the linker takes the object File produced by both
Clang and Swift compiler and combines them into a single executable File.
This is pretty unique, as there are few systems that accept combining different languages
and compilers like that.
It's also done with a lot of under-the-hood work that the build system does for us.
It's important to understand that the linker only moves and patches code, and it cannot
create code.
First, we need to understand what a symbol is.
So a symbol is just a name that refers to a fragment of code or data.
A fragment of code is just a piece of code.
These fragments may refer to other symbols which you would see if you write a function
that calls another function.
Symbols can have attributes on them that affect how the linker behaves.
One example is a weak symbol, which is an annotation on a symbol that says it might
not be there when the executable runs or called runtime.
An example of this would be using the atAvailable markup.
Now I marked this new Store class available only on iOS 15 and above, which means that
if we are in an app that runs on previous versions of the OS, this class will not be
available on these versions.
So the linker needs to handle this class differently, as it might not exist on the operating system
that runs it.
Another example would be the weak linking of a framework.
So on the EssentialApp, as an exercise, I'm going to link against a very new framework,
which is the code location UI framework that was introduced also in iOS 15.
Again, since our app supports older versions of iOS, if we set this dependency as default
on the required, it will Result in an app Crash when running on iOS 14 or over.
But we have the option to set the link type as optional.
What this does is it tells the linker that this framework might not be there when the
app runs.
So the linker is preparing the executable for that scenario.
This is important because one of the linker's job is to determine which symbols are definitely
going to be there versus symbols that it may have to deal with at runtime.
So we have symbols, which are names referring to code and data.
We know the compilers generate object files.
Those object files are just collections of those code and data fragments.
They contain executable code, but they are not executable on their own.
While they are compiled code, they aren't finished.
They have missing bits, which is what the linker is going to glue together and fix up.
In our example, the SceneDelegate invokes a NullStore initializer.
And the NullStore is defined in the different File.
When the compiler tries to compile SceneDelegate, it treats this like a promise or a contract,
like there is a File somewhere defining a class named NullStore, which contains an initializer
with the signature.
For the compiler, that is enough, and it marks the NullStore initializer as an undefined
symbol in the object File it produces.
But when the linker processes that object File, it really needs to resolve this symbol.
So it will search in the inputs it has received for actual symbol definition.
As you remember, the inputs are the object files from the same target, as well as the
link to libraries and frameworks.
The point here is the linker will either find the definition of that symbol and Embed it
into a binary or fail with the linker Error.
This is important because at runtime, there is no component that does this look up for
symbols, as this would be inefficient.
So the linker must resolve all the symbols.
So the executable it creates contains all the information about how to resolve its symbol.
Some symbols can exist in other modules, like dynamic frameworks.
That's the case of our HTTPClient, which is defining the EssentialFeed framework.
The linker will include information about exactly where and how to load this symbol.
Or when linking against system frameworks like UIKit or Foundation, it will Embed the
information where they are available and how to load them.
As a note, at runtimes, there's a component in the operating system called a loader, which
will load the executable into memory.
But it will also load other modules, like system frameworks, based on the information
from the executable that the linker has included.
Back to the linker.
The linker takes two kinds of input files, object files, or.o, and libraries.
Dylibs are dynamic libraries, TBDs are text-based, Dylib Stubs, and.ar archives are static
libraries.
So what are libraries?
Libraries are files that define symbols that are not part of the target you're building.
The dynamic libraries are files that expose code and data fragments for executables to
use.
The system frameworks distributed as part of the system contain such dynamic libraries.
Like we mentioned, UIKit, Foundation, MapKit, and all the others.
But you can also create your own dynamic libraries, and there's a good chance you've used dynamic
libraries from third parties.
TBD files, or text-based Dylib Stubs, these are only used for distributing SDKs to reduce
size, so they're basically lighter versions of the frameworks, containing just the name
of the symbols without the bodies, as the bodies are only needed at runtime.
And finally, static archive, or static libraries, those.a files are just collections of object
files, or.o files, that have been built with the ar tool.
According to the ar docs, the ar utility creates and maintains groups of files Combined into
an archive.
This is very similar to the zip format you're probably familiar with.
So.a is basically like a zip of object files.
Regarding linking, there's an important difference worth mentioning about static and dynamic
libraries.
But please note, this is just one of the many differences between them.
So don't use only this information to decide which one to use in your project.
This is subject for a more thorough analysis.
We only care here about linking.
So when using non-system dynamic libraries, the linker cannot make any improvements, like
excluding symbols that are not used.
The linker uses a cautious Strategy, so these libraries will be installed or embedded at
their full size.
On the other hand, the linker can work more efficiently with static libraries.
So if you reference a symbol from a library that is linked statically, the linker pulls
out the corresponding object File containing that symbol from the archive and includes
it into the executable.
But it will not include the other files.
The effect of this is that the final executable will contain close to only the symbols it
really uses and, of course, other symbols that were defined in the same files.
So let's recap what we learned today.
So we learned that the compilation process or the process from source files to executable
relies on two Main components.
The compiler that takes source files at input and produces object files at output and the
linker that combines these object files and references to other link modules into a final
executable.
We know that Apple has created a unique ecosystem that relies on two compilers, Clang for C-based
languages like C or Objective-C and the Swift compiler for Swift.
We've explored the way the build system uses dependencies to create a build graph and we
clarified how incremental builds work differently and more efficiently than clean builds.
We went through what dependencies are for the build system.
The built-in dependencies provided by build rules, explicit dependencies or target dependencies.
You mark dependencies to other targets in the same project or sub-project.
Implicit dependencies listed under link binary with libraries.
The order of build phases and the order of targets in the scheme editor.
And we can help the build system by declaring inputs and outputs for our run scripts, avoid
the auto-linking option and adding explicit and implicit dependencies using the target
dependencies or link binary with libraries.
That's it.
Thanks for your patience and if there are any questions, I'd be happy to answer them.
Oh, we can always talk about him on Slack.
Oh, sorry, I had...
Just a second here, okay.
Okay, can you see me, can you hear me?
Yes.
Cool.
So I have a question about non Xcode IDE and this is AppCode by JetBrains.
As far as I know, Xcode build is a CommandLine program that we use for building.
So Xcode is just a fancy and beautiful interface, but basically everything happens in a CommandLine
environment.
So do you know anything different that we have in AppCode?
And what do you think, how it works over there?
Maybe they invented something new or they just replicate the same order, the same process
that we have in Xcode.
Interesting question, I actually used AppCode myself like a few years back.
And I know Mike used to be a fan of AppCode.
Well, what I know is that they do not use Xcode build behind doors, but I might be mistaken.
So they just use the compiler commands like the Swift C or the, I think it's LLVM for
the Clang compilation lines.
Or Xcode build is actually embedded into Xcode, so I don't think AppCode can access and use
that.
I think they have their own components which parse the project File and then try to do
the build.
So that's one reason why I think not many developers use these different IDEs like AppCode,
because they might actually generate different results than Xcode.
So when that happens, you're basically on your own, especially if you're doing anything,
I don't know, out of the box, there's little to no help available.
I used it like in parallel, so at some point I know AppCode was really nice for refactorings
and finding usages of entities and stuff like that.
So for that, yeah, definitely I was preferring AppCode, but I would still do my due diligence
and build with Xcode just to be sure everything is in check and my changes from AppCode are
not breaking anything.
Yeah, also CI helps here.
I'm not sure if I responded to your question entirely.
Yeah, basically that's how I use AppCode on my own.
I use it only for writing code, for editing code, for coding itself, but when I setUp
something, when I add target, even when I change target shape for different files, I
prefer to use Xcode.
I just wondering is it possible to ever to switch to AppCode totally, because now I have
to open IDs, Xcode and AppCode.
Yeah, basically that answered my question and if I'm allowed to ask another one, since
I'm already talking, yeah.
I'm wondering about this new fancy tools like Tuist.
Really it uses YAML files to generate Xcode projects, so you don't have any collisions
and any problems with big projects when you refactor it or like merge conflicts or something.
And what do you think, is it like something that can be used in big production projects
or it's something like a toy for playing and just forget about it?
Yeah, I know about this.
I just want to quickly say something about the first topic about AppCode.
I don't really see a way where you could go around Xcode because Apple is really diligent
about making that their primary tool, so I don't think we can do that.
And that's one of the risks you expose you and your team to when you use any third party
tool like AppCode or the other tools you mentioned and I'll talk about them right now.
But that's always the risk when you go to third party tools, they might not work in
a Future version, you might be entirely broken in your workflow because of this.
So it's a risk, sometimes not worth taking.
So our strong recommendation with the program is to always use the default tools from Apple,
which have been maintained over time.
I've been doing this since iOS 2 and none of them have really disappeared while third
party tools come and go.
Yeah, about your other question where I think Xcode project, there's a number of tools that
can generate an Xcode project.
Yeah, I know teams that use these, they can be useful, especially like you said for avoiding
conflicts because if there's no project File checked into the source control, there's no
conflicts when you add a File or remove a File or something like that.
But again, you are adding this risk of, I don't know, these two not supporting whatever
new SDK or build version and then you're stuck.
So again, take it with a grain of salt.
My preference is to keep to the standard tools unless I really need to.
So for instance, if we see a lot of conflicts in the past, I know, months or weeks, we can
talk in the team and say, okay, where are these conflicts coming from?
What are the available solutions?
Because sometimes one solution can be just moving to XC config files like I showed in
another lecture, or there can be other options, not necessarily moving all the project generation
to a third party.
But again, that's something that each team has to decide on its own.
But I think there's more harm in actually many people just starting to use all these
third parties without making sure they really need them, as opposed to the small number
of teams that really need those projects.
So it's a close call, I think.
Well, yeah, it's not only avoiding merge conflicts.
It's also easier to read when you read this YAML File, you can see what like custom build
rules, build phases, scripts or something.
You can see it right here, right now, in Xcode projects, you have to jump over the different
tabs and search for specific parameters, specific sections.
It's not so clear what's going on in Xcode projects.
It's like too fancy with a lot of UI.
That's also the problem with Xcode projects.
Yeah, I don't know if you saw that, I think it was one of the first lectures in this series
where I actually showed the PBX File format and how it's structured.
So this is the File backing up the Xcode project.
So yeah, I agree with that partially, but not entirely because Apple still knows what
it's doing.
So I need to trust them on that one.
In my experience, even ramping up junior developers to a setUp like where they need to generate
their project File and need to do some custom thing to add new settings to a YAML, all that
can really complicate the way they interact.
If it's, again, if all your teammates are on board with that, it might be a really good
decision for a particular case.
But what we're teaching here cannot be built on top of that as a standard.
So yeah, sure, it's a kind of custom solution.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you for answering.
Thanks for the questions.
Hi.
Thanks a lot for your election.
It has been very informative.
Though I have a question a little bit specific particularly to Swift versions.
So basically, there is a thing called Swift ABI, which was introduced a couple of years
ago, which basically provides a way for different Swift runtime versions to load Swift symbols
compiled by older versions of the compiler.
And my question is, do you think it's reasonable to say you have a couple of modules in your
app and the core module is not being modified at all for years, for example.
So you recompile it and commit the binary to a repository or HTTP server to just download
it to a Swift Package manager, for example.
And do you think it's reasonable to recompile it every Swift compiler version release along
with, or do you think it's fine as long as it's working to leave, say, for example, a
library compiled with Swift 5.0 to be bundled up with a bunch of frameworks, dynamic libraries
and the final executable, which were compiled with Swift 5.4, for example.
That's a very interesting topic.
So for people that I see, you know the situation pretty well about ABI.
For people that might not be in possession of such depth, basically this ABI feature,
like Ruslan said, was only added in, I think, in Swift 5.
So before that, any executables were bound to the Swift version they were actually compiled
with, so you could not compile something with Swift 3.0 and use it together with Swift 4.0
just because of this ABI difference.
That's the reason why if you ever used Swift before, some Swift libraries were actually
system libraries were embedded into your app or framework just to be able to run these
at runtime because, like I said, they were really dependent on the version of Swift you
use to compile them and at runtime the system might have different versions and you would
just end up with a Crash.
But since Swift 5, I think, this problem was addressed, it was always a goal, but other
features delayed the ABI stability.
And now that we have this stability, we can, like Ruslan said, we can mix and merge, so
we can use modules compiled with Swift 5 together with modules compiled with Swift 5.4 or 5.5
and so on and even Future versions.
I think as long as everything works, I don't see a big problem, even if Swift releases
does not super often, so recompiling those modules once every, I don't know, a few months
is not a huge pain.
On the other side, the new versions of Swift might not really work for that codebase, so
it may require some changes that also needs to be factored in.
And on the other hand, this is like the more cautious approach, the more futuristic approach
is where you might want to use the new features into that Swift code, so like the latest async
APIs or anything new that Swift adds.
But like I said, if you're happy with your module, if the Tests pass and it seems to
function as appropriate, I don't see a need to recompile or redeploy that module.
So yeah, that's how I look into it.
It's not a clear answer where yeah, you should or you shouldn't, it's more like it really
depends on the whole situation.
And of course, like how much time does it take to build, if you need like a special
build machine or configuration to build that project, there's many verticals here which
I would advise to consider.
All right, thanks a lot for your answer.
Any other questions?
Oh, Sergey is waving.
Okay, also one question, probably it's not like 100% related to the current topic, but
I just gave her opinions from people who knows, they think so.
Let me ask you, what's your preference about having this nested projects inside other projects?
Like in one situation, we can have one project and different targets for different frameworks
or different platforms, like one project and then we have tvOS, macOS, iOS and different
frameworks or we can wrap every target in its own project and Embed this project into
like one big workspace.
How does it feel like what approach is better and how it affects build time?
Did you get it?
Yeah, I think I did.
So you're asking whether it's a better version to make these sub-dependencies between projects
like Embed a project in another project or keep them at the same level or just keep all
the targets in the same project like these different variations of setups.
Again, I think at some level when the question is complicated enough, the answer is always
it depends and in this case, I would say I never really fancied this sub-project setUp.
I think it's a bit unnatural for me.
So that's why I like the standard setUp in the essential feeds use case repo where all
the projects are on the same level.
And like I explained with these find implicit dependencies, basically the build system gets
all the information it needs without this option to add explicit target dependencies.
I don't see another reason to Embed them.
Of course, if it's a different project like coming from a third party or something like
that, which I saw in, like if you're not using a, I don't know, Swift Package manager or
another dependency manager and you just get some project from somebody and you want to
link against it, again, you can use the sub-project approach or keep it on the same level in your
workspace.
It's also a personal preference.
The difference is not that big, so you only get a project reference in your Xcode proj
File.
And I guess where they all might become too crowded is like you get all these schemes
together in the same workspace.
So it might be too much.
To launch this project separately and work on the Embed project separately without launching
the big one.
Yeah.
For example, if you wrap some small Model in the project and you nested it in the big
one, you can launch it without having everything in your memory and have your example app wrapper
around your current scope and everything works fine.
And only then you can nest it in the big one and you can separate your workflow from the
big one.
I think that's the only thing that you have to consider, like are you going to launch
only this project separately or not?
That's the only way that I considered before and now I'm just wondering maybe there is
something pitfall.
So anything I should know about approaches managing different targets, basically it's
how we manage the set of targets in your projects.
So I think one thing to consider and I've always had bad experiences with this is the
bigger the project, like the more targets, the more projects you have in a workspace,
the more work Xcode has to do.
So if, for instance, if you're using like 20 CocoaPods with source files, every time
you open that project, Xcode has to index everything.
So it deals with a lot of symbols, a lot of frameworks, and sometimes that can lead to
a bad experience.
Like in our example, it's just a short app with a framework, actually two frameworks,
different projects.
So the setUp is pretty small.
But if you scale that up, it can really lead to something that's hard to maintain.
So that's why one of the recommendations from the program is to rely on modularization
and actually try to have as many modules independent from each other as possible.
While for starters, you can keep everything in the same repo, like the git repository
can be one, but you can have multiple projects there.
And as you said, if I need to work only on, I don't know, in this case, the Feed, the
EssentialFeed framework, I don't even need to open the workspace.
I can just open that project, deal with just a subset of the files, run my Tests there,
make sure everything is in check.
And then I get a much better development experience because the test takes fewer, like less time.
Indexing is faster.
Xcode probably won't restart every five minutes because auto-complete is off and all that
stuff.
From my experience, big projects always have these issues around indexing and also building.
So the more decoupled you can create your setUp, the better.
But this is something you go towards incrementally.
So I wouldn't recommend starting with, I don't know, 20 modules, which each has one File
of 10 lines just for the sake of it.
So build the project as you go, define modules as they appear, and you can use this approach
that's also in the program where you separate on a conceptual level.
You don't actually draw them into different targets and frameworks, but you keep them
separated and clear of each other.
And if you need to extract them, you can.
So that's all something you and your team need to decide when you are making these moves.
But I've seen a lot of bad workflows where it takes a lot of time to build the whole
thing, to test it.
Just using Xcode with it is an unbearable experience.
It might have gone better in the meantime, but nevertheless, something to consider.
Yeah, I agree 100% on everything you said.
I had experience working with a really big project called Build took like 45 minutes.
I just went to lunch and then I just, yeah, it had this 70 sub-projects inside it, really,
really big, huge project.
And I struggled with Xcode a lot and AppCode just freeze like in the first two seconds.
It was like nothing to do.
I purchased AppCode and it just didn't work at all.
Like I couldn't even type something.
I know, I feel you.
I quit.
So now I'm fine.
And why this is sad is because for once your developer experience is so bad.
And I've been on projects like that where the context switching in your mind, like you
were trying to work on a Task, you have your idea, maybe done the implementation and until
you get the feedback from the Build, from the test, it takes so long that you can't
hold on to your thoughts.
And you probably context switch or talk to somebody in the meantime or do something else.
And then you have to come back to that whole workflow.
It's so bad.
And it's also bad for the business because with smart decisions, this does not need to
happen.
Like this is probably the, I don't know, the end Result of people not knowing how to manage
that mess.
So they start with something small and they have no idea how to scale it.
And then everything is just a big mess and a lot of people come with these theories where
once every years you have to rewrite your project from scratch.
And that's not very nice because with the same principles, they're going to write it
in the same way.
So after another three or four years, it's going to be the same.
So I think that's why this course is built on top of the Main program, the Main course.
That's where we have all these recommendations about modularization and clean architecture,
clean design, low coupling between modules.
All these principles are super important if you want to be working on a project that you
don't hate.
So yeah, that's it.
Anyway, thank you for having me.
And if there's any specific questions about these topics, we can, as always Slack is the
way to go and we'll try to give a solid answer.
Sometimes it takes time to do that, but that's fine.
I didn't answer to Ruslan's point, so 45-minute build is a non-addressed tech debt and or
missing build engineers in the team.
Yeah, that's very true.
But sometimes even adding build engineers to the team does not fix the issue.
So I once worked on a project where after adding the build engineers to the team, we
actually went to like a four-hour cycle of build back on CI and running the Tests.
That was just so bad because every time you wanted to get feedback back on a pull request
or something, you would wait for four hours and then get some results, sometimes a failure
and then start to look into why that happened.
So yeah, if it gets to, I think the problem is if you let it get to 45 minutes, like when
it's passed, I know 10, 15 minutes, you start, you need to start to ask questions like why
is this taking so long?
How can we improve it?
How can we, for instance, I know we, Kyle and Mike covered this in a mentoring session.
How can we recompile and test and redeploy only the modules that got changed?
So you don't need to rebuild everything when you know that your changes affect, I don't
know, like only a component.
So there's different approaches which you can take and improve these, but you first
have to care about it.
So if the team sets this as a high priority, then I'm sure solutions can be found if of
course, if the knowledge is there.
All right.
This was nice.
Thanks for staying up till the end and being available for this talk.
So thank you and see you soon.
Bye.