Hi everyone, and welcome back to our tooling series.
Today we'll explore another cool topic
which is mixing Objective-C and Swift together.
This is important because many projects out there
still contain a mix of Swift and Objective-C.
And even those Swift only projects
use the system frameworks
which are mostly written in Objective-C.
So to become a complete senior iOS developer,
it's really important to know
how to mix together the two languages
and how to get the most out of it.
Our plan for today is to understand how Clang
or C-Lang and the Swift compiler work to find declarations
and how to mix Swift and Objective-C code
in different setups.
See how we can make our Objective-C APIs more Swifty,
if that's an accepted word.
And take a look at a common problem,
how we can write Swift code
that uses all the language features
if we need to expose this code to Objective-C.
We'll give you a solution on how to approach this.
And as always, we'll wrap it up with the Q&A,
but if there are questions during the lecture,
I'll try to respond to them as they come.
A quick recap from our previous lecture
about the build system.
We know that Apple ships two different compilers
embedded in Xcode.
C-Lang or Clang is the compiler for the C-based languages
like C, C++, Objective-C, Objective-C++.
The Swift compiler is compiling Swift code.
So an important part of how the build system works
is influenced by how the two compilers work together.
Clang compiles each Objective-C File separately.
If you want to refer to a class from another File,
you have to import a header that declares that class.
We'll dive into how these header File works
in a few minutes,
but I think you can recognize the syntax.
By comparison, Swift used to compile each File separate,
but after several improvements Apple made
to the build system,
the Swift compiler can now compile multiple File at once.
This is not as important as the fact that Swift
was designed not to require headers.
This is because headers are repetitive and hard to manage.
Having no headers makes it easy to get started
with the language and avoids repeating declarations.
However, this means that the Swift compiler
has to perform some additional bookkeeping.
So let's use our EssentialFeed use case repo as always,
and see how the compilers resolve declarations
in different scenarios and how that booking View works.
The EssentialFeed repo has no Objective-C code,
but we'll add some.
I'll start by creating an Objective-C class called Logger
and added it into the EssentialFeed project.
So I will right click the EssentialFeed group,
set new File,
and let's spend a few seconds here
looking at the File templates.
There's an Objective-C File template for implementations
and a header File template for headers.
Since no Objective-C relies on combining header files.h
and implementation files.m,
these templates would be enough.
But there's also the CocoaTouch class template,
which is a helper creating both a header
and an implementation File at the same time.
Let's use this one for convenience.
So I'll double click it.
I'll type the name of my class, which will be Logger.
We'll use Objective-C as our language.
And we'll put it at the root folder.
We can immediately notice some interesting instructions
like this nsassume non-node.
For now, I will just remove those
and we'll talk about them later
because we want to really explain what they do.
So now we have a simple interface Logger
that inherits from NSObject and its implementation File,
both empty.
So how does Objective-C find declarations
from other Objective-C files?
Well, by using headers and importing them.
Anyone using Objective-C is pretty familiar with this.
It's those import statements at the beginning
of the.h or.m Objective-C files.
Header files are a concept that Objective-C
borrowed from C and C++.
What's important to know is the headers
must contain the declarations we want to expose
to other files.
Or put it another way, if we want to expose any entity
to another File or another module,
we need to declare it in a header.
And by entities, of course we mean classes, protocols,
global functions, global variables, enums, and many more.
So the declaration of an entity contains
like a high level signature of that entity
without any concrete implementation.
Let's see this difference.
I'll add a method to myLogger class called log.
It's a simple method that returns Void
and takes a String Message parameter.
First, we see the declaration of the Logger class
marked with add interface and the mention of a subclass
from any subject.
And also another declaration of the log Message.
It just contains the signature, but not the body.
Now let's add the implementation of this Objective-C File.
I added implementation for our log Message method,
we added in the header, but I also added
a private function called private log.
Internally, our public method calls the private one.
What I wanted to highlight here is,
one, this time the definition of the Logger class
marked with add implementation is present in the.mp File.
Then the body of the log function is the definition
in the.mp File, and that we can only use the.mp File
and that we can also add other signatures
and their definitions like this private log Message
that we don't need to expose to other files.
Back to our header File.
It's a best practice to keep the header File
as short as possible.
So make sure to only include the declarations
of entities like classes, methods, protocols
that are needed to be shared with other files.
You can still add their definitions
to the.mp File like we did.
Also for headers, it's recommended to keep
the minimum needed imports in each header.
Keeping the imports limited helps the compiler
easily resolve these imports and the resulting code
will be minimal, the code size will be minimal.
We can define more entities inside our.mp implementation
File without exposing any of them to other files.
So I'll replace this implementation we have now
with a more complex one.
So I added a Logger type enum with two cases,
console and File.
I added a, let's call it a private class Logger helper
which is NotVisible outside the.mp File
that has a class method clean logs.
And to make this clear, we're actually calling
the clean logs from the dialog of our Logger.
So whenever we dialog our Logger, we clean the logs.
Again, all these new entities are available
inside my.mp File, but they're not exposed.
They don't belong to any header.
Now we mentioned this term importing headers
and I wanna clarify what this means.
The hash import is a macro and is very similar
to another macro from C, C++, which is include.
They actually are pretty similar.
You'll simply get replaced by the pre-compiler
with that exact full content of the header File
they point to, like a copy and paste.
So since this happens to all the macros
and it's a recursive process,
it can lead to really big files
and of course, potential duplication of symbols.
To make this more clear,
if we go to the Foundation header definition,
you'll see it actually imports like 170 other header files,
all of them with big bodies.
So you can imagine the size of the simple Logger header
when these macros are expanded.
So between the two, the import macro is a bit more advanced
as it was added for Objective-C
and it avoids duplicating the declarations
if the same files are imported multiple times.
If you have an Objective-C project,
you probably import Foundation or UI key many, many times,
but they still work.
So you don't get like duplicate symbols Error
because of that, which includes in C,
we have to be more careful,
which I'll show you in a second
because the Xcode header File template
contains these instructions.
So during time Objective-C has evolved
and Apple added a new way to do imports.
They are called semantic imports
and they kind of try to replace the hashtag import.
Hashtag import.
They look like at import in the name of the framework,
like this.
Actually, if your grand enabled module build setting
is set to yes, and it is so by default,
even those hashtag import are replaced by the compiler
with at imports or these semantic imports.
So you get this for free without having to manually convert
all your existing imports.
Since they do the same, I will remove the ladder for now.
Using these semantic imports
is more efficient than regular imports,
resulting in faster builds
and especially avoiding compiling issues.
The builds are faster because the compiler
doesn't need to parse the headers
as it can rely on module maps.
We'll talk about module maps in a few minutes.
You might wonder, how does Xcode find these header files
we mentioned here?
Well, it turns out it has a pretty complex mechanism
for locating header files.
It uses different build settings like header search paths
or user header surf paths and more,
as well as on system paths
where the system frameworks live to search for headers.
When you want to share Objective-C code
from one module to another,
you have to share the binary of that module
as well as the headers.
Without each header, the clients of your module
cannot find the declarations inside your module,
so they cannot use your types.
Sharing the headers happens through a build phase,
which is called headers in the recent Xcode,
or it used to be called copy headers in previous ones.
If we expand it, we see three subcategories,
and these are three levels of visibility
that each header can have, public, private, and project.
And to understand them,
I'll create a header File for each one of them
and see how they perform.
We already noticed that the project tab contains one File,
which is the Logger header, which we just added.
By default, adding any header
willSet the visibility to project level,
and we'll see what that means.
For now, I will right click, new File,
use the header File template,
and my first one, I'll call public.
I'll check the EssentialFeed target and hit create.
If I use the inspector on the right,
in the target membership, we see the target
that we just added the File to, which is EssentialFeed,
and a selector next to it.
This controls the visibility I just mentioned.
So since I created my File, namely public,
I want this File to be public, so I'll select public here.
Just a quick note about this File template.
I mentioned earlier that for C headers,
the include directive does not know
how to avoid duplicating symbols.
So a common practice in C, C++ was to guard everything
inside the wrapper of these instructions.
So if public underscore H is not defined, define it,
and end if.
In the next File that we'll try to import this header,
we'll actually find that public underscore H is defined
and skip.
That's how it avoids duplicating symbols.
So back to our flow, we added a new header File
called public.H, and we set the visibility to public.
Now, if we get back to the build phases,
and let's make this a bit bigger.
I see my public.H File under public headers.
I will build, everything builds fine,
and I'll use the finder on the derived data folder
to inspect my Bundle of the EssentialFeed framework.
And I see there's a new folder called headers.
If I look into this header, for now,
I will only see the public.H File I just created.
Please ignore the EssentialFeed Swift,
as we'll talk about it in a few minutes.
A few minutes.
So my public header.H was added to headers folder.
All the clients that will import the EssentialFeed
will be able to import this header
and use the definitions inside.
So all good.
Let's repeat the exercise with another File, header File,
header File, which we'll call project.
I'll also add it to our EssentialFeed
and check that it's visibility set to project.
I can also see it appear under the project group,
which now contains two files.
If I build
this and go back to my Bundle
of the EssentialFeed framework,
I will not be able to find this header anywhere.
That's because a project header is not included
into the module Bundle.
The interface is for use only by implementation File
in the current project.
So the symbols inside this header are NotVisible
to clients at all, only to you.
The third level
is private.
Let's see how this works.
I'll create a header File called private.
I'll also add it to the EssentialFeed
and this time I will choose
the private target membership level.
And I'll see the new header under private headers.
Building,
we see a new folder appeared,
which is called private headers.
A private header is actually copied into your Bundle,
but instead of the headers folder,
it will go into the private headers folder.
A private header is included in the product,
but it's marked private.
Thus the symbols are visible to all your clients,
but the clients should understand
you're not supposed to use them.
You should always avoid importing private headers
as this can lead to breaking changes
in Future releases of that module.
So you don't want to be coupled
with these implementation details.
Now that we've seen all these potential levels,
it's really important that you express your intent
by properly setting the visibility level
to each header in your target.
So for all the versions of Objective-C,
sharing headers was enough
to distribute libraries or frameworks.
Clients would import exactly the headers they want
from the module and be done.
But Apple has created an improved option
to expose your Objective-C code to other modules,
either Objective-C or Swift.
You can use an umbrella header and a module Map.
You probably heard this before,
let's explain what each of them are and how they work.
The umbrella header is the Main header
for File for a framework.
It's nothing fancy, just a simple header
that shares the same name as the framework name.
So in our example, that would be EssentialFeed.h.
Let's create this header to make it even more clear.
So I'll create a new header, I'll call it EssentialFeed.
I'll include it into my target and hit create.
I will delete these macros as we don't need them.
I will import the EssentialFeed public header
we just created.
And I'll also import myLogger.h and try to build.
Oops, I got an Error, let's see why.
We get this umbrella header EssentialFeed not found.
This is a pretty common build Error.
This happens pretty often too.
I forgot to set my umbrella header as public.
This is really important.
When trying to compile this umbrella header,
Clang tries to import all of these headers
and they all must be public,
but our Logger.h File is not public.
So if we make it public,
and now everything should work, okay.
So to recap, I created an umbrella header
which has the exact name as the target it belongs to,
the framework EssentialFeed.
And I had to make it public and all the imports
of headers inside of it need to use public headers.
This umbrella header is used to import
all the public headers you want to expose.
A common example is Foundation.h.
As you can see, it's actually an umbrella
like the name says for other header files.
But what this does is it allows us to use this type of import
where we say import Foundation, Foundation.h
instead of having to type each type of import
like NSString.h, NSArray.h and so on.
We don't have to do this.
We can just use the umbrella and get all the definitions.
Now, this is how the umbrella header looks like.
We also mentioned module Map.
Let's see what the module Map is.
But the module Map is a text File.
By default, this is generated by Xcode
from the information describing your module
like the umbrella header.
If the define modules option is enabled,
the one we showed.
It basically describes the mapping
between modules and headers.
As an example, I want to look at our essential feeds,
generated module Map.
So to do this, I'll go back to finer
and inside the EssentialFeed framework Bundle,
there's a modules folder
and inside it, there's a module module Map.
This is the File I want to open.
Let's take a look.
First, it defines the framework inside,
which is EssentialFeed.
Then it mentions that the umbrella header
for this framework is EssentialFeed.h.
And after that, there's a couple of exports
and module definitions,
which basically say that all the headers
imported in umbrella header
will end up in a different sub module.
So we can have this granularity we'll see in a second.
Also, there's a separate module
which is called EssentialFeed.Swift,
which contains that File we'll still haven't introduced yet.
So let's ignore it for now.
Sharing the module Map allows you kind to
import specific parts of your module.
And for example, the EssentialFeed.Swift we saw,
or in case of the system frameworks,
we can import sub components of them.
For example, if we could write import Foundation like this,
we can say Foundation.NSString or Foundation.NSArray.
Autocomplete does not work, but you see this works.
Actually, let's reopen the project.
Sometimes Xcode just wants a reboot.
Yeah, this time it works, autocomplete.
Good.
So we talked about headers
and how the system works to find headers, module maps.
I want to introduce another concept,
which is forward declarations.
You can get your project to compile
by using only imports all over the place,
but keep in mind they're pretty inefficient.
If you import large header for referencing
one or two entities inside that File,
or if you're not careful and clean up imports periodically,
they just add up and you have a huge File to compile
even if some of the imports there are not even needed.
Not to mention, you can have cyclic references
in cases where you'd have a header A imports header B
and header B imports header A.
And this is a situation the compiler
just cannot resolve on its own.
So the Clang compiler offers a more effective solution
to referencing entities from other files or modules,
which are forward declarations.
These are basically promises to the compiler
that a cluster Protocol or another entity
will be declared in another File.
And in situations where you only need
to reference an entity and don't care about all the details,
like for instance, you need to pass a Logger instance,
but you don't care about the properties
or methods on that glass,
you can use a forward declaration instead of an import.
To compile each File,
the compiler doesn't need to resolve this forward declarations.
It's enough to know that they will be declared somewhere else.
Finding these files and filling in the right declaration
will be done by the linker
at the end of the compilation process.
Again, something we described in detail
in the Xcode build process lecture.
So you should check that if it doesn't make sense.
Now let's build an example
by creating a new Objective-C class.
This time I'm gonna call it log manager.
It's not gonna be a Singleton,
but again, let's delete the NSAssume instructions
as we haven't said what they are.
And for this class, I want to add a simple method
that allows code log, that allows passing a Message
and using the Logger, it should know how to log.
Now I immediately see that the compiler is not happy
because there's no Logger type.
Of course I can fix this by using import Logger.h
import Logger.h and everything will be fine.
But as we said, this import will actually be replaced
by the pre-compiler with all the contents of myLogger.h
and I might not need these details
because I just wanna pass a Logger instance.
So what I can do instead is use a forward declaration
at class Logger, compiler is still happy.
And I know some of you are thinking,
yeah, but you didn't add the body of the function.
Let's do that.
So I'll add the body and I'll call the method log.
We added on Logger previously.
If I try to build, I get this Error
which is saying Logger is a forward declaration.
But in the case of the implementation File.m
the compiler really needs to know how to resolve this symbol.
So in this case of the.m File, I need to import the header.
And now it works.
So we've shown how to use at class forward declaration.
There are other types of forward declarations
which I wanna quickly show.
So I'll go back to myLogger.h
since this is the place where I want to stack my entities.
And I'll add an empty Protocol called Logger Protocol.
And if you recall, we added an enum definition
inside the Logger.m and I wanna move this to the header.
So exposing it to other files and back to myLogger manager.
Before declaration for the Logger Protocol
would be add Protocol Logger Protocol.
And this would allow me to use a,
it's like this, it's referencing the Logger Protocol.
And I can also do a forward declaration for the nse enum.
Do a forward declaration for the nse enum and I can pass.
This is how you would use forward declarations.
But there are some cases
where a forward declaration does not work.
And some of them are using NSOptions or in other cases,
but I wanna show like the primary case
where we need the import.
And this is when we try to subclass.
So I'll create a new CocoaTouch class
and I'll call it File Logger.
And I want my File Logger to expand or to subclass Logger.
If I try to use my forward declaration here as before,
I will get an Error because the compiler is not happy
that we just forward declared the Logger class.
Since it's subclassing, it really needs to know
all the signatures, all the methods
that are available on this class.
So in this particular case,
we have to import the Logger.h
in the header File of the File Logger
and now the compiler's happy.
So we covered how Objective-C declarations
used from other Objective-C files are found.
And we have seen that there can be done
through header files or through forward declarations.
Now, let's take a look at how Swift does this.
So I'll take a look at the SceneDelegate class
inside the EssentialApp module.
Let's take a look at this new Store init invocation.
When compiling the SceneDelegate.Swift,
the Swift compiler will look up the type
of the new Store, initialize it, so it can check the call.
The same lookup happens, for instance,
when the compiler tries to resolve the static function
feedComposedWith and these following parameters
on the FeedUIComposer.
But before it can do that, it needs to parse these files.
So we'll Store.Swift File
and the FeedUIComposer.Swift File
and validate them to make sure that the declarations
of the two functions we used in the SceneDelegate Swift
are well formed.
The Swift compiler is smart enough to only check
the declarations of the involvement functions.
So it still needs to do some work to process
the interface parts of the File.
What this means is unlike Clang,
when compiling one Swift File, the Swift compiler parses
all the other Swift files in that target
to examine the parts that are relevant
to the interfaces used.
So to recap, the Swift compiler parses all the Swift files
in a target to find declarations
between Swift files from the same module.
I mentioned the two files are in the same module
because handling the case where we reference the Swift File
from another module is a bit different.
So let's see how that works.
If we go back to our SceneDelegate,
we, for instance, see that it uses the URLSession,
HTTPClient type, which is defined
in the EssentialFeed framework.
So in another module.
We mentioned modules and in Swift the module
is a distributable unit of declarations.
And to be able to use those declarations,
you have to import the module.
In this case, import EssentialFeed.
And in Xcode, any Swift target produces a separate module,
including your app target.
This is why in your test Bundle, unit test Bundle,
you have to import the app module
so you can access its types.
Like this.
So when importing the module,
the compiler deserializes a special Swift module File
to check the types when you use them.
I can show you how this looks.
So we notice that next to the EssentialApp Bundle,
we have the EssentialApp.swiftmodule folder.
Inside this folder, there are files with multiple extensions,
but we care about the Swift module files.
These are serialized binary representation
of the module's declarations.
This includes public, internal, and private declarations
since the internal and private ones are needed for Debugging.
Back to Xcode, if you remember the setUp,
you know that the EssentialApp target
has a link binary with libraries,
implicit dependency to the EssentialFeed framework.
Because of that, Xcode knows to build
the EssentialFeed target before the EssentialApp target.
Now, Xcode uses some optimizations
to allow building in parallel.
So the EssentialApp will only wait for generating
the interface of the EssentialFeed module,
but not wait for the entire build.
So this gives you some parallelization for free.
Back to SceneDelegate.
So to resolve this initializer,
the URL, session, HTTPClient, initializer with the session,
the Swift compiler uses the interface
from the Swift module we just showed
to resolve this declaration.
So to recap, when finding Swift declarations
from other Swift files from different modules,
the Swift compiler relies on Swift modules.
Swift modules.
Now let's start the cross-reference.
So first, finding Objective-C declarations used in Swift.
This is crucial because most of the system frameworks
are written in Objective-C,
including the ones we import in almost all our files,
like Foundation or UIKit.
The Swift compiler embeds a large part of Clang
inside of it and use it as a library
to import Objective-C frameworks directly.
So where do Objective-C declarations come from?
The importer will look in headers
depending on the type of the target.
And we have a few cases here.
When importing an Objective-C framework from Swift,
the importer finds declarations in the headers
exposing Clang's module Map for the framework.
Since we've explored the Foundation umbrella header before,
let's see how the module Map
for the Foundation framework looks like.
I'll use the showing finder
to go to disk at the path
where the Foundation framework is found.
And next to the headers folder, there's the module folder.
And we can explore the module Map
for the Foundation framework.
It's a bit different than the one we just saw
for the central Feed.
It still defines a framework module,
but this time it marks it at extern C
and as a system framework.
Again, there's an umbrella header,
which is the Foundation header,
the same exports and modules
that make the system define a sub-module
out of each header imported in umbrella header.
And there's an interesting case where they exclude a header.
So by having an umbrella header and a module Map,
in Swift we can have concrete imports
like Foundation.nsring or Foundation.nsray,
the one we showed in Objective-C.
So this was the importing Objective-C frameworks from Swift.
Now let's see a case where a framework
mixes Swift and Objective-C.
And this happens to be the case
for our EssentialFeed framework.
So within a framework that mixes Swift and Objective-C,
the importer finds declarations in the umbrella header.
As you remember, this is the header
that defines the public interface.
In this way, the Swift code
inside the EssentialFeed framework
can call public Objective-C code in the same framework.
Remember, we just created the EssentialFeed umbrella header
for the EssentialFeed framework.
Since it imports the Logger.h File,
the Logger class is accessible from Swift.
So as an exercise,
if we go to the LocalFeedImageDataLoader
and we want to maybe log before this do catch,
we can say let Logger equals Logger.
And we can invoke the log with Message Error.
If we build everything is okay.
Again, because the umbrella header EssentialFeed
imports the header File that defines the Logger class.
What's important here is this concept of an umbrella header
exists for framework targets.
It doesn't exist for app targets or unit test targets.
They have something equivalent,
which is called a bridging header.
So within app or unit test targets,
you can add imports to the targets bridging header
to allow declarations from them to be called from Swift.
This bridging header, which I just mentioned
is just a header File that contains all the declarations
or imports of entities, which we expose to Swift.
As I mentioned,
there are no bridging header for framework targets.
So it's either one or the other, you can't mix it up.
To see this in example, let's create one,
but we'll do it through Xcode automatic mechanism.
And I'll just add an Objective-C class
to my EssentialApp target this time.
Again, using the CocoaTouch class template.
And I'll call this String helper and create.
And you see that I got a prompt from Xcode.
Would you like to configure an Objective-C bridging header?
This is because this was my first Objective-C File
being added to the EssentialApp target.
And Xcode knows that to share this code to Swift,
I need to create a bridging header.
So let's create one.
If I look into this EssentialApp bridging header File,
Xcode automatically created, I see it's empty.
Xcode uses like a template for this name,
but we can use any name for the bridging header.
The important thing is there is a build setting
called Objective-C bridging header
or Swift OPC bridging header that contains this name.
So if I rename my File,
I just need to make sure I also update my build setting.
So back to our String helper
and we'll see how the bridging header works in a minute.
I want to add some methods to this class
and I will copy paste them.
So I added three methods.
The first method does nothing.
It's called do nothing,
takes no parameters and returns Void.
The second method returns Void,
returns Void, takes a String and a CG point.
And the third one will return a bool
and takes a String parameter
and uses the NSR double pointer convention
to return an Error.
For the imports, I use the specific header CGGeometry,
which is where CG point is defined.
I also want to add the bodies
so the implementation of the String helper.
So it imports the String helper.age.
We also import a specific header we need from UIKit
to drawString at point.
And this is just an example.
And the body of the validate String method
checks if the length is greater than zero,
we turn true, otherwise we draw an Error.
It is a pretty simple case.
Note that there's a convention in Objective-C
that a function like this that returns bool
and can also return an Error
is considered to have failed,
even if we return false, but provide no Error.
So that's also an Error case.
This is important when you use these methods from Swift.
So let's see if this compiles.
It should compile fine, okay.
Now remember, I didn't add String helper
to my bridging header.
So if I go to SceneDelegate and try to use it,
I'll get a failure.
So I need to go into the bridging header
and explicitly import my String helper.
And now this works.
So I can use String helper.validate String, any String.
And since it will draw,
so we will try question mark to get the compiler to be happy.
And now it works.
So to recap, finding Objective-C declarations
that are used from Swift,
realize on the fact that Swift C or the Swift compiler
embeds Clang as a library.
And this allows importing Objective-C frameworks directly.
We use module maps to partially import these modules
to resolve Objective-C declarations
inside the same framework target.
The compiler uses the umbrella header
while for add target, it uses the bridging header.
When the importer brings in declarations
from Objective-C to Swift,
it often changes them to make them more Swift.
Let's see some examples.
I'll go to the NSManage object context header from CoreData
and try to use the system, but I get a no selection.
So I will reopen my project.
And this time it works.
And I'll use the Generated Interface assistant.
And the method I wanna look at is executeRequest.
And to find its correspondent,
I will use NSPersistentStoreResult,
which is the only function that uses this.
So you can see on the left, the header File
of the NSManage object context from the CoreData.
And on the right, using the Generated Interface assistant,
we basically simulate how Swift would generate
a header File for this object.
A header File for this header
and make it available into Swift.
We notice a few things.
First of all, the method name was executeRequest.
Now the request part was removed
and it's only called execute.
It has no name for the first parameter,
but the request variable name to be used
inside the method definition.
Also, since it was following the convention
like the last parameter is an Error,
double pointer NSError,
it got converted to a throws method.
And you see no NSError parameter nowhere.
And it returns an NSPersistentStoreResult.
Another example, inside the nstring.h,
let's look at the component separated by String API.
And it's a component.
And it's equivalent.
So the Objective-C original API
was called component separated by String.
The Swift Generated Interface name
is components separated by and a separator parameter.
If you're familiar with Objective-C Generics,
we'll explain them in a second.
You see that we have an NSArray of type and a String here.
So an Array of strings.
So that's why the return type of this function
is an Array of String.
Another example
is inside the nstring drawing.h,
we do these two APIs.
So draw at point and draw in rect.
For them, the words point and rect
will be removed.
So let's find them.
Those are the corresponding extension
on an asset with a String.
And you see the first method.
So draw at point was converted to draw at
and draw in rect was converted to draw in.
So these words are omitted in Swift
when the method is imported at simply draw at or draw in.
So how does this work?
Now, you might be surprised to know
that the compiler contains a List
of common English verbs and prepositions.
Because it is just a hard-coded List,
it's limited to only a handful of words.
Furthermore, in order to match Swift's naming conventions,
the importer will also rename methods
to remove words based on the part of speech.
So to check how your Objective-C headers
will be imported into Swift,
you can use the Generated Interface assistant
we just showed.
Let's take a look at our String helper.
So we see it converted all three functions.
So do nothing to do nothing.
This is pretty straightforward.
drawString at point got converted to draw at
and validate String that returned the bool
and had an NSR double pointer
is now validate with the String parameter
and function that throws.
Another interesting thing is the import to core graphics,
CGGeometry.h was replaced by import
core-graphics.CGGeometry.
Now let's see how we can make these APIs
a bit more Swifty.
First of all, we can use NSSwiftName
to control the resulting Swift API name.
So if I want to, let's say,
rename my do nothing method to nothing,
I will add an NSSwiftName and the nothing name.
This is how I refresh the Generated Interface.
And I see that the new name of the function
is nothing as instruct.
But since this function really does nothing,
I want to exclude it from the Generated Interface entirely.
To do this, I can use another attribute
which is NSSwiftUnavailable,
which takes a String parameter
like the information on why this is unavailable.
And let's say it does nothing.
So again, I'll refresh the interface.
Sorry.
And this time, the function has disappeared entirely.
So I only get to draw and validate functions.
This is how NSSwiftUnavailable works.
Now let's take a more deep look
at the parameters of my functions.
So by default, all Objective-C parameters
are imported into Swift as implicitly-unwrapped optionals,
like these strings here.
But I think this is wrong
because an NSString pointer
can either point to a String value or to Null.
But if it's set to Null
and we try to unwrap this implicitly-unwrapped optional,
the app will Crash.
So to help the compilers,
Objective-C added annotations like non-Null or nullable
to explicitly mark which parameters can be Null
and which can't.
I'll mark this
String parameter of drawString as non-Null and build.
And what I can see is I got a few warnings.
This is because once we add one annotation,
one nullable annotation to a File,
the compiler considers we have opted in
to use nullable annotations in that File.
So we must provide this information
for all of the parameters of our methods.
So let's add the remaining annotations.
I marked the second one,
the String pass to validate String as nullable
because we know we can process empty,
so new values there.
And I mark with underscore nullable these pointers.
Build and let's look at the new interface.
Now, the String parameter for the draw function
got changed from a implicitly-unwrapped optional String
to a String.
This is exactly what we want.
For the validate function,
since we marked it as nullable,
the type is now String optional.
But especially in large files,
adding all these annotations can take up a lot of space.
So Apple added some convenience instructions.
These are the nsassume non-new begin and non-Null end
you saw in the File templates
created automatically by Xcode.
Between these, Xcode will consider
all the variables are non-Null.
So you just need to mark the ones which are nullable.
I'll build and regenerate the interface.
And the interface should be the same.
Yes.
Another way we can help the compiler generate
correct interfaces for Swift is to use
three types of instructions.
NSEnum, NSOptions, and NSErrorEnum.
I'll just copy-paste an example in our header File.
So first we type deft MyEnum type,
which uses NSUnsignedIntegers as backing.
With three cases, MyOptions, NSOption type,
also backed by unsigned integers with zero, one or two options.
And an NSErrorEnum called MyError
with two specific Errors.
Let's see how the interfaces look for this.
First, we see a SwiftEnum using unsigned Int
with all the cases, case zero, one and two.
Then a struct called MyOptions conforming to option set
with initializer taking the raw value
and only the option one and option two static vars
because option zero is the default one.
And the MyError struct is even more complex.
It has an initializer that takes an NSError.
It has an embedded enum code with the specific Error codes
and some static vars for the specific Errors.
So we should prefer these to regular C-style enums.
Another thing which we can do to help the Swift compiler
is following this convention of functions
that return a bool and return a Null.
That return a bool and return like user in out
double pointer NSError as the last parameter
and it's called Error because the Swift generated header
can detect that that's actually a throwing method.
So it can transform that to a Swift API that throws.
And finally, the Objective-C Generics we mentioned.
So I'll paste in my String helper some functions.
The first function is called MyArray
and just returns a simple NSArray.
The second one uses the Generics so that it returns
uses the Generics so it's an explicit NSArray
using NSString pointer as the backing type.
Then a simple NSDictionary and again an NSDictionary
where the key is an NSString and the value is an NSNumber.
And we'll see how the interface for these looks like.
Oops.
So the MyArray function returns an Array of any
as the MyDictionary returns AnyHashable to any.
This is because NSArray and NSDictionary
don't provide any information about the type
so it basically can be anything.
But if we use these Generics,
we really help the compiler resolve the types.
So MyArray of strings, here it returns an Array of String
and the same for the dictionary,
an explicit hash from String to NSNumber.
These Generics are nowhere near as powerful
as the Swift ones, but they do help,
especially the Swift compiler importing the declarations.
But even the Clang compiler is pretty smart about it.
So to recap, we've seen the implicit transformations
applied by the compiler to Objective-C headers
when importing them to Swift.
Also, we've seen ways to make our Swift interface
friendlier or more Swift-y by giving explicit Swift API names,
hiding APIs from Swift when they're not useful,
providing nullable or non-Null annotations
to avoid implicit and unwrapped optionals
using NSEnum, NSOptions and NSErrorEnum
and using the Objective-C generics
to let the Swift compiler know exactly which types to use.
So that's how Swift imports Objective-C,
but what about the other direction?
How does Objective-C import Swift?
Well, the answer is pretty simple.
Swift generates a header for each target
that you can pound import.
This header follows the convention
of the targetName dash Swift point H.
I'll go to the SceneDelegate class,
Swift class in the EssentialApp target
and using the Generated Interface.
So the Generated Interface assistant
now shows my EssentialApp dash Swift header.
And there's a lot of macros and instructions here,
but if we scroll to the end,
we'll get to the part that's important.
Let's see how this works.
The compiler will generate these Objective-C declarations
for the Swift classes that extend any subject
and for the methods marked with add of C.
For apps and unit test targets,
the generated header will include
both public and internal declarations.
This allows you to use internal Swift
from the Objective-C parts of your app.
Using the Generated Interface assistant,
like we are already doing,
we can see the generated Swift interface
for the EssentialApp target.
And we notice two entities,
the AppDelegate and the SceneDelegate.
This is because these are the only NSObject subclasses
because UI-responder is actually a subclass of NSObject.
And their definition.
But if we go to, let's say, the URLSessionHTTPClient,
Swift File that's a part of our EssentialFeed framework
and try to look at the EssentialFeed.Swift,
we'll see that it has no definitions
besides the macros automatically included by the compiler.
This is because there are no entities in our EssentialFeed
that are exposed to Objective-C.
But as an experiment to see how this works,
we can make the URLSessionHTTPClient
a subclass of NSObject.
And we can also mark this in public initializer
with the add Objective-C mark.
If we build, the Swift Generated Interface is regenerated.
So now we can see that it contains the interface
for the URLSessionHTTPClient.
And the Swift name is interesting
because it's a mangled variation
containing the name of the framework,
which is EssentialFeed in the name of the class.
This prevents conflicts at runtime
when two modules define a class with the same name.
Since Objective-C has no namespaces like Swift,
all the entities belong to a global namespace,
so collisions are likely to happen.
The mangling the Swift Generated Interface does prevents that.
You can tell the Swift compiler
to use a different Objective-C name,
but passing that name with obc.
And now, even the Swift name is also URLSessionHTTPClient.
But if you do this, you're responsible
for making sure the names don't conflict.
So to use this Swift interface in this class,
we need to create a new class.
And if we want to use this Swift interface
in this Swift interface into an Objective-C header,
we can go to one of our Objective-C files.
Over here, I can use the import essential,
yes, EssentialFeed, yeah, it works.
So here, I can use my URLHTTPSession type.
Client equals.
It only exposes this initializer,
so that's the way to use it.
So to recap, finding Swift declarations
that are used from Objective-C
is done through the Swift generated header.
An important note here is never import
your Swift generated header inside the umbrella header,
because this creates a circular dependency.
So if you want to use Swift generated header,
you need to import your Swift generated header
in a circular dependency.
It's something that Apple really recommends we don't do.
And finally, let's talk a bit about
how to harness the power of Swift,
even when mixing it with Objective-C.
So if you've mixed Swift and Objective-C
into the same project,
you probably noticed that making your Swift code
accessible from Objective-C
requires limiting the Swift features
that you can use in that Swift code.
Using the following Swift features
will make your code not accessible
or limitedly accessible in Objective-C.
The use of generics, tuples,
enums with associated values, structs,
top level functions or global variables,
type aliases, nested types and more.
So in practice, this means that you can't really use
all the power that Swift offers you,
since you most probably have to share that Swift code
with your Objective-C layer.
And that leads to suboptimal Swift code.
If your objective is to gradually migrate
from Objective-C code base to a Swift one,
writing new code in Swift with these limitations
will lead to Swift code that is suboptimal.
And most of your types will be classes
which inherit from any subject
and all the enums are in-based.
So you probably want to rewrite that code
in the Future as well.
Let's introduce a Strategy
by which you can still write your new code in Swift,
taking advantage of all the new features
Swift has to offer,
while preserving a layer of compatibility
with Objective-C code.
The idea is to reduce the points of intersection to a mean.
Try having subsystems like modules,
features or components written using the same language
instead of going back and forth
between Swift and Objective-C.
If such a system, subsystem is written in Swift
and needs to be accessed from Objective-C,
only the subsystem interface
needs to be accessible from Objective-C.
So for that, we can write a wrapper in Swift
that follows the Objective-C limitations we talked about,
while all the other files in the subsystem
can continue to use the Swift features.
Also, writing these wrappers is only temporary.
And once you've rewritten all the clients
that use that subsystem in Swift,
you can remove them.
And the remaining will be Swifty types and code.
Now let's see some example.
Let's add a new Swift File and we'll call it a timer.
So our timer class is pretty simple.
It has an enum that can be now
or later with an associated Date
and an execute function that takes one of these time enums
and execute a callback now if the enum case is now
or later at the Date using this patch async after.
Pretty simple.
This is not code I recommend you use in production,
but it works as an exercise.
The only real limitation we have on this class
is the fact that the subclass is NSObject,
but that's easy to remove in the Future.
Other than that, we can use these enum
with associated values inside
and other entities like mentioned features.
And then we have the extension for the Objective-C axis
where we expose a function marked with Objective-C
for each of the cases of the enum.
So one's execute now and the other's execute later.
And the execute later also takes a Date.
And behind doors, they both just call our Swift function.
Swift function, so that's the Objective-C wrapper.
Another example is you might want to define your value types
or Models as structs.
Such an example in our project
is the FeedImage struct.
So how can we expose a struct to Objective-C?
Well, we can't, but we can write a wrapper around it.
So I'll just quickly remind everyone
that the FeedImage has an ID, a description,
a location and a URL.
And we'll wrap this FeedImage
into a FeedImage underscore Objective-C,
which is a class because it needs to inherit from NSObject.
It uses the FeedImage inside.
And we've written some computed vars
that just return the value of the FeedImage.
There's a special case about the description variable
because NSObject already contains
a property called description.
So we had to override that.
And it has a slight different signature
where it returns a String instead of a String option.
So by wrapping the FeedImage into a FeedImage
of C class, we allow the Objective-C
to interact with the Objective-C code
and this NSObject subclass,
while all the Swift code we have
can still use our FeedImage struct.
If you have all the Swift types working with FeedImage
that needs to be accessed from Objective-C,
let's say the FeedCache,
you can apply the same technique as before.
So writing an extension and defining the API
that works with the wrapped FeedImage of C subclass
of NSObject.
So this extension looks something like this.
So we use the OPC prefix
and instead of taking an Array of FeedImage,
it takes an Array of FeedImage underscore OPC.
It also throws and we call the save Image,
the save method we already have
and we Map to get the FeedImages inside.
Another example would be,
we used to have a FeedLoader Protocol
inside our project.
It got removed when creating some,
like the final refactoring is doing generics.
But this was the signature.
So it had a Result type
that was either an Array of FeedImage or Error
and an API called load,
which is a async API and basically returns a Result.
Now, if we have a solid Objective-C implementation for it,
for convenience, I will still List it here as Swift,
but let's say this is Objective-C.
Then,
we can again write a Swift wrapper this time around it.
So it's the other way around.
If we have a solid Objective-C,
which we want to use to Swift,
we wrap it in a Swift object, Swift type.
Now, our Objective-C has some limitations.
It cannot use the Result type.
So it has to use two parameters,
an optional FeedImage Array and an optional Error.
While we know that we want to use the Result type,
which is either an Array or an Error.
So we wrap the RemoteFeedLoader of C
inside the RemoteFeedLoader class.
And inside the load function
that this time follows the FeedLoader Protocol,
we just Map over the load,
which can return two parameters.
And if we get an Error,
we call the Completion with the failure.
If we get a Feed, we call the Completion with success.
And because there's a state here,
which shouldn't be representable,
but is because of the combination of optionals,
we can have no Error and no Feed.
And in that case, we complete with the failure
and this unexpected Error struct.
So that's how I would suggest
you approach this problem of gradually migrating.
Thank you.
And if there are any questions,
Sarthak says, allow FeedImage or FeedImage of C.
Yes, it should be a FeedImage of C here, right?
Okay, hello, hi, so in FeedImage underscore Objective-C
in the class, you exposed a FeedImage.
So will it be okay?
There's a reason for it.
So like I said, this Objective-C wrappers are temporary.
We need this because in the FeedCache implementation,
we need to Map and to actually get the FeedImage.
So this is where we use this property.
That's why it's public.
You could hide this by just creating a new FeedImage.
So this will become private.
And then this cannot be accessed,
but we can create a new FeedImage.
And we have to pass $0.ID, $0.description.
So making it public will be an optimization
when bridging back.
So you don't need to instantiate a new object.
But if you don't want to expose it, that's fine as well.
We just create a new one.
So if there's no other questions, we can wrap it up.
Okay, thanks.
Thank you.
I'll see you next time.