Alright after going through the Start
here section
you are ready to start the program so
this first
module is an introduction to planning
software design and architecture
there is code there's diagrams and there
are concepts you may have
never heard before so be open-minded
to new ideas exactly and if you feel
overwhelmed
be sure you'll learn every concept you see
in this section
in detail with concrete examples as you
progress in the program
so don't wait to move on to the next
lectures even if you don't get the
concepts 100%
at this point so let me say that again
don't get stuck
in the first module this is just an
introduction
you will learn every concept in detail
with concrete examples as you progress
in the program
so don't feel overwhelmed right now you
will learn
every concept in detail exactly
and in this lecture you learn how
singletons and global state
can damage your app architecture and
make code harder to test
especially in the networking layer
exactly
that's a common issue in iOS codebases
over-using
Singletons and global state
so you will learn that there are better
ways and again you will learn those
better solutions
in detail as you progress in the
lectures
remember this is just an introduction so
don't
get stuck here keep moving complete the
lectures
and ask questions below let's start
So two big topics here first is this
networking layer
testability and then we have the
Singleton so should we talk about
Singletons first
okay I have the definition of the
Singleton pattern from
the Design Patterns book by Gamma
Johnson
Vlissides and Helm, the GOF book the Gang
of Four
so basically the authors say that
the design pattern the Singleton is a
way to make sure that the class has only
one instance and it provides a single
point of access to it
the pattern specifies that the class
should be responsible itself for keeping
track of its sole
instance and it can further ensure that
no other instance can be created by
intercepting requests for creating new
objects
and provide a way to access the sole
instance
okay that's a lot yeah let's put some
code here
and go one by one let's start with a
class here
ApiClient and I can just create my
client
for example that's fine that's a normal
class you define your type you define
the methods
and properties in here the initializer
and that's it
now how can we make this a Singleton so
the key points here is that
this class needs to have a single point
of access
right so the whole point of a Singleton
is to have only
one instance of this class right to
guarantee that right I shouldn't be able
to just create
an ApiClient like this so first of all
we can prevent people from creating
ApiClients by just
making the initializer private that's
correct now
the type should give you access to one
right
and if you follow it by the book we
would end up with a private
static instance and that's an ApiClient
and then we would have a static function
getInstance yeah that returns
an ApiClient
that's it and you return here the
instance
okay yeah so now from the outside world
we can say
getInstance but in Swift
what we can do is we can just make this
a static let
instance because we cannot mutate it the
type system already
enforces this for us so it's much
simpler here we can just say
instance and boom we have access to the
shared instance and we guarantee that
we can only have one instance per
application run that's it so this is a
Singleton
this is a Singleton so what if I make
this class final then
right the book though says you shouldn't
be doing this
because a Singleton may be extended in
the future
the pattern is saying that we should
allow extension for example adding more
methods to the ApiClient by having a
subclass
right right so we could have a class
MyApiClient that inherits from
ApiClient and then we can add more
methods
to it yes or we can even override some
behavior
yeah you can override yeah but you can
make a case that in Swift we can use
extensions
without using subclass so we cannot
override behavior but we can still add
more behavior
so it's a trade-off here if you want to
allow people to change the behavior of your
class
you allow subclassing otherwise
you just use extensions yes this looks
good
that's how you would implement a
Singleton you have only one instance
but URLSession.shared
it says that this method provides a
shared singleton
session object right the weird thing is
that I can still create
a URLSession myself yeah with different
configurations as well this is just a
convenience
but of course this breaks the whole
contract that the
Gang of Four refer to in their book so
this is the Singleton with capital "s"
the
by the book implementation and you have
the lowercase singleton
which is like a convenience right okay
in this case you have the shared
type there is only a getter you cannot
set the shared to point to another
instance
which means you still have like this
unique instance per application run
but you can still create your own if you
want to yeah exactly
so this is the difference from the
singleton with capital "S" and the
lowercase "s" and then people start asking
well how can I test code that uses
a singleton for example well it
depends
because there's nothing wrong with
having a singleton and still have
testable code
so let's illustrate this with
for example
a ViewController like a
LoginViewController and you have a method
didTapLoginButton
and here you want to use the ApiClient
okay to log in to a service
let's say yes the Singleton ApiClient
.instance .login
right and you pass a login request
and you get a user back for example
right and then you do something after
you log in
like show next screen now
this would be hard to test first of all
we would need to have a
function login it gets a closure for
example
LoggedInUser
and let's define here
our LoggedInUser
now if you want to test that LoginViewController
is working properly but you
don't want to make an API request
right how can you override this call
here how can you
replace the ApiClient with a mocked one
to be honest personally I don't know any
way to do that in Swift probably in
Objective-C you could swizzle the
getter and replace it with a mock but in
this case
since you cannot subclass ApiClient and
this is a let
you cannot do it at least in Swift yep
it sounds accurate but there are other
choices we can make here
so I want to be able to at least
subclass it
because now I can have an api
in here okay I see what you're doing so
you're gonna have a property injection
basically
yes for example ApiClient.instance
and now I don't access this
directly
which means in my tests I can inject
this with a
MockApiClient
for example
that overrides this login and does something
else
right and you can intercept now the
request to this login
function and you can test whatever it is
that you need to test in your
unit tests yes okay and then there's
another thing that I see people doing
as well nothing wrong with it but again
it breaks the pattern
that is to make this thing settable
so now what I can do in my test here in
this case is to
inject the instance to be a
MockApiClient
and then I don't even need this anymore
I can just go back to what it was right
so now you introduce global state
for the test target yes so probably
in the setup I need to
set up the mock client and in the tear
down I need to remember to replace it
back
yeah so this is not a singleton anymore
this is something else because it's not
a single term with capital "s"
it's not a single term with lowercase "s"
this is just
global state mutable global state
mutable global state yes the dark arts
that's what it is
but people still call it singleton
because of the semantics it looks like a
singleton it has a static
instance right no I think that's very
important what you mentioned there the
semantics
I feel that if developers see the
word instance somewhere or sharedInstance
or
.shared something like that they
tend to think that this is the singleton
pattern but then there's no
differentiation
between the singleton and mutable global
state
yeah in this case what's the point of
making this private
right and I think that's even better
because now this can go back to a let
so it's an immutable shared instance and
if you want to create new instances of
this ApiClient
well you have the initializer now exactly so
at least this global state now is
contained so this is back to
lowercase "s" singleton an instance that
is only created once
it cannot be replaced but you can still
create your own and pass it along
yeah exactly so that's the difference
from capital case Singleton lowercase
singleton
and just mutable global shared state
yeah so okay let's fix the problems here
what this is now is just shared but
in this case if you want to test it you
will need to have a property
and now we can use property injection to
replace it during tests so you don't
make API requests right
and for example let's say that this is a
Instagram-like application and when you
log in you go to the feed screen
so let's expand this problem a little
bit let's say we have a
FeedViewController now
and on viewDidLoad we're going to call
loadFeed right
and when you load the feed you expect to
get like loaded items
and then you update UI for example
okay so what we would need here is also
to have an API
and add a new method to the ApiClient
right load feed before your completion
and let's say it's an array of
FeedItems
so we need to define our FeedItem
here cool did you see the problem
I implemented a new feature the FeedViewController
and I had to add a new method
to this shared type right and then the
question is why is this a problem what's
wrong with that
well let's have a look at the diagram so
imagine you have the ApiClient and then
you have the Login
and then you have a login function and
then you have the Feed and you have a
loadFeed function
and if you've implemented the followers
feature you have a loadFollowers
function
but the Login doesn't care about feed
or followers
and the followers doesn't care about
login or feed and the feed doesn't care
about
login or followers but since this is
shared we have these
different modules sharing this type in
the middle
this concrete type ApiClient and every
time
I need to add a new method here I need
to recompile redeploy all the other
modules because they depend on the
concrete type
so what's happening here is that we have
source code dependency
in this ApiClient layer so if I want to
reuse the Login
in a different context in a different
application how can I move the Login
module to a separate application without
bringing the ApiClient with me
you can't is the answer well you can
if you now move the ApiClient to a
shared module and then you move the
Login and you reference it
right but then you make a change and
then the other modules break as well
yeah if we add another module for
example upload videos
you need to add a new method here uploadVideo
and you break all the other
modules you need to
bump a version in this framework and now
everyone else
needs to update yeah the references and
then you start having
semantic versioning issues right but we
can solve that yeah
we can solve it if you care about
modular design
you should probably consider breaking
these things into
something much more responsible exactly
what this class needs is just to call a
function
right but now this class actually needs
to
know where to find this instance know
it's concrete type
and an invoker function right there are
three layers here where you should need
one and it creates this implicit
dependency of this ApiClient
as well yes this global shared state
here is very convenient
yeah it's easy to create into use but
introduce some problems
so what we're doing here is making a
case that if you need to achieve some
kind of reusability
you might need to think about these
problems you need to understand the
trade-offs so when this trade-off bites
you
you know what to do about it absolutely
absolutely
so a solution to this problem of every
time you add a new method you might
break
other modules it's actually fairly
simple what we could do here
in Swift is to use extensions
for example we can have a generic method
executeRequest
that can execute any type of
request and then
every module has its own ApiClient
extension with
whatever method they need so let's say
we are breaking this now in modules so
this is the
Api Module
then we have the Login Module for
example
and we have the Feed Module
and what if we had like a generic
function here
execute and then it has a completion
let's say it just completes with data
for now we're not handling errors
right so this API is enough to execute
any
get or post request for example maybe
not enough for uploads
and downloads but we don't have this
requirement yet and then what we can do
is move
the login function to the Login module
by introducing an extension
in a separate module to the ApiClient
with the login implementation we can
even move
the LoggedInUser struct to that
module as well yeah that makes sense
and we can do the same thing for the
Feed module we have an extension
in the ApiClient that is the loadFeed
and the loadFeed
and the login methods we'll call the
execute
the generic method and then we can move
the
FeedItem to the Feed module
as well and now we have this
implementation
where we specialize the client for the
module
and we have a generic client in the
middle which can make this
ApiClient thing redundant we could have
just used
plain URLSessions by creating
extensions on URLSession
or AlamoFire or whatever you use and
look how we broke the
dependencies without breaking the
implementation we just restructured
changed a little bit the architecture
the dependency graph
but look how the ApiClient is still
shared between
all those modules so if at some point
you need to add a new module where you
want to upload
data to the API you might have to add
a new method here and you break the
clients as well you're not completely
safe
from change but it's much more flexible
now
now this is stage one yeah what if you
need a little bit more flexibility
to make this more reusable and not
breaking the clients
now we talk about inverting the
dependency
what if instead of the modules depending
on a concrete
ApiClient we actually make
the concrete ApiClient depend on the
modules
yeah that's the second stage and this is
going to give us
all the freedom that we want basically
exactly
and most applications I've seen 99%
of the applications I've seen stop
here yeah and eventually
when this gets too messy the solution is
to
rewrite the application right because
that's what's going to happen if you
don't
proactively understand where your
architecture is moving to
and change it as needed you don't need
to start with a super abstract
implementation you can move little by
little
yeah but you need to move you need to be
proactive and to make those decisions
as you go and at some point you might
need to invert dependency
because the ApiClient is just a detail
what is important to the business
is not the ApiClient implementation
yeah and API requests
if you go to your boss and say oh we're
having a problem with the request they
don't care
right right they care about the features
they don't care about
the technicalities and the details
that's why
I prefer to have contained logic in
modules
and details depend on the features in
this case the details the ApiClient
and to do so we introduce
protocol or closures or any type of
interface
for the modules for example the Login
it needs a function
or it needs a type that implements a
function talking to an API
the Feed will need a function to load
the feed
the Followers will need a function to
load the followers and that's all they
need
it doesn't need to know where it comes
from so when you have a concrete type
dependency
as we have here when
the Login module directly references
the ApiClient
we depend on the ApiClient we need to
know how to locate the instance
in the shared pointer and then we need
to invoke the function we want
when all we want is a function so why
don't we
just depend on a function or on a
protocol that implements the function
right so now there is this
specialization that you mentioned before
so what do I need as a Login module as a
Feed module as a Followers module what
do I need and I don't care about
anything else
you can go level four yeah and level
four is
you have your generic ApiClient in the
center you have your
modules with only what they need and
then you implement
the adapters this is completely modular
because you can use this ApiClient in
other applications you can use the
Login in other applications
in other contexts you can use the
Followers module in other contexts as
well
you can just compose all those things
together and when you're testing you
compose it with mocks
or you compose it with stubs you compose
it with whatever you need absolutely
you open up possibilities level four
yeah as I mentioned before freedom by
the way these levels
we just mentioned them as a way
to keep count for
the slides right it's not a thing no
it's not a thing it's a level of
abstraction
based on the slides that we have there
and
the bigger the codebase and the more
complex it is
the more complex the requirements are I
think freedom is a tremendous asset
to have on the other hand it doesn't
come easily
you need to be very disciplined to reach
that stage and as we mentioned before
if you're making a small application and
you should definitely not start with a
level four
I agree this is not easy but I think
this is simple it is simple
you can compose those things simply you
can change things
simply you can test things simply and to
be fair
people look at this diagram and they
compare with the first one we showed
and they're like this is over-engineered
look how many things
but the diagram doesn't tell the truth
exactly it's not over-engineered
the architecture is in the code so
let's show the code that implements
exactly that
all we need is a login function and the
login function is this
so all we need here is a login function
that gets a callback let's make this
optional
for now it needs to be injected
of course this is a closure where you
invoke with a closure callback
right now you can move the ApiClient
to a Main module
great now the feed
all you need is a function or a protocol
with that function
so we have a loadFeed function where
you pass a closure
and now you move the loadFeed to the
Main module
and now the Main module just needs to
compose the functions by passing
it to the modules and not just these
functions
the Main module can compose any
functions right so this is very
important as well here because we just
abstracted the
Api the remote part for these
actions you know login and loadFeed
however
these are just signatures of these
functions right meaning that you can
have a remote
or a cached version for example yeah
you're free to do whatever you want very
simply and you have the same amount of
code
yeah absolutely absolutely so maybe you
look at this diagram and you feel
intimidated
but it's just because you cannot
translate diagrams
concepts modularity into code
sometimes it's not as difficult as we
think it is
yeah certainly not it just takes some
time to fiddle around with these things
and get it working definitely in my
opinion
test-driving these things and working
with
protocols or closures for dependency
injection
I think that's a great way to become
better improve
so now how would you test this how easy
would it be to just inject a function
and expect
something to happen right that's it yeah
how easy would it be yeah and it doesn't
need to be a ViewController
of course you could be using a ViewModel
in here right it can be anything right a
ViewModel
and then you have like a load function
yeah
it can be a service a service
exactly it can be other things it
doesn't need to be a ViewController
let's say it's a Feed module somewhere
you need to load this data
and it needs to talk to an API but it's
not your concern where this API
is how to locate it in memory what kind
of implementation what kind of concrete
type
I need to talk to and then from all the
methods it implements which one should I
call
you don't need to be concerned about
that I think the word concern is
extremely important here
that you mentioned because that's what
we're doing here we're doing separation
of concerns basically
and each component like this service or
this ViewController before
they were just concerned about
themselves they were not trying to fit
everything in nor have access to
everything that's very very important
all this code here can be tested without
actually talking
to a real API now the way you're going
to implement this ApiClient
if you have this separation here I don't
care it can be a Singleton
it can be global state it can be a capital
"s" Singleton a lowercase singleton
it can be URLSession it can be AFNetwork
I don't care
as long as my modules are abstracted
from that and I'm able
to easily replace it I'm able to easily
compose those types together
I don't care about the ApiClient I have
my preferences how I would implement
this
but then it's a personal preference all
I advise people to do is to
go to step one two three four or maybe
five, six
when needed just understand how you can
go from one step to the other
understand the limitations of singletons
with capital "s"
with lowercase "s" and make the choices
for your current problem
you can make Singletons testable and
you can make lowercase singletons
testable as well while property
injection if you allow
subclasses for example and then you can
just transform your singleton into a
global mutable state and replace it in
tests
that's another approach I don't
recommend it but sometimes it pays off
so
maybe you start there but know that
there might be a problem and when the
problem occurs
you know where to go to the next step
and then to the next step and then to
the next step
your code should be soft that's the
essence of software
you should be able to make those
decisions as you go so don't limit your
decisions
with frameworks or design patterns
yeah practice is the number one thing if
you would like something like that to
work
that's our advice I recommend you to try
it out yourself
try to look at your code right now and
draw some diagrams
try to find some bottlenecks in there
yeah you need to spend some time
testing out these things trying new
ideas recognizing
what you "did wrong" in previous
projects
and then at some point it will click
cool don't forget to check the links in
the description
and we'll see you next time, bye y'all