Hello Mike, hey Caio
so many viewers have expressed some
difficulty
when it comes to reading diagrams right
so why don't we explain through a simple
demonstration
all these arrows that we pull from one
component to another
and interfaces, protocols all these
things
yeah and we can write code and show the
diagram evolution
as we go yeah I like that but before we
start
why do we write diagrams right when we
draw them
why well it's a communication tool
for ourselves
and for other developers in the team and
when I say ourselves I mean our future
selves as well you know
understand what was the thinking
process at the time and
document it in a way the other thing
that I like about diagrams is
that you can validate your design
decisions
because you can see what module
talks to what module for example so it's
easier to see
the dependency graph right
of your objects of your classes or even
your functions
if you're writing some functional codebase
absolutely
absolutely and also it helps find memory
leaks
potential memory leaks right not actual
memory leaks because we would probably
need
Instruments or something to find that
well we can visually see some retain cycles
yes
exactly to be fair it's very easy for
the code to evolve
and the diagrams get out of sync so
there's a good argument not to keep them
as documentation I don't keep them as
documentation most of the times
I mostly use diagrams when for example
i'm starting to write a feature
in a team and we can pair in the
beginning and we draw some diagrams just
to
put our thoughts on paper it might take
us like
five, ten minutes to come up with an
initial plan
so it's just a framework to think it's
not always documentation
as you said it's a communication tool
yeah I think you make a very good point
there because
it's a bad investment actually after
some sort of
complexity being introduced in the
system then
it's just too costly to keep track of
all changes
and if you don't have a tool that will
produce these diagrams
for you that it will translate the
source code into diagrams I mean
then I agree with you 100% and I've never
seen a good tool
that can do that for me so right exactly
maybe there is
maybe unfair here but maybe one of our
viewers will make it
yes please
all right so let's start writing some
code great
why don't we start with the example last
time the
FeedViewController so we had a class
it was a FeedViewController
right that's how we started yes so how
does
this exact code we have right here
translate to a diagram right
so this is just a class a single
component
and it has no references no dependencies
no behavior nothing so we can represent
it with just
this box and its name right
but in our example in the previous
episode this class inherit
from UIViewController right
so just by doing that by importing
UIKit
and inheriting from UIViewController
that's a modular dependency
so we need to introduce that in the
diagram so now it looks like this
we inherit from ViewController and
since it's another module
let's use a different color to represent
it I like that so the
FeedViewController
inherits from UIViewController which means
we now depend
not just on UIViewController but UIKit
exactly because that's
the module where UIViewController is
defined
thus we had to import UIKit here and
that's a source
code dependency to UIKit from our
project
and the strongest of the couplings
inheritance
that is true but we had some more
dependencies here
in the previous episode we had the
loadFeed
closure right so let me
quickly paste this here there you go
very nice so we have a closure
where we could load the feed and in this
case let's say it's an array of strings
so we can render in a table view
yeah or a collection view it's simple
enough and on viewDidLoad
we invoke the loadFeed closure and
expect to get some items
right that's pretty common and we update
the UI yes
but now we have a new dependency it's a
closure right but even though it's a
function
it's still a dependency absolutely we have
a dependency on the signature of this
type and the signature
is this yes exactly it's a closure so we
can even name this
just to make this clear let's call it a
Feed
Loader
now we can replace it here and that's
what it is it's still a dependency
I can pass any closure that have the
same signature which means even though
we are passing a
closure we change our diagram yes so we
have
an arrow from the FeedViewController
towards the FeedLoader it's a closure
but
it's an interface it is it's a signature
exactly
and because it's an interface we prefix
and suffix with these greater
less than symbols there and this is a
reference this is a dependency
as a reference from the
FeedViewController to the FeedLoader that's why
we
choose the arrow with the closed head
basically
yeah it's a strong reference actually
yes and we know the closure is in Swift
they are reference types just like
classes this could very well be
a protocol and we have the typealias
there FeedLoader
and FeedLoader seems like a fine name
for a protocol
and basically it's exactly the same
thing it's a signature
right okay so why don't we make this
into a protocol then
let's do it so we wouldn't require much
work we can just
change this to be a protocol now with
one function
loadFeed for example
right and we need the completion there
as a named parameter
and we can omit the return type of void
because implicitly it returns void yes but
now we don't have an escaping
protocol yes and we can even change the
name of the loadFeed var let's call it
loader yeah I like loader and now it's
loader
.loadFeed since this is a protocol now
and we need to
invoke a function on the protocol where
before we would just invoke a closure
and the diagrams do the same
yes I wouldn't change anything in the
diagram I agree with you
they are very similar in concept they
are because
the FeedViewController only knows
basically about this
loadFeed function in the first example
it knew it through the closure here it
knows it through this protocol
but there is nothing else it can do with
this FeedLoader type
a protocol with one method can always be
replaced with a closure
I think that's fair to say I think
that's pretty much what it is
and some people prefer closure some
people prefer protocols pretty much a
personal choice I would say
although we now depend on this named
type FeedLoader where before
it could be any anonymous closure that
match the type signature right
and naming is hard it's one of those
big problems but sometimes you want to
name things to enforce some kind of
contract
so protocol defines better a contract my
advice
would be use whatever you're comfortable
with
if you're comfortable protocols go with
protocols but don't be afraid of getting
out of the comfort zone and trying out
some new ideas
absolutely very important okay so we
have a
FeedViewController we have a
FeedLoader well we can't do much
with this we need someone to implement
that exactly
let's say we have a RemoteFeedLoader
that implements the FeedLoader
interface and when you call loadFeed
it's going to talk to an API layer
URLSession, AFNetwork and call
the completion
when it's done right now how does the
diagram looks like
so now we have this dashed line with the
open head
from the RemoteFeedLoader towards the
FeedLoader
which means that the RemoteFeedLoader
conforms
to the FeedLoader protocol and I
decided to use some colors here to show
how we can bundle those types into
modules
right for example the FeedLoader can
live in the FeedViewController module
but the RemoteFeedLoader the
implementation can live in another
module that's why it has a different
color
let's say it's the blue module it could
be an API module
for example or a service module but they
could also be
all in the same module but they
shouldn't be immobile
right that's why we create those
separation of concerns
so if it's time to share these at some
point or have a different implementation
that we can replace
we can do it we have options or
facilitate testing
that's very important oh definitely
so we can have a different
implementation of the FeedLoader
right a LocalFeedLoader yes for
example this LocalFeedLoader
that just fetches some data from a cache
system or even a predefined JSON file
bundled in the app when you ship it so
if you don't have internet connection
you can still see something on the
screen
exactly you can have a persistence store
you can have a cache
mechanism, a JSON file it doesn't
matter
that's the beauty of the abstraction of
the FeedLoader there you can have a
bunch of implementations
conforming to a FeedLoader protocol and
be passed around
as a FeedLoader and now we have a new
type in our diagram okay
there it is the LocalFeedLoader that
also implements the
FeedLoader interface it conforms to the
FeedLoader interface
and it can be in a separate module
that's why it has a different color
but you can have everything bundled in
the same module but we have options
absolutely now imagine that your boss
comes to you and say
I want you to always try to get the
latest version from the remote but if
you have no
internet connection I want you to get
data from the cache
right so I think that's a that's a very
reasonable requirement
and it's often the case on iOS it's a
good
user experience and there's a bunch of
ways we can do that
yeah right for example some people might
have some logic
in the RemoteFeedLoader and say you
know what I should have only one type
that does
everything right and then you break the
single responsibility principle most
probably
yes and maybe that's that's fine for you
right but
we often see cases where there are
different approaches
to the problem yes it will be easier not
simpler right
yes and I like the easy versus simple
comparison
because for example an easy and often
used
approach is to change now our
ViewController
to depend on the concrete types again so
for example
instead of talking to an interface we
now depend on concrete types
and then we need to introduce some sort
of logic
in the ViewController to know which one
we should call
and when so let's say
if network is available we use the
remote one
otherwise we use the local cache so now
we make this code
more complex rather than simple but that
was an
easy change, absolutely, that was an easy
change
fulfill the requirement move on now we
have two dependencies they are both
concrete
and code is starting to get more
immobile because every time there is a
new requirement we're going to come here
and add more if statements
more logic and very easily this view
controller is going to be a thousand
lines long
and everybody is going to be afraid of
changing it
and our diagram now looks like this
which looks easier we have less things
but I don't think it's simpler
because it's not simple to change this
anymore yeah I cannot change the
behavior of the ViewController without
changing
the internal code which means it's not
open for extension
yeah we're going towards rigid town
here so how can we go back
and have the FeedViewController
depending on that interface but it still
have this new behavior right so we can
use composition
we can encapsulate this logic to
a type that checks if the network is
available
will fetch the remote otherwise it's
going to rely on the
local version of the feed so let's do
that and I'm going to undo the
changes here so we are back to having
just the loader
interface but now we're going to add a
new type right
so we move the same logic we added in
the ViewController but now
into a service but again how can we make
the ViewController
talk to this service we have to go to
the ViewController and change it
if it's a concrete type like this yeah
the ViewController talks to a
FeedLoader
so if we make this RemoteWithLocal
FallbackFeedService
conform to the FeedLoader protocol we
can then plug it to the ViewController
and the ViewController remains agnostic
from the provenance
of the feed and the RemoteFeedLoader
also is agnostic of this and the
LocalFeedLoader is also agnostic of those
types
absolutely these types are isolated
and they can be tested isolated but here
we can compose them into this new type
and separate the concerns
throughout the system so to do it we
can transform this service into actually
a loader
that also implements the FeedLoader
interface I like this change it reflects
the intent
of the class based on the FeedLoader
protocol so what we does is it composes
these two
concrete types as you can see we are
using the concrete types here
so now how does this look in the diagram
seems scary
as you can see the RemoteWithLocal
FallbackFeedLoader
implements the FeedLoader and it
depends on a RemoteFeedLoader and a
Local
FeedLoader everything else hasn't
changed yes which means the
ViewController has no idea of this
logic which means we changed the
behavior of the code without changing
the ViewController we added a new way
of composing these things and I really
like that
because the FeedViewController it
doesn't know
where the feed is coming from and it
doesn't care
and how easy we can test now the Feed
ViewController there
yeah we can test everything here in
isolation which is great
and we can use the type system to help
us compose those types together
and if you think this is a property of
protocols no it's not you can do the
same with closures
yeah I'm very happy with this design we
can even simplify this code here we can
just forward
the completion blocks
for example we can keep changing the
implementation of this
until we are happy with it let's say we
have a
load function that depending on the
network state
we do one thing or the other
yeah I mean it doesn't matter right as
long as you conform to the interface
you can test this behavior and refactor the
code until you're happy with it
for example instead of having just one
local maybe
you're gonna have different types of
fallbacks then you can have an array of
fallbacks
it's up to you as the requirements
change you don't have to
break any other part of the system to
add new behavior and that's the open
close
principle plus the dependency version as
long as you have this clear separation
you have options
and that's simple I would argue it's
easy
as well if you know how to do it it
doesn't take more time
so one thing I would like to mention
here is that perhaps the diagram
looks a little bit scary with all these
colors and all these blocks
but when we would instantiate all these
types
I think it's much simpler it could be a
one-liner
for example you can create your
ViewController
it's a FeedViewController and we pass a
loader
anything that conforms to the loader
interface for example we can
create it with a RemoteFeedLoader or we
can create another one
with a LocalFeedLoader or we can create
another one
that uses the RemoteWithLocalFallback
FeeLoader right and then we pass the
RemoteFeedLoader
and the LocalFeedLoader for example
that's my point here that
the code doesn't reflect the complexity
of the diagrams
because the thing is this diagram is not
complex
that is yeah that is true if you can
read this yeah that makes sense
yeah but in the beginning I think it can
be
a bit daunting especially for newcomers
yes and some people might say well
so you're creating the FeedViewController
with those dependencies which
means
I cannot use storyboards all right
because I don't have control over the
instantiation of my ViewController well
is this a fallacy or not I think it is
yeah because what I can do is
for example I can set my loader
after it's created we're shifting from
initializer injection to
property injection here and now we can
inject those dependencies
you can use custom segways you can use
custom objects in your storyboard or nib
files
we have a video where we show these
techniques you can find a link in the
description
so there's no excuses if you want to
have composable types
it's a choice it's just a choice there's
nothing magical about it
right you don't have to but if you want
to you can
alright I think that's it for today and
we'll see you again next time