Hello Mike, hey Caio
so today let's talk about decomposing
code
into modules okay more modular
design here so let's use the same
example as last time
where we created a FeedViewController
that has a reference to a FeedLoader
protocol
and then we have two types that
implement the protocol well three types
we have the RemoteFeedLoader the Local
FeedLoader
and then we have one that composes the
two and we said that
we are decomposing them into modules by
using these different colors which means
there are five modules here, four of
those
are in our control and one of those is
UIKit
I think we can zoom out and demonstrate
a little bit better this
modularity going on there, so let's start
from UIKit that's an easy one
so this is UIKit let's forget about the
types and let's think about modules
yes exactly up from UIKit we have a
ViewController
and what kind of module would you add a
ViewController to right I think that's
an easy one it's the UI
module, okay so if we call the views
a UI module does it make sense to have
the FeedLoader protocol
as a UI element I guess it depends what
the FeedLoader represents there it
represents a behavior
that the UI requires like a feature
so I think we can make the case of yeah
it could be
but then again maybe it can reside in
its own module
but for now they have the same color as
they had in the previous episode so
let's imagine that
this protocol or interface it's a
boundary right we are defining a
behavior that we want
but we don't have and we expect another
module to implement it
okay so this represents a boundary right
it's an entry
point or even an exit point where
messages go
out and in and this is the point that
separates the modules that's the
dependency inversion
by introducing this protocol in the
previous episode we showed how
the UI stop depending on concrete Feed
Loaders and the FeedLoaders don't know
about the UI
yes so this is an entry point for the
Feed
feature yes exactly so let's call this a
Feature interface right we can have a
bunch of methods here we can have a
bunch of interfaces
that will be implemented by external
modules so in this case we have the Feed
Loader but we can have a FeedItem
struct right as a model for passing data
around
yes, from module to module so the Feed Feature
interfaces
are a bunch of functions, protocols
and data it just happens that at this
point
it lives in the same module as the UI
I think that's
much better to visualize in our heads
probably because
now the RemoteFeedLoader depends on a
Feed Feature
rather than a UI interface there
yes so what is this RemoteFeedLoader
right so we know that it has some sort
of interaction
with a network so we can name it as a
component of the API module right so
it's like the Feed API module
for example yes and the LocalFeed
Loader
it has to do with persistence I'm happy
to name it Database or something like
that
right a repository or database
yeah and then we have the type that
composes the two
yes it's a composer right and we
normally compose
types in the Main module it's a good
idea since all the arrows
come from this module and none of the
arrows
go towards this module so Main
I think is a great example yes
we could create an Adapter module or we
could create a Composer
module or we can just leave it in Main
for now
right and we should make that clear that
these modules can contain
a bunch of components right it just
happened that we showcased
an example with one component, one class
in each module but in reality they can
have a bunch of them
yeah the Main module can have the App
Delegate for example
you can have a bunch of factories and
assemblers you can have composers
adapters, right exactly, the API module
can have
services, URLSessions, services
the Database can have Core Data
dependencies or
Realm and the Feed Feature component
can have a bunch of interfaces as we
mentioned and Feed models
right so this is a fairly common way of
composing
applications if you're breaking down
things in modules, yeah I agree
but at some point we might say well I
want to have an AppKit
application as well we're using those
other types
which at some point we might say well we
need to separate the Feed
Feature from the concrete UI because
this UI is a UIKit
user interface right so you might end up
with
a new module the Feed Feature module
where we have all the interfaces
and shared models but it's important to
say that this
Feed Feature module doesn't depend on any
other module where there are no arrows
coming out of this
only arrows coming in it's the boundary
module
exactly now we can have different UIs
and we are able to plug and play those
modules together as needed
and this seems great on paper but
it's not the everyday use case
however it doesn't have to be in order
to
create an architecture like this
because
such a design enables us to as you said
switch modules or components without
knowing the rest of the system without
depending on the rest of the system
and test and isolation as well exactly
exactly
enables us to test in isolation and also
we can reuse those in different
applications
but this is not normally the use case
normally you have one application
and it's iOS or only macOS
and you don't have the need to reuse
these in other applications you don't
have the needs to use these
into other platforms so there are other
ways we can compose this we don't have
to start with this level of separation
this is maybe an extreme case where
everything is decomposed
in separate modules but the point here
is that it is possible to do
and if there is the need it should be
able to easily adapt
but a much simpler app
for example the API, Database and the
Feature interfaces
and models in the same module and you
can decide to separate the UI
right so here we have the API the
Database and the Feed Feature
modules with red which denotes that they
are
in the same module in the same module
basically yes exactly
and then the UI has a dependency on this
Feed Feature
which may create some coupling
especially between the API and the
Database there
this diagram doesn't show that but it
could very well be
as long as you don't add a dependency
here
right or the other way around yeah
and as you said you can create some
coupling here unnecessarily
maybe your UI doesn't need a database
but as long as the arrows
are pointing in the same direction with
the same level of abstraction
you're still able to decompose as needed
if at some point you want to reuse the
API another application you just move it
to another
framework and then if there's the need
to share the database you do the same
and you go back to here so we should be
able to go
from everything in the same module
to set up your module right and you can
even decide to put
even a Composer in the same module for
example and then you don't have a Main
module
or maybe the UI is the Main module in
this case because it's going to compose
those types directly
or you could have everything in the same
module apart from UIKit's because we
don't own
UIKit right and this is the case
for a monolith application as they say
right
yeah it's a monolith but it's still well
separated which means we can break this
monolith as needed
and I would advise people to start
probably here keep everything in the
same module
but keep a logical separation of
concerns
so if you ever need to break it down
it's easy so there's nothing wrong with
monolith
as long as you keep your types modular
inside the monolith and as we saw in the
previous episode you have the same
amount of code
you're just breaking down into small
classes or structs or functions
with clean interfaces in between them
right exactly
one downside though in this monolith
approach and I guess this is a matter of
preference but
if you're creating an iOS project you're
going to have to see the simulator
and well it bugs me to be honest having
to test
API components or Database components
through the simulator
instead of having the mac as a test
target and having
blazing fast unit tests you say that if
we have a Database
module that is not in an iOS target
we can run it without the simulator, yes
exactly
and we can run the tests without the
simulator, yes, and the same for the APIs
and for any type that doesn't require
UI yes it would be much better to
test those types without the simulator
but if they live in an iOS target
to run your tests you need to boot a
simulator
which is let's say three to five times
slower or maybe more
it's costly and it can add up
so it's a trade-off you can definitely
start like this
if you see the need of having faster
tests which might be
immediately for some people then you can
just
extract your code with these boundaries
and
good source code dependencies but you
also add some overhead of maintaining
separate frameworks absolutely
absolutely that's
that's that's one of the trade-offs so
that's pretty much
one way of composing types in separate
modules you can have all the types in
one module
but as long as they are separated your
monolith is still
pretty testable and decomposed as needed
you can
move those types to separate modules for
usability for testability
for faster tests or for whatever reason
you need to move them
but why so rare to see applications they
are
composable or decomposable, in my opinion
I think it's because
it's harder to do so it requires a steep
learning curve there
and we often see developers wanting
control
of their components and referencing
components
inside other components without good
separation
like dependency injection, initializer
injection in this case you know
enforcing immutability so working with
concrete types
you feel more in control and having even
procedural code
feels like you're more in control
because you can see line by line what's
happening
but as soon as you start using dynamic
dispatch and start using interfaces
and closures people start getting afraid
yes absolutely
so for the untrained eye perhaps it's
harder to think abstractly
for example invoking a closure in a
function
instead of having an implicit dependency
of a singleton let's say
and invoking the singleton's function
directly
which would lead them probably to have
an architecture as we commonly see
in iOS applications where we have the UI
talking to a concrete model layer that
could be a ViewModel or a Presenter
that then talks directly to another
concrete API or a concrete Database that
could be singletons or it can be
injected but they are concrete
and they are not very easily composable
you might have a chance
of injecting different behaviors by
subclassing but
you would see UIKit elements in the
Model layer
you might even see UIKit elements like
UIImages
in the API or Database layer and there's
no clear separation
of concerns sometimes you see the UI
fetching things from the Database directly
or the API
it's often the case that we see UI
elements accessing
databases and APIs for convenience might
be easier at a time or faster
but you quickly lose control the so
desired control you wanted in the
beginning
yeah and I think in this example the
problem is the lack of proper
communication
between these modules where there are no
predefined communication channels maybe
they're going to be
bi-directional or single direction
communication between the Model and the
UI or the UI and the Model there
the API and the Model, the Database and
the Model
so we're going to see components being
referenced all over the place the UI
in the Database or the Database in the
UI
and this can create tight coupling and
confusion and rigidity as we go on
the so called spaghetti architecture yes and
to be fair
you can still have a concrete
architecture there is no spaghetti
if you keep the layers separated
like this it might work well for a
majority of applications
absolutely, depending on the application
I'm working on if it's very simple I
would probably start like this
but I know how to go from this
architecture
to something more modular and I would do
the transitions as needed
backed up by tests backed up by the
compiler
so there's nothing wrong with starting
like this or having an architecture
that is super monolithic and start
breaking it down as needed
you don't have to start with a very
modular application
and again a modular application doesn't
need to be complex
yes that's very important if we follow
good
principles we can end up with a pretty
good architecture there
I've seen codebases they were
monolithic and they were very concrete
but they were
easy to change they were easy to work on
they were tested you just need to
understand the trade-offs you need to
understand the problem you are trying to
solve and tailor the solution
yes that's that's the most important
thing to remember
that there is no holy grail right for
architecture or design you need to
tailor it to your own needs
as my friend likes to say you can fit
both
feet in one shoe right you need to
tailor it to
your own requirements and it's hard
it's definitely hard to do so, so my
advice is to learn different approaches
because the more you know the more
options you have to solve problems
we have problems and we find solutions
we don't settle with
lesser value, yes absolutely, for example
going back to our super modular approach
you can then have another module that is
an Assembler, a Builder or a Factory
that composes everything together, whoa
that's a lot of dashes and a lot of
arrows there
and it might look complex but when you
translate this to code is
four lines of code two lines of code or
one line of code
it's not that hard it's simple it can
achieve the same level separation
by following OO principles or functional
principles
yeah I agree 100% with you it might
seem complex but it's not it's simple
and it's worth testing it out by
yourselves
so I think that's it and we'll see you
again next time