Hello Mike, hey Caio
so we've been talking a lot about
architecture and we end up with this
modular diagram right it's just a proof
of concept
and we also discussed that sometimes
having a more monolithic
approach can actually be a better
solution
so what is a good architecture for me
it's an architecture that solves
the problem at hand and we came up with
this architecture while trying to create
a problem
and solving it right otherwise all
architectures are good
yes they need to solve something yes and
solve it well
in an elegant form yes so our point here
is that
to decide which architecture you're
going with it depends on the
requirements
so if you have bad requirements you can
end up with a better architecture as
well
exactly and the process of dealing
with the requirements and refining the
requirements as you go
and making more things known to the
developer team
I would make the bold claim that if you
have very good requirements
you will end up with good architecture
um
right probabilistically maybe I don't
know like it's not a
certainty okay it increases the chances
yes it's
it's definitely more probable I would
say because if you have well-defined
requirements
it's easier to design your system
absolutely because
you know what you need to build I think
most of the problems
occur when the assumptions are going to
be made by the developer
because of the miscommunication with
other
team members and I'm not saying the
developer is
the victim here no communication is the
victim here
you know from all parts but the goal of
the design
is not only to solve the current problem
because software is soft it's constantly
changing so you need to have a
trade-off with welcoming future changes
and solving the current problem you
don't want to abstract too much
to solve a future problem that might
never happen
but you also don't want to make your
architecture rigid enough that if you
need to change things
it's too hard absolutely and this is a
very very
difficult problem to solve basically you
need to facilitate
future needs at the same time you don't
know what these needs are going to be
so what do you do well you establish
good processes that's what you do from
the requirements
to planning, to designing, to architecting
to coding
everything, communicating of course very
very important there
and a good architecture is a form of
communication, of course it is
just like a requirement just like a
diagram or a planning session
exactly and we showed how bad
requirements
bad planning, bad execution might lead
you to end up with a very
rigid architecture where we have no
clear boundaries
we have no clear flow of control
the dependency graph here shows that
every module depends
on every other module which makes things
super rigid
and fragile, spaghetti architecture
let's not kid ourselves here yes and
most of the time
this is the byproduct of bad
requirements yes that's where
everything starts right if you're trying
to
fulfill the current requirement and
that's a bad requirement
and you have no long-term vision no
long-term goals
any architecture is fine it's like the
saying
if you don't know where you're going any
path is fine
right I like that yes that's exactly
right
and it's also the lack of discipline
in order to refine the requirements in
order to learn more, to care
to find out okay what should we do here
what should we do there you know
establish some branches of logic
some edge cases because the requirements
are bad it doesn't mean that the code
should be bad doesn't mean that the
product should have bugs or
mistakes so who's to blame the developer
to write the code the analyst that
writes the requirements
the product manager, the business who's
to blame right I don't like to blame
anyone
I think it's a communication problem
that can be solved it's
everyone's responsibility everyone
should hold themselves accountable
exactly in a functional team if a
developer sees that the requirement is
not good enough the developer will help
the analyst or whoever wrote it to
improve it
there's no blame and if an analyst sees
that
the end result the developers built
doesn't fulfill
actually the requirements they would
hold their developers accountable
right and that's the best case scenario
unfortunately
that's not the case everywhere so why
don't we show a progression of how you
can end up
in a state like you just mentioned okay
so we're talking about this Feed
feature so let's follow the same example
we've been using right
imagine we receive a new task
we open our project management tool and
we see this new story
assigned to us okay as you can see
as a user I want the app to load to the
feed so I can see the feed
okay we are laughing here but I see
those stories
all the time no absolutely, absolutely
this is out there
and the problem with these stories is
that first of all the developers don't
actually understand what kind of value
are we delivering
to our customers what are the benefits
of using this feature
why are we building this you know it's
so shallow
how I'm going to build this where are
the error cases
right what is the feed what does load
mean, load it from where
yes so then we look at the acceptance
criterias
given a user when the user opens the
feed
then the feed is displayed okay that
sounds a bit obvious but there's so many
questions
in there this is probably even gonna
drive
our tests, yes, but what kind of value are
we delivering
right exactly and this is a prime
example of the
miscommunication we mentioned before
so clearly here the
analyst or it doesn't matter someone
might be the developer as well
in some cases they have not communicated
properly
the intent of the system mentioning
edge cases and as you mentioned the
value where is the value for
the customer here so how can we improve
this because if I get a story like this
what I would do is to go back to the
analyst to whoever wrote it
and start asking questions like how can
we improve this and for me this is the
value
of doing BDD right for me it's the
conversation part
it's not about tools it's not about
testing, is understanding
what the maximum value you can
provide to the customer and sorry but
you're not going to provide that
with three lines written there
right you you need to dig deeper
basically
you need to understand deeper all the
possible scenarios that are out there
although this is a bad story for me this
is the beginning
of a very good conversation you're gonna
have with the business
to understand the value proposition
absolutely and if you go
and start the conversation by being
negative and
blaming others then I don't think you're
gonna reach very
far but that's the clear message
that the business is passing or this
analyst representing the business
is passing to you so it's in your hand
to understand more and go build a case
the biggest problem is when developers
see a story like this
and they are afraid of asking questions
because they think they're going to
sound silly right
they think they're going to lose
credibility because
they believe they should be able to read
these and imply
everything and that's the biggest
mistake right well I can't
so I'm always pro for the questions no
matter how
silly or it doesn't matter you know the
vision
is common for everyone or it should be
common for everyone
we're on the same team that's my
understanding of this thing
for me actually that's my job I have the
technical knowledge
to ask the right questions and get the
answers to deliver the highest amount of
value
to the customers and that's how we
create good products
you have good habits one of those is
asking a bunch of questions so you can
understand better
what is the need of the customer what is
the need
of the business and then you can
implement that need
through code, yes so what we would like
to end up with
is a document that is much more precise
than this
for example what started as just a
load the feed and show to the user can
end up as
as an online customer right it's a
customer with
connectivity right I want the app to
automatically load my latest image feed
so it's an image feed so I can always
enjoy the newest images
of my friends okay so now I can see the
value proposition here
yes we are zooming in, exactly
so we started from a super high level
view of what we're doing
but after having the right conversations
we learned that
well this feature is to connect friends
sharing their
images or their travels or their food or
whatever they want to share with their
friends
right and a bunch of other user
experience information
like automatically loading the latest
and
my feed right it's my latest feed
right it's customized right it has value
to the customer
okay so now we can start painting a much
better image
of the system, yes from this narrative
we can come up with the scenarios or the
acceptance criteria
for example given the customer has
connectivity
when the customer requests to see the
feed
then the app should display the latest
feed from remote
and replace the cache with the new feed
okay so we need to cache the feed
somehow
right exactly by asking the right
questions
for example what happens if I don't have
connectivity we came up with the concept
of caching
the latest downloaded feed and that
created a
second narrative as an offline customer
I want the app to show the latest saved
version of my image feed
so I can always enjoy images of my
friends right so if you are in the tube
and you open the app you still see
something you don't see just an error
message
absolutely just by asking questions but
look how we
expanded the value yes we're breaking
down
the system requirements and we can
branch out
to the online and the offline
user experience and from there we can
even
branch out to if we have a cached
version of the feed if we don't have a
cached version of the feed what should
happen there
which lead us to more scenarios for
example
when the customer doesn't have
connectivity and requests to see the
feed
then the app should display the latest
feeds saved
but if there's nothing in the cache then
the app should display an error
right but the value proposition is to
always try to show something to the user
and that's the kind of value you can
only get by having a conversation from
technical people
with the business bridging the business
and the technical side
is super important to deliver value to
the customers
and as you can see we can write some
high high level tests
from those scenarios not just the test
right but through the tests
you can see components emerging you can
see behaviors emerging
and this shouldn't take hours and long
meetings no
this could be an informal conversation I
wouldn't even call this a meeting
yes yes absolutely, and there are other
approaches
right BDD is not the only way of doing
this
right I know you are a big fan of Ivar
Jacobson
guilty, so why don't you explain to us a
little bit about use cases
right so we can represent in another
form
pretty much what we had in the scenarios
of course it's not the same
but here we can see an algorithmic view
of what the system should be doing so in
this case we have the Load Feed
which has as input a URL
represented by the data and then we have
a primary course
which for this case we have denoted as
happy path as well
and then we have a sequence of steps
a finite sequence of steps actually that
this component should do
and I like how this doesn't talk about
user interface or
showing a feed to a user or pressing a
button
or any kind of user interaction with the
system
it's a much more procedural approach to
it maybe more technical they don't have
to be
but they are more technical in this case
and for me they are a complement
of the user stories I don't think we
have to choose between
BDD or use cases no I think we can start
from
the BDD story we can have conversations
we can improve it we can document that
and then from what we learn from those
stories and from those scenarios
we can start stretching out the more
technical side of it
with the use cases right absolutely for
example we have a concept here of
invalid data that we could have written
it
in our scenarios in our BDD stories but
I like to
have this more technical approach in a
separate format
as a developer I find it more readable
easier to digest
yes because it's a recipe that's what it
is it's a checklist right
it's just a sequence of steps that your
component
needs to do that's how we understand
things you know if it has a
beginning a middle and an end it's much
easier to digest
and the error cases of course and we
need the error cases there as well
we have the data input/output for
example the input is a URL
and the output is the feed items right
but it doesn't say it's an array of feed
items that's up to the developer
yeah we don't know if this is too high
level to understand
right now you know how we're going to
implement that and even though it reads
like a procedural
step-by-step thing it doesn't have to be
procedural code
you can use OO here for example you can
have a functional approach
we can have a bunch of objects
collaborating to achieve this
or a bunch of functions or monads, yes
exactly it might look procedural but it
doesn't mean that
all these steps are gonna happen
procedurally
in one method for instance of course not
when the time comes
we're gonna have to dive into a more
detailed
level where we're going to have to
follow different kind of principles
and these principles they talk about
code how to
structure and write your code here we're
talking about requirements we're talking
about
business requirements in this case so
it's open
yes it's an algorithm but it's open
how we're going to implement it and
another example
expanding the use cases we can have a
separate use case
that is the Load Feed Fallback if the
Load Feed fails
so it's for the offline customer
following again
this algorithmic approach we have a
primary course the happy path
that specifies what the recipe
for retrieving feed items is and
again we specify well what happens if we
don't have
a cache or we have no items in the cache
in this case
well we deliver no feed items
yeah and what is no feed items well
it's up to the developers
again exactly anyone can understand this
although it's more technical
than the BDD style yes it complements
the BDD style
by bridging and getting closer and
closer to the technical side
and when it is written and read by
business people it improves the quality
of the process
absolutely it facilitates the whole
process of the development
and it improves communication for sure
just to be more precise not just
business people writing it but
in collaboration with developers when
they both sit down and write this
together
and yeah these are roles right it
doesn't mean that a developer cannot be
a
you know a "business person" in air quotes
oh yeah you can
right these are just roles I mean
usually there are separate people
conforming to these roles you know
but yeah it could be and finally the
last use case
would be to Save the Feed Items in the
cache
where we execute the save items command
with the data
provided then the system is going to
encode the items we're going to
timestamp it
it's going to replace the cache with the
new data and then deliver a success
message yes
if you have this requirement wouldn't it
be much easier to implement the feature
and now if you don't have 15 minutes to
half an hour
to come up with good requirements you
have bigger problems
exactly than bad requirements yes yes
right there's something wrong in there
that needs to be solved
but look at all the details we come up
with
from a basic story that's the process
you start with a bad story
and you improve it in collaboration with
the business
the goal is to crush the assumptions and
that's what this
process does you eliminate them
you know more and more and more about
the system
and about the requirements about what
the customer needs
that's why we believe it's so valuable
there are even other ways to represent
those requirements to improve
the knowledge sharing right other views
absolutely like the flowchart for
example
another problem of working with bad
stories is that
how would you make a flow chart for
example from this story
right it would be sequential very linear
right
very linear, Show feed screen
Fetch new items, Update screen, profit
yeah
well maybe, maybe hopefully
it's like is this the path we are
implementing here
I don't think so because the actual
value is better defined
in this detailed document now if we
drive a flow chart
from the detail requirements it will be
much more descriptive
like this one right look how we show the
feed screen
we fetch the new items and then we have
different paths
from that yes if it succeeds we cache
the new items
and we update the feed, if it does not
succeed to fetch the new items
then we try to load it from the cache
and update the feed screen
right this is much more descriptive and
anyone can understand this
I can show this to anyone in the
business side I can show this to
a developer as well it's very clear but
we can only come up with this flowchart
by understanding
what we are building and then we can
represent the detail requirements
in different visual forms and one of
those
is our beloved modular architecture
so look at that we started from the
bad requirement you know the zoomed out
version of the requirement and then we
dived in, we dived in
and at the end we come back to this
design
this is the byproduct of the whole
process
of breaking down the requirements and
ending up
here the architecture the design is
derived from
the requirements and by getting better
requirements we understand better
the problem we understand better
the value position and we may even
understand better
how this product can evolve in the
future so we can come up with better
designs for our code it's all
interconnected
you cannot separate architecture you cannot
separate
testing you cannot separate value we
cannot separate business it cannot
separate developers
everything is connected so the only way
to come up with good solutions
is to have good communication absolutely
in my opinion this is
the single most important thing
understand what is going on
eliminate assumptions I know we
mentioned so many times but it is true
so yeah we need to find a way to
eliminate the assumptions
and communicate with our team with the
developer team
with other teams even better that's the
process
as you said it doesn't take too much I
mean of course
when you start out it's going to take a
lot of time
you'll improve as with anything that we
do right
and 15 minutes, 20 minutes for something
for a feature like this yeah it's
definitely enough
even if it takes longer right what if it
takes
maybe an hour, two hours as long as it
pays off
as long as we gather the requirements we
need
yes absolutely what's the quote if I
have six hours
to cut down a tree I'm gonna spend four
hours
sharpening my axe right well that's it
right it's
pretty much the same thing here and we
do that
to eliminate the risk as much as we can
as much as we can yes we try to
eliminate the risk of doing mistakes
because mistakes are what are costing
businesses
a lot of money and we shouldn't be
accomplices in costing businesses a lot
of money
because we are hurting ourselves at the
end of the day, communication
is key so now that we laid out this
foundation
for our proposed architecture let's stop
here and in next episodes
we can start actually implementing it
yeah
can't wait for it and we'll see you
again next time