Hello Mike, hey Caio
so today we're going to continue the
Feed Feature case study we started last
time
exactly so I've created a GitHub repo
with all the BDD specs we created in
previous episodes, use cases
flowchart and the initial proposed
architecture
but we are still missing the user
interface design
and a backend, right I think we can
manage
without them you can start you can
communicate with the other team
what the contract between the server and
the client is going to be
then both teams can work their way to
the feature with unit tests always so
from the requirements we gather
we can come up with a model spec for the
Feed Item
so let's say by talking to the backhand
folks
you can come up very quickly with at
least a spec
that's not final of course things are
always changing but
at least something to start working on
some kind of contract as you said
so a Feed Item for example you can agree
that it has
an identifier and let's say it's a UUID
you may also have a description
in this case it's optional, location
that is also a String
that's optional and the URL to download
the image, right
normally those specs come from
conversations with the designers as well
because
they probably have some kind of sketches
already
and they know they're gonna have to
display the image we'll have some kind
of description
right now the id is a technical detail
that the backend developers and the
frontend developers agreed upon
yeah that's understandable so we can end
up with a payload contract
like this one we're going to execute a
GET request to a specific URL
to be defined and we expect to get a 200
response
right we're going to represent the Feed
Items
as an array of objects so for example
every Feed Item will have an id and an
image for sure
as defined in the model specs but
description and location
are optional so for example this object
doesn't have location
and this object doesn't have description
and location which means if we have a
missing
key in our object we can just ignore it
for description and location but id and
image should always be there
and an image should be a valid URL and
the id should be a valid
UUID, okay that makes sense let me also
point out here
that this is very very convenient for
anyone who is going to see
this contract as we mentioned last time
eliminating assumptions
is a key part for succeeding in making
good systems
and I think that the developer when he
sees
okay the location is optional the
description is optional and now they see
this picture here where you can see an
example
of the API response I think that might
help them
understand even better the requirement
I like that
we pretty much have a set of valid
responses
that we can even use in our unit tests
absolutely and this is the kind of
detail I like to have in requirements
yeah it's beneficial for everyone not
just the developer you know like
everyone that is gonna
contribute to this project we are all in
this
together you know we are on the same
team so at the end of the day
we make our lives easier as well, agreed
awesome so let's start definitely
but from where should we start right
I always like to start from the parts of
the system we have the most
information, yes so that would exclude
the UI
right now yes we know what we're going
to present in the UI
and we could come up with some
prototypes
it is an option but maybe in the Remote
FeedLoader we have
more confidence since we even have the
JSON payload contract
right we have everything that we need
except the URL which we
don't need to build the system so that's
option one and we want to separate
the RemoteFeedLoader from the user
interface
so the UI module would not talk directly
with the RemoteFeedLoader
we have an interface or a Feature module
in between
with the interfaces and data types
right and we could start from this place
as well right so you mean the Feed Item
could live in this module the protocol
or the abstraction for loading the feed
can live there as well
yes the representation of the Feed Item
model
will be in this shared module right and
this model can be created from a remote
representation or from the cache
representation
and we could now develop this feature in
parallel
I could implement the UI you could
implement the RemoteFeedLoader
and another developer could implement
the LocalFeedLoader
in parallel and at the end we just
compose all the implementations together
right so what I like about option two
the Feed Feature
is that all arrows point to that
meaning it doesn't depend on anything
else I think that's a good candidate
to start okay and at the end of this
series
we might end up with five different
modules meaning five different
frameworks
but let's start as a modular monolith
let's keep the code modular but the code
can
all live in the same project for now
I agree with that
and what I like to do is create a macOS
target
and separate the UI that is going to
live in an iOS target
in a different project and we can start
implementing all the components the Feed
Feature, the RemoteFeedLoader, the Local
FeedLoader
in the mac target right so all of those
modules here don't depend on UIKit
exactly so we can run it on a macOS
target and run our tests much faster
without the simulator
yes I prefer that, okay that makes sense
so
let's start as a macOS framework yes
let's call it EssentialFeed, yeah
okay clean project let's create a file
that's our FeedItem first okay so our
FeedItem
has an id
that's a UUID right it's not optional
description, the description is an
optional String
yes, location it's also optional
and the imageURL, that is a
non-optional URL
very nice so this FeedItem now is
internal
and we want several modules to create
this FeedItem
right it might be created from a remote
representation
or it might be created from a local
cache representation
yes, if we want external modules to be
able to create
FeedItems we need to provide a public
initializer
is this something we need to decide
right now we don't need to do it right
now
why don't we wait until we have a
compiler error
okay let's commit, all right so we have
actually a bunch of things here let's
commit first the project
okay create EssentialFeed
framework now let's commit to the Feed
Item
create the FeedItem model okay
beautiful so we have the FeedItem and
the interface yes that will separate
the modules right the boundary interface
yes
and we call it FeedLoader right we talked
extensively
about a closure version of it
or a protocol version of it I think we
can go with the protocol version here
okay so the protocol FeedLoader
yes what kind of behavior do we want
here to load items
so we will pass the completion block
right
and it needs to be escaping now we need
to think about
the return because previously we just
showed
the happy path yes when it works and it
returns an array of feed items for
example
yes now this may fail, loading the feed
may fail
right exactly so we can
create a Result type and we know that
for the success
case we want to pass along the Feed
Items
and now the error case is interesting
many things can go wrong
yeah how do you represent that well the
standard way in Swift is to use the
error protocol and it's up to the
clients
to cast it to a specific error type
right
if they care about the error type so
I'm happy to go with that right now but
starting from the Feed Feature starting
from these
abstractions it can bear risk because
for instance we could provide our own
error type here
perhaps we can provide a bunch of cases
that based on the
use cases and the requirements we have
already can represent some of the
sad paths however I feel that it is too
early in the project
to do that yeah so should we just go
with the protocol now and we change in
the future
yeah I think so okay so calling it
Result probably is not a good name
because result of
what, right, so why don't we call it Load
FeedResult yes much more specific here
if
at some point we decide to use a generic
result type we can have a typealias
yeah I think that makes sense okay so
this is what a FeedLoader should return
a LoadFeedResult it's either a success
with an array of with FeedItems
or an error, yes awesome so I think
that's it
that's the initial interface we'll be
working with
we only defined our data types and
our protocol boundary so we don't need
to test anything
we don't have any behavior here
everything we declared here
will be checked by the compiler yeah we
can commit
and then bundle those two files in a
folder
awesome let's commit create the
FeedLoader protocol
boundary yes and as you said we should
probably bundle these two things
into a folder and let's call it Feed
Feature yeah
okay you can always change it later yeah
Group Feed Feature
files yep perfect
so I think that's it for now and next
time we can
start doing the networking part
sounds good
perfect we'll see you all next time