Hello Mike, hey Caio
so we finished the implementation of the
Feed API module
we paid a lot of attention with the
production code and test code
but there are more steps we can take to
improve the integrity of the codebase
including automating a continuous
integration pipeline
and we can even add end-to-end tests at
this stage
to test the integration of the Feed API
module with a backend
absolutely but first there is a test
configuration
where we can randomize the order of the
tests which will increase
their value yeah so we can go to the
scheme
edit scheme, test
and the options for the target we can
select randomize
execution order and why would we do that
right by randomizing our tests we
eliminate any possible
order dependency that might exist in our
test suite that could affect the test
results
exactly so let's see if we have any
order issue
running the tests and they still pass
beautiful which means that there is no
order dependency
for example we don't expect the first
test to run
before the second one because we don't
want a test method to depend
on another one to run first absolutely
you want all the tests
to run perfectly in isolation and as a
group as well
so if one test fails all the reasons for
its failure is
within its own method definition yeah
we've seen many codebases where
you need to run each test in isolation
and you see it pass
but when you run all the test suite you
get a bunch of errors
and this is a flaky test suite
and the opposite as well they pass in
integration but they don't pass
in isolation yeah you don't want that
alright so let's commit
so enable random test execution
order to guarantee there is
no order dependency between
test methods another option
we have here is to run the tests in
parallel
right what do we gain by doing so in
theory by running in parallel you can
speed up
the execution of the tests but we do
have a few tests
so I don't think there is any benefit in
enabling it
now since we don't have a performance
problem there's nothing
to improve at this time exactly another
option we can enable here
is the gather coverage right
the legendary code coverage exactly and
we can select to run it for all targets
or only the ones we care about
so let's select the targets we care
about in this case it's the Essential
Feed
so now when we run the test Xcode will
gather coverage analysis
well I hope it's a 100%
boom okay the Feed API module is 100%
tested
nice but when we're looking at the code
coverage
there's a caveat there I think it's 100%
tested with an asterisk
what code coverage actually measures is
which lines of code were executed
during tests and 100% of the lines were
executed that's what it means it doesn't
mean 100% of the behavior was tested
that's why we often don't even look at
this metric code coverage is not our
goal
it's a side-effect of our TDD process we
write the test first
assert the behavior we expect and then
we write the production code
so we often end up with 100% coverage but
that's not the goal
exactly the goal is to have confidence
that we've tested the behavior and that
we are free
to change our code we are agile and fast
adapting to changes and preventing bugs
yeah it sounds great we can even commit
and keep it on
all the time the overhead seems minimal
here
so I'm happy to leave it on so enable
code coverage gathering but if this
becomes a problem in the future
if it slows down our process we are
going to disable it sounds good
okay I believe those were the settings I
would like to enable to improve our test
integrity but as you mentioned we could
add some end-to-end tests now
exactly we need to test the Feed API
module
with our little cloud in integration so
we can integrate all those components
plus the back end and see if they work
correctly if both sides are conforming
to the agreed contract
and that's very interesting to me
because our backend
is not ready yet I spoken with the
backend
overlords to create a test endpoint
to test the integration so they sent us
a URL we can
get a nice representation of what to
expect
when the API is ready so we're gonna
actually make the request to the back
end and we can investigate
those values to make sure we mapped
everything correctly
and I understand that often you cannot
get a test server like this
but if that's the case they don't have
time to do it I would go there
and build it myself it would take maybe
a couple of minutes
it shouldn't take long yes some
hard-coded values that we can assert in
our tests
exactly and sometimes if you cannot have
a test API you can create
a test account with predefined values
that we can assert against
in our end-to-end tests but if you do so
we should make sure to have a single
test account per application
that means one for each iOS app one
for each Android app etc because we
don't want
other applications interfering with our
test expectations
exactly it's better to isolate the test
and even within an application you may
have multiple test accounts
to run separate tests and we would
advise to use some kind of a vault
system
for the test account passwords yes you
know keep
everything organized and use strong
passwords yes
of course probably "alligator123"
is not gonna cut it here
yes okay but I would like to run those
tests
separately from my main target because I
really appreciate
how fast my unit tests are that sounds
good
so let's add a new target to the project
it's a test bundle we call it
EssentialFeedAPIEndToEnd
tests okay as you can see we got a new
folder where we can edit those tests and
we also got
a new scheme to run our end-to-end tests
in isolation
yes so when we're developing the
EssentialFeed module we can switch
there
when we are developing our end-to-end
tests we can switch
to that scheme exactly okay so let's add
our first end-to-end test
and it looks very similar to a unit test
we don't need anything special
so far so let's call it end
to end test server GET
feed result right it matches the
test account data so the fixed test
account data let's leave some context
here because this should be fixed test
data account
absolutely I like that so we need a
loader
and it's our RemoteFeedLoader
so we must import the EssentialFeed
framework
and the loader needs a URL so that's the
test server URL
and we need a client so the client is
the URLSession
HTTPClient perfect and the test
server URL is the URL the backend folks
gave us
now we need to load our feed and get the
result
and since this is asynchronous we need
to do the same dance
let's create an expectation wait for
load completion
and let's capture the received result
this is a LoadFeedResult so we capture
the result and we fulfill the
expectation
of course we need to wait for the
expectation to be fulfilled but now we
need a timeout here and I would like to
start with a small number
not more than 5 to begin with ideally
this should be between 3-5
seconds
but sometimes depending on the network
performance you have on your machine or
on your CI server
you might have to bump this yeah but
let's start with a small timeout and
let's keep an eye on it
I'm happy to go with 5 for now
finally we can switch
over the received result and we care
about
the success case that's what we want I'm
gonna get a bunch of items to assert
on so in the test account there are
8 items so let me add some more context
to this expectation expected 8 items
in the test account feed so if it fails
we'll know where the problem is
let's also add a nice assertion if it
ever fails
expected successful feed
result got error instead
and since the feed result is optional we
need to
unwrap it right which means we need to
care about the case where it's
nil so default case
expected successful feed result
got no result instead
okay let's run this test
okay they passed but you probably
realized how much slower
those tests are yeah it took
2.7 seconds wow that's a lot
the unit tests are running in 0.1
seconds yep
I think it's a good thing this test case
is isolated
because we don't want to have to run it
all the time
with our unit tests exactly and also the
seconds timeout looks like a good bet
because if we choose 3
it might fail so let's keep it 5
right now I'm happy with it
so we can guarantee here that we are
receiving 8 elements as we expected
in the test account
but there are still the values we think
those elements we care about
so we have a bunch of UUIDs description
location URLs and some cases don't have
description some cases don't have
locations some cases don't have
description
and don't have location exactly so we
want to assert
the fetching and the mapping of the
items in integration here
so we can iterate over the items
let's use a for each
then assert the equality of the item with
an expected
item pass the index of the item
by enumerating the array
and creating a helper function
so expected item at index
we return a FeedItem
then we need an id we can say id at
index description
at index location at index
and imageURL at index
okay I'm not going to make you watch me
type
all of that code so I got this helper
method to get id at index with the
expected ids
the same for description as you can see
some descriptions are
nil when they are not in the JSON the
same for location
and imageURL right okay that's all we
need
oops expected item
alright they are all matching our
expectations but what if they
didn't for example get a wrong
description here
for the element at position 0
okay the test failed but it's hard to
find which one was it
especially when more than one failed
as you can see they both show in the
same line which might be a problem it
might be
hard to debug so we can either add a
message
unexpected item values at
index so now
when they fail we get some extra context
about
which item had the wrong values but when
I have a finite
number of items I know there are 8
items I prefer
not to use for loops and I'll show you
why
what if we had an assertion for item at
a position
for example 0 and we can do the same
for all the other items so 0 to 7
8 items
let me run the tests look at that
we know precisely which one failed and
with which
values I find this much easier to deal
with when they fail
but it's a choice the problem is that
maybe you are dealing with data that is
not fixed
so you don't know how many items you
have in this case I know
and it's not a lot of items I'm happy to
leave 8 items inline
so let's fix the problems here
we're on the test again
and it's passing and as we mentioned in
the last lecture
getting the right feedback makes tests
extremely valuable
you don't have to lose time to find
what's wrong
you want your tests to indicate exactly
why they failed and where and where yeah
exactly and in this case where we have a
finite
number of items yeah I think it's a
no-brainer
so I'm happy to go with the solution all
right let's commit
add end-to-end API tests
in a separate test target
yeah that's it okay
and I think this can be moved into a
helper function because there's a lot of
setup
in this method so we could create a
function
that is related to the test name so
we add more context to the code within
the test method yes
so end-to-end test server GET feed
result so
GET feed result is the action let's
create a method called get
feed result then
getFeedResult will return a
LoadFeedResult and it's optional
because
it might fail or timeout you can just
return the received
result let's run it alright
it's passing let's commit extract
test setup to a helper method
okay I'm happy with this look at it
looks clean yeah
very precise assertions nice messages
although I just found a typo here
unexpected
it happens fix typo
and since we're here why don't we add
memory leak tracking as well
since we are testing everything in
integration that would be a great
addition
so we want to guarantee that the client
and the loader working together
don't generate any memory leak so track
for memory leaks client
and loader but we don't have access to
the function because it's in a separate
target
right they belong in our unit test
but we can add it to the other target as well
by just ticking this box
yep so since they are API
related types I'm fine by adding it to
both targets because they always gonna
move
together agreed we also can get the file
and line
to improve our assertions
let's run it alright no memory leaks
so we automate this check as well add
memory leak
tracking for components in
integration okay so this target
end-to-end tests how often should we run
them
well as often as we want exactly
but you don't want to run them all the
time because they don't have fast
feedback as the unit test
so you might run them less often yeah
I'd say we don't want to run them
while we're developing because the
feedback loop is
much slower but we do run them often
and we would be even better if we could
run them before merging to master for
example
before merging our branch back to the
trunk yes
through a continuous integration
pipeline perhaps exactly we can automate
and create a smoother process within the
team very nice
we don't disturb developer happiness but
at the same time
we reinforce the integrity of our code
base by running
automated tests in our CI exactly
and we want to run both unit test and
end-to-end tests
so we can create a new scheme and we can
even call it
CI now if we
edit the CI scheme in the test option
we can add all the targets we want to
run so the unit tests
and the end-to-end tests and we can also
enable
the randomized execution
and the gather coverage for the targets
we care about okay
let's run the tests on the CI scheme
alright they do pass so let's commit
add
CI scheme and now we need to set up
a continuous integration server yeah and
since this is an open source project
we can use TravisCI yes we're not
vouching for it right you probably need
to find a perfect CI server for your
team
yeah exactly but for open source
projects it's free and easy to set up on
GitHub
so we're going to use it let's create
the travis
YAML file to set up the configuration
okay it's an osx image
with xcode 10.1 the latest one so far
and the language is Swift and we need to
run the script to build and test
the target so let's use the xcodebuild
command line tool
so first we clean the project to make
sure we don't have
any cruft in the CI server then we can
build and
then we test the project
is the EssentialFeed project
and the scheme is CI and since this is
just the CI
integration pipeline making sure we can
build the project and all the test
passes we don't need to code sign it so
we can skip
code signing by setting up an empty
identity
and disable code signing
that's it can we just run the command
first in the terminal to make sure
everything is fine yes
okay it's building we are in the matrix
currently
and test succeeded perfect that's what
we want
so let's add the change and commit
add travis CI config
if we push this to master it should
trigger a CI build
alright there it is, it is running
okay now we just need to wait
alright it's passing fantastic
indeed we have an automated continuous
integration pipeline
now every time we push code to GitHub we
get feedback about our code
so I would like to add the Markdown
for the build passing badge because I
think we deserve it we earned it for
sure
alright let's open the README and
let's add it right at the top
proud of it very proud of it
okay let's add the README
and let's commit add CI viewed
status badge nice that's it
so the Feed API module is ready we also
set up
a continuous integration pipeline so we
can start a new process
from now on instead of pushing
everything directly to master we can
start branching out of master
writing our components yeah modules or
features
and keep merging back to master often
with
the CI pipeline guaranteeing that we can
build the project
all the unit tests and the end-to-end
tests are also
passing so the CI pipeline can give us
confidence that we won't break any
module
in our end-to-end tests we'll guaranteed
that the client
us and the back end are both respecting
the agreed contract
and to be fair we could have set the CI
pipeline from the beginning
it's highly advised to start with a nice
infrastructure for a CI pipeline from
day one
every PR should trigger a build with a
full unit test and end-to-end test run
if everything is okay we allow it to be
merged
to master and we want to merge to master
often we don't want long-lived branches
we keep merging several times a day as
long as the tests are passing we keep
merging to master and why do we do it we
want master
to always be stable right and if
anything fails
we can block the pull request until the
problem is resolved
we want our feedback loop to be fast so
we don't stop the progress
and going further we would like merges
to master to trigger
an automated release of the application
it could go to a beta or TestFlight
group or to the actual App Store that's
a dream isn't it
it's possible and it's not that hard and
as soon as we have a running application
we can start thinking about doing it
absolutely alright so I think it's time
for a recap
about what we've done so far and we can
move on to the persistence or database
module
awesome see you all next time see ya