Hello Mike, hey Caio so in the previous
episode
we started test-driving our RemoteFeed
Loader
we got as far as testing the
communication
with the HTTPClient yeah and before we
carry on
I would like to move this production
code to the production package
outside the test file because I don't
want to be scrolling up and down
up and down, yeah let's do it
so let's create a new folder in
production
and let's call it Feed API yeah this is
the API
let's create a new file RemoteFeed
Loader
and now that we have a separate file we
can open it on the right pane
and keep our tests on the left pane that
sounds really good
let's make some extra space now let's
move the RemoteFeedLoader
to the file and let's move the client
protocol as well that's production code
but now since those types are in a
separate target we need to import
our EssentialFeed module but that's not
enough because those types are internal
right so we need to make a decision here
are we going to expose the internal
types
in the tests by using @testable or are
we going to make these types public
and use them in the test so if we make
this @testable import
the test will have access to those files
right
as you can see it builds fine but when
possible I like to test my components
only through the public interfaces so
why don't we try to
declare everything that makes sense to
be public and see if that's enough
for us to test the code absolutely first
of all the protocol
HTTPClient it can be public because it
can be implemented by
external modules right now the class
RemoteFeedLoader
can also be used by external modules so
it's fine for it to be public and it can
even be created by other modules so we
can make the initializer public as well
and then we have the load behavior it's
the main behavior of this
class so this should be public as well
and what about
the properties yeah I like those private
no one is using
these properties outside this class okay
can we build now
yes that's enough to expose our types to
external modules
and also test it through the public
interfaces fantastic
perfect do we want to allow subclass of
this type
we don't have a use case for that right
now so
I'm happy to make it final and not allow
subclassing
okay so by making it final we prevent
subclasses
of this type and the last change I can
see is the order of the client and the
url properties I think we can reverse so
they can reflect
the order of initializer okay I like
that
yeah perfect let's run the test and
commit
okay it's passing so let's commit
move RemoteFeedLoader components to
production
yep so now we can see both the
test and production code at the same
time I like that, very nice
any more refactorings there let's check
our test names
the naming convention is test underscore
the method we are testing and the
behavior we expect
so test init does not request data from
URL
so the second one tests the method load
and the behavior we expect
requests data from URL oh let me fix
this
requests data from URL very nice
so improve test name let's commit this
okay we can carry on now and one thing
that bothers me
when i'm testing two objects
collaborating like we are doing with the
RemoteFeedLoader
and the HTTPClient is that it's not
important to test just the message that
was passed
but how many times the message was
invoked for example
if by any chance I invoked this method
twice
the test will not fail and this is a
problem because this would be
unexpected behavior
right so although we are calling load
once in our test the client in this case
is called twice
exactly because our spy is capturing
the value that is passed so I can call
this method 10 times
and it always going to capture the last
value passed to it
so although we are asserting that we
passed the right value we are not
asserting how many times
the method was invoked and how many
times it was invoked in this context
is very important because I don't want
to make a bunch of API requests
so we need some sort of mechanism to
keep count of how many times
the client behavior is being invoked
exactly
so I would like to start by adding a new
test
if I call load twice I want to load the
request
twice but if I call load once I want to
load only
once right so let's add a load twice and
it should request
data from URL twice so if I invoke
the load twice we need a better way of
testing
how many times this was invoked and we
can do so by adding an assertion
that something like the requested url
count
should be two and we add a new property
in our spy right and then of course the
requested URL will reflect only the last
url that was captured exactly
because we care about the value and we
also care about the count
of how many times that was invoked yes
but there is a better way
what if we accumulate all of the
requestedURLs
in an array then we can test the value
and the count at the same time because
when we compare two arrays
for equality we assert order equality
and count at the same time that's a huge
enhancement in my opinion
and because it's a new test we don't
have to break previous ones right we can
create a new property
requestedURLs an array of URLs and we
keep the old one
and we keep the old one and when we're
done we can
migrate the previous tests to this new
API
so I want to see these tests failing
because we are invoking
more than we should and it does fail
perfect so if you remove the extra call
it should pass now
and it does so we can commit here
guarantee that we can load more than
once
perfect great and now we can migrate the
old tests
yes so we can use requestedURLs now and
here should be
an array with only one url and the url
should be the same that was passed
and the first one instead of assert
nil now we can assert
true that requestedURLs is empty
which means no messages were captured
fantastic
let's see if it passes and it does
great now we can remove
the old property run the test again
oh good let's commit simplify
spy let's have a quick recap
we moved our production code out of the
test target
then we improved our assertions by not
checking just the value that was
captured
but also how many times they were
captured by using arrays
so coming next we should start thinking
about the client response
yeah perfect so thanks for watching and
we'll see you next time
bye y'all