Hello Mike, hey Caio
so in the previous episode we moved our
production code out of the test target
then we improved our assertions by not
checking just the value that was
captured
but also how many times they were
captured by using arrays
right okay so now it's time to start
thinking about the client response
because so far we only send the message
get but we don't expect anything back
so let's start from the error case what
happens
when we get an error on the client side
right so
when the client fails we want to send an
error
so delivers error on client error
right because when the HTTPClient fails
it means we have some kind of
connectivity issue
right exactly so if we have our sut and
client
and we call load right we want an output
basically
and since the callback is asynchronous
we're going to pass a completion block
yes to the FeedLoader okay I like that
and we're going to get
let's say an error and we want to
capture this error
so capturedError equals error
so let's define our capturedError so
what's the type here
let's use the Error for now okay and we
have some compiler warnings so why don't
we start solving these
first first of all load doesn't receive
a completion block
so let's do this
and we expect to send an Error back and
since we don't want to break
the other tests let's just give it a
default closure for now
that's a nice Swift feature okay the
compiler errors are gone let's carry on
do we want this Error to be
just a generic protocol or should we
give it a better definition
right I think we should as we said if
the client fails
we are going to define it as a
connectivity error
so why don't we define our own Error
type it could be even inside the
RemoteFeedLoader yeah it can be a
public enum there okay so public enum
Error yeah and I like how this will read
later
it's a RemoteFeedloader.Error type and
it needs to conform to
Error and since they have the same names
we need to give it the namespace
Swift.Error fantastic and the case
name will be connectivity makes sense
it's a connectivity error yep so this
now should be a RemoteFeedLoader.Error
and we expect this to return Error
so we can assert that the capturedError
was a connectivity error and the
compiler is
notifying us that we are never using the
client in this scope
but we have to we need to tell the
client that it failed
well we can stub the client that's one
way of doing it
okay so we don't have this functionality
but we can implement it something like
client.error
equals let's say an NSError just to test
let's say Test code zero
okay you can now set an error here
optional right so this is the
setup we want in our tests but right now
we don't have any method for the HTTP
Client to tell
the RemoteFeedLoader that an error
occurred so let's run this test
and hopefully we see a failing test
we do how can we send an error from the
client to the RemoteFeedLoader and I
think we can use the closure
again yeah the same technique complete
with an Error
but which kind of Error I don't want to
pass the same Error as the RemoteFeed
Loader because this Error now
is in the domain of the implementation
of the HTTPClient
absolutely this error is an HTTP
kind of error so it should have its own
type there
so what the RemoteFeedLoader is doing
is mapping the client errors
to a domain error in this case
connectivity
right an error that comes from the HTTP
domain as we can see here when there's
no connectivity
we deliver an error that's the domain
error no connectivity
so let's make this escaping and this
should be escaping as well
and we now need to pass the closure so
here we get the client
error but we want to complete with our
own domain Error yeah connectivity
but now our spy needs to implement the new
method
and now we can say if we have an error
right
we invoke completion with the error
in the spy that should do it
okay it's passing okay getting there
so let's commit delivers connectivity
error on client error
fantastic I think we can do some cleanup
here
we don't need to define a name for the
error in the closure we can just use the
dollar sign
0 and another improvement we can do is
instead of using
the optional and capturing it we can do
the same technique we did with the
requestedURLs and use an array
of errors to guarantee that we only
received one error
so now we just append the received error
and at the end we can compare
that the capturedErrors is just one error
and it's a connectivity
error yeah that looks good all right
commit
yeah guarantee we
only receive one error
fantastic so we made a choice here
to stub the client even though our
client
is a spy right so we are mixing concepts
now
stubbing and capturing values yes
and from the test point of view here we
stub before we call load but that
doesn't reflect the asynchronous nature
of this behavior exactly so I would
prefer to keep our spy
a spy just capturing data instead of
stubbing it
with some behavior and we can do so by
capturing the completion block and it's
up
to us in the test scope to invoke that
completion block, okay how to do so
so we can do so by creating our client
error and invoking the completion block
that we will capture so for example we
have a completions
array and we want the first one and we
can invoke it with the client
Error yes so let's go to our spy
instead of an error we can add our
completions
array that will hold
all the completion blocks passed
so we append the completion received and we
don't need the error anymore
so we are not stubbing yeah we don't
have behavior we just accumulate
all the properties we received let's run
the test
and it passes and we should definitely
mention here how
the code order changed from the arrange
to the act section previously the
client.error stub
was part of the arrange scope now
the client.completions belongs to
the act part
that's the action and it makes sense
when the client
completes with an error then we want the
load
to complete with an error as well so I
believe this test tells the truth
because the completion happens after you
invoke load
exactly so I'm happy with that but now I
think this is not as readable
it doesn't look as neat as it was before
because we need to get a value from an
array
okay but we can solve it yeah let's
commit and try to solve that
replace stubbing by capturing
values instead let's see if we can
improve this
spy what if we have a method
called complete with and we pass
our client over here yeah that's exactly
what we want we want our spy to
complete with an error so in
the implementation
we pass an error and here we call
completions
at index and invoke with the error
and we can even make the subscript there
dynamic
okay we can have an index and give it a
default value exactly default it to zero
okay so we get the completion block at
the past index
and we invoke it with the error let's
see how it looks now
it's passing and I think it looks
cleaner now absolutely
so let's commit so improve
readability with helper
method, I think we can even go one step
further
and perhaps combine the captured values
since we are capturing the whole message
instead of having two different arrays
we can capture it in a single array of
tuples
for example we can have a messages array
there is a combination of the captured
URL
and the completion block yeah it's the
signature
of the get method basically
now in the get method we can say
message.append
url and the completion block and if in
the future we add more parameters to
this method
we append it to the tuple as well right
so there is no need for completions now
we can just use the messages array at
index
.completion the completion for that
message
and then complete with error exactly and
we can do the same for the requestedURLs
so we can make the requestedURLs a
computed property
yes and we return
messages.map and we get only the
URLs
inside the messages and we don't need to
capture
the URLs anymore and we didn't break
the clients and that's how I implement
spies normally
I like to just capture values I find
this very
nice let's commit so
combine spy captured params
into a single type and it's a tuple
yeah okay looking clean
okay another addition with this test
was the completion block in the load
method that was not used before
in other tests and now to break the
tests we added
a default value to the parameter but
this is not actually the behavior we
want in production we want someone to
always pass
a completion block so now we can move
this default parameter
to the test scope okay
so this enables us to continue with the
load function in the production side
without having to think about this
exactly I think it's a good time to do
it yeah
let's commit it yeah remove default
value for completion block moved it
to the test yep great
so what is the next behavior let's have
a look at the requirements
connectivity is done now invalid data
so what is invalid data so if we take a
look at the
response we see that we are expecting a
HTTP response status code from the
server
okay we can start there if it's not a
200 response
it's an error
so I think I'm gonna copy the delivers
error test
because this is also an error test and
we change it okay
yes so delivers error on
non 200 HTTP
response okay so instead of sending a
client ever now
we are going to complete with a status
code
yes and let's say 400 anything that is
not 200
but it's not a connectivity error anymore
is it, no
there will be invalid data
okay so let's add our case invalid
data and we need to implement
the complete with status code right so
our spy now is going to help us complete
with status code
it's an integer and let's also pass an
index
as before for the messages so how can we
create a response
with a status code, Foundation offers the
HTTPURLResponse type
perfect yeah this is the standard type
we can use
so the URL we can grab that from the
requestedURLs okay
requestedURLs at index perfect status
code
is the code passed to this method and
HTTP version
I don't care about this and I also don't
care about the headers
nice let's format that
and then we invoke as before our
messages
at index completion and we need to
complete
with an HTTPURLResponse now right hmm
but we cannot do this yes yet we need to
change some
stuff because so far the client
completes with just an Error
so one way of doing it is to append
another
value after the Error and if I have a
response
I don't have an Error right for example
the Error is nil
yeah but I have a response and in the
error case here I have an error but I
don't have a response
that is correct okay so we are starting
to add some nullables here we might have
to revisit this in the future
but apparently that's the simplest thing
to do right now so let's add a URL
Response
also optional yeah and let's solve the
compiler errors now
we now get error end response
okay this is fixed
in the spy we also get an optional Error
and an optional HTTPURLResponse
and the same in the get method let's run
failing test perfect
and it expected invalid data but it got
connectivity
because we are always completing with a
error, so let's add some logic there to
resolve that
I guess it's pretty simple so we can either
check for error or check for response
right so if response is not nil
we complete with invalid data
else we complete with connectivity I
think that should do it
perfect it passes fantastic and
just to show how important it is to
capture all the errors in an array
if I move this connectivity outside the
if statement and I've seen this bug
in many codebases countless times we're
gonna get a failing test
yeah because of the array yes
exactly as you can see we got two errors
I've seen many codebases where we
forget as developers to add the else
and we just complete every single time
exactly
so checking how many times completion
was invoked is important I want it to be
completed
once and only once per request let's run
the tests
and commit
delivers invalid data
error on non 200 HTTP
responses yes and I know what a lot of
people
are thinking right now you have one test
for the 400 case right what about
500 what about 404 yeah
what about 201 what about 199
yeah these are good examples and we can
protect by testing some of these cases
so how much is enough right that's a
good question
when I'm checking integers I like to
check one
less than a value, one more than the
value
in a couple of cases yeah I guess you
can be very thorough
check all the values as well exactly you
can say from
zero to infinity and you invoke these
bazillion times yeah yeah but I think
that's a good set
yeah I think so
so we iterate through all the examples
and we capture the code
and since we are capturing the errors in
an array we want to reset the array
after we are done it's passing
but I think this reset after the test
can be confusing for the readers of the
code
so why instead of resetting it we
execute this
for all the cases and then we want to
complete
the client request at a specific index
and this index can be the index of the
array here
so we can enumerate our sample
and now we get the index and the code so
let's run the test
passes but this is hard to read let's
put this in a constant
and call it samples
let's run the test again fantastic
Add more test assertions
for different HTTP status code
okay anything else we can refactor in
this production code
yes I'm very unhappy with this API with
optional errors
yes, yes, yes, for me the problem is that
we either have an error or an HTTPURL
Response
up to now but we can represent a case
here where both are nil
the error is nil and the HTTPURL
Response is nil well it should never
happen
right if something should never happen
it shouldn't be representable in our
code
exactly we allow a case like this
exactly
because Error has two states nil
or it has a value and HTTPURLResponse
here
since it's optional it has two cases as
well, right, nil or with a value so we can
represent here
four different states why how far
when we can have two exactly so we can
create a new type
let's make it a public enum HTTP
ClientResult it's either success
with the HTTPURLResponse yes
or a failure with the Error that's it
now we have restricted to two branches
we are either going to have a success
with a response or
a failure with an error so now we can
replace the optionals
with our enum type and the code now
gets only a result type instead of using
an if statement we can switch on the
result type
so case success
we complete with invalidData for now
yeah I know it sounds silly but that's
what we need now
and case failure we complete with a
connectivity error
let's change our spy as well so the same
thing in the spy
we should now use our HTTPClientResult
and when we complete now we don't need
to pass nil
we just wrap our response in the right
case
failure for errors and
success for response
fantastic and since the initializer of
HTTPURLResponse returns an optional
as you can see here right let's force
unwrap it because we know that this
hard-coded HTTPURLResponse we are
creating is always valid
so let's run our tests
it passes perfect let's commit so
replace
optional params with
enum with success
and failure cases I think this is much
nicer absolutely and I think we're done
for this episode
let's have a quick recap we've moved on
to checking the behavior of the Remote
FeedLoader that delivers an error
mapping client errors to a domain level
error in this case the connectivity
error and also
when we get a known 200 HTTP response
we also map it to a domain error invalid
data
and finally we showcased a way for
designing
APIs that exclude cases that you
don't want ever to happen in this case
removing the double optional parameters
in favor of an enum so the goal is to
make
invalid paths unrepresentable and in
this case instead of using
two optionals we have an enum with two
cases
so it's either one or the other we
eliminate two invalid states
that was a big win absolutely imagine if
we had
a third optional parameter there then it
would be chaos
yes we would be able to represent eight
possible states
because when we combine optionals the
number of representable states grows
exponentially
and who knows how many of these states
we didn't actually
never want to happen probably most yeah
exactly we also showed how to test
with samples by having a simple array
and the differences between capturing
values in a spy
and stubbing behaviors and in our
current tests
we prefer to capture values to keep our
spy
clean and simple yeah keep it pure
no need to mix those two so coming next
we should start mapping the response
into
FeedItems okay happy path and handling
mapping errors as well the sad path
right
so thanks for watching and we'll see you
next time bye y'all