Hello Mike, hey Caio
so in the previous episode we finished
handling all the HTTPClient errors
now it's time to start mapping the JSON
response
into feed items right so
the feed items are the models that the
rest of the system
are going to use and we want the API
module
to convert the data that come from the
HTTPClient to this model
so this is our model FeedItem
and here we have the contract with the
backend on how this model is
represented
in JSON form very nice so again it's a
200 response
we are already checking that and then we
have an object
with a keypath items which contains an
array of objects
and location and description is optional
so we might not have one
and when there is no description or
location they are just not present
in the JSON representation yes
okay let's start with a test as always
let's start with the unhappy path right
okay so you're talking about the 200
response
but invalid JSON yes so it delivers an
error
yes on 200 HTTP response
but with invalid JSON right
can happen yeah we should be ready for
it regardless if it's going to happen or
not
so as before we have our sut and our
client
I think we can even copy the setup here
so we are capturing the errors right we
are completing with a 200
status code but now we need to pass some
data
right and it's invalid JSON yeah that's
the setup
and we want to make sure that we
received an invalidData
error yes so we need to create this
invalid JSON
so invalidJSON is equal to well it can be
any
invalid JSON data representation exactly
we can create some
data here with whatever like invalid
JSON
yeah okay
okay now our client spy doesn't know how
to handle this data yet
right so let's implement that right here
we can receive data now but this is
going to break the other tests
right but we can just give it a default
value
for now yep and what should we do with
this data
right this data should come in the
success branch
when we get the response we also expect
to get data
so we can append it in the enum
success tuple okay but this is going
to break our production code but that's
good
yep that's what we want so we need to
add something
else in this result type yes
it's Data and HTTPURLResponse
can we build now okay we can build and
the test is passing
right but I would also want to see a
failing test
right so we can quickly just comment out
this line of code
there you go so we can see a failing
test we are covering this
scenario let's put it back
it's passing let's commit delivers
invalid data error on 200 HTTP
response with invalid JSON yeah looks
good
okay so it seems to me there is a lot of
duplication in these
tests that are handling the error cases
yes they are all repeating this dance of
capturing errors and asserting
the correct value so what changes here
only the action
that generates the error and the error
so if we can expect a certain
error case and we can give it the action
I think we can save some lines there and
even make it
more readable okay so let's try to
create a helper then let me copy
the current setup let's create here
a helper function and as you say it's
something like expect
right the sut RemoteFeedLoader
to complete right we're completing with
an error
in these tests okay so complete with
error
and it's a RemoteFeedLoader.Error
and when some kind of action occurs so
yeah let's pass an action closure yeah
okay let's see is everything there so
this is the action part
right the client is not needed this is
going to go in the closure
so we can call there the action
yes perfect and the captured error
is the one we passed exactly that's it
yeah
okay let's see if we can refactor this
test then
so expect sut to complete with error
invalidData when yeah
when we complete with a 200 status code
and invalid JSON
perfect okay looks good to me
let's see if we can build yeah and the
test is passing as well
fantastic but I would like to see a
failing test what happens when this
fails
right okay we have a failing test
but I don't like that the error message
is in the wrong place I would like to
see the message
in this line right
so we can pass the line and file
parameters
to the assert equal function and we
can just add it here
with the default values yeah let's add
the file and line parameters there
file, file, line, line
great let's see if the failure now goes
to the right place
and it does so now when it fails it
fails
in the exact line where we should look
for the error
yeah it's great okay let's put it back
let's see if it passes
still yeah let's try to refactor the
other test as well
okay so here we can use the same
helper function and the action is to
complete with a status code
right and we expect invalidData as the
error
let's run the tests fantastic
now this one we expect connectivity error
when we complete with a client
error let's run the tests it's also
passing
beautiful let's commit remove
duplicate test code by creating
reusable expect helper method
that's it okay so now the happy path
but since this is a collection of items
let's start with the empty case
so delivers no items on 200
HTTP response with an
empty list right or empty
JSON list so the setup
is very similar sut and client
but now we want to capture right
these are the feed items here but our
function can only
complete with Error right at this point
so we are facing the same dilemma we had
before
are we going to have two optional types
there Error
and FeedItems array or I think we can
go with the result type here yes as we
said previously
when we combine optionals we just
increase exponentially
the number of paths and most of them are
just invalid paths
so let's just use enums yep so since
we're going to change the signature of
this method
let's comment out right what are we
doing here and
let's refactor the previous tests to
receive a result type
so this is a preparation step for what
comes next
I like that and since we have this
expect method we only have to change it
in one place
yes that was a good refactoring
absolutely so instead of
capturedErrors we are going to receive
some kind of captured
results yes
so what is the result type in this
scenario
right we have the success case which
bears
an array of FeedItems and then failure
with an error okay which error
well we have the Error type above right
okay so this Error
yeah perfect the RemoteFeedLoader
Error type
okay but if this is a public enum
exposed to the tests
right the FeedItem also needs to be
public yes and I think it's time to do
it
yep so let's make this a public
struct okay
so now when we compare the error we need
to
wrap it in a failure result
yes but we are using insert equal
which means the result type needs to be
Equatable yes
should we make the result type Equatable
yeah I think so
it's data as we say
right it facilitates our testing here so
I would like that okay and it's also the
easiest step
so we can rethink this in the future yep
so let's make this Equatable
but this cannot be Equatable because
field item is not Equatable so we're
gonna have to
also make the FeedItem Equatable I'm
fine with that
it's data I think it's a good argument
you know
why wouldn't it be Equatable why
wouldn't you be able to
compare FeedItems so now our
load method can complete with a result
and we need to wrap
our errors into the failure case yeah
that's it
now it's building and the test is
passing okay
so we may have to rethink this Equatable
in the result type and the FeedItem but
I'm happy to carry on absolutely I agree
let's commit
okay but let's not commit the commented
out test
exactly we don't need this yet
so add RemoteFeedLoader
result type with success
and failure cases okay now I think we
can carry on
with our test so we're also going to
capture
results so let me copy this here
for the action we are going to perform
we want to complete
with 200 status code
and an empty list
JSON yeah so what is an empty
list JSON we can create a string
containing the items key with an empty
array
representing the JSON so this needs to
be a valid JSON
right so it's an object with the key
items and an empty array inside
which matches our payload contract
exactly right so now we expect a success
here
a success with an empty array okay so
we're going to assert
equals that the capturedResults
is equal to an array with only one
completion
and it's a success with an empty array
of FeedItems
right hopefully that will fail yeah
and it does okay now we can start adding
some logic
okay so what is the minimum we can do to
make this pass
so what we need to get our data here
and our response
and to make this pass we just need to
make sure that we can
convert this JSON right it's just
checking if it's a valid JSON
yeah basically so we can use an if let
JSON
equals JSONSerialization.jsonObject
with data right
then we complete with success and let's
pass an empty array of FeedItems that's
all we need else we complete
with the failure invalidData what is wrong
here
this method throws so we need to use try
since we are using response or the JSON
we can just use the
underscore let's see
it's passing let's commit
so delivers empty items array
on 200 HTTP response
with JSON empty list
and I think we can even use the expect
method here
in this test right so this setup is very
similar to the error case
yes okay so we can do some refactoring
instead of say complete with error
we complete with a result yes
and we don't need to wrap this anymore
we just make sure we are completing with
a result
yeah the result is Equatable so we can
do that
but this is going to break our current
tests let's fix one by one we just need
to wrap it
in the failure case the same here
and here
okay it's still passing so now we can
use the same
helper method beautiful in here
expect sut to complete
with success with an empty
array when
we complete with an empty JSON list yep
let's run perfect
yeah I think it reads very nicely by the
way I like it
let's commit refactor helper
to receive result instead of
error types yeah to enable
reusability for different
potential results that's it
fantastic
so the next test is the real deal
where we deliver the FeedItems items
yep on 200 HTTP
response right when we have valid JSON
items
so now it's not empty it's not invalid
JSON
no it's not an invalid HTTP response
this is
the happy path like we have the items we
have everything we need
we just need to map it yes so
setup is the same yep
but now we need to create some items
that we can equate
let's say item one
but if I'm not mistaken we can't create
FeedItems
yes we don't have access to the
initializer
yep we need to address that
it's because its initializer is internal
by default
and our module doesn't have access to
internal types
right so we can either import this
module as testable
or we create a public initializer for
the struct
right but if we look at the architecture
other modules
will implement these interfaces and use
those
FeedItem models which means they might
create it
so if other modules are going to create
FeedItems
we need to have a public initializer
so it's time and we're going to have to
do this manually yep
so description it's an optional String
location it's an optional String
imageURL is a non-optional
URL now we can set the properties
okay okay now we should have access to
the initializer
yeah and we do fantastic so let's just
create any UUID they are always unique
every time we create it
it's a different one let's have this
first item with
no description okay and no location
but it should have an imageURL so let's
create a URL here
a-url.com
we also need its JSON representation
okay which is
a dictionary with the first key as
id and it should have the item1
.id but as a String right
so we can transform this UUID into a
String
yeah but we don't have access to the id
property right let's make this public
and actually let's make all of them
public because we're going to need all
of them
this FeedItem does not have a
description
and in our JSON contract when you don't
have a description
it's not added to the JSON payload yeah
so we're not going to add a description
or location but it needs a image
URL and the key path is just image
so item1.imageURL
.absoluteString yeah I think that's
what it is
yeah and I guess this is item1
JSON it is
and let's create another one item2
yeah is a FeedItem with another UUID
but this one is going to have a
description a description and
a location and another URL
fantastic
and the item2JSON is also a dictionary
with id item2.id
.uuidString this one has a description
and the key path is description
it has a location item2.location
and it has an image as well okay
so that's a lot of setup yeah I don't
think we're done
so those are the items we are mapping
right we're gonna have our item
one and two so we can compare it and
also its
JSON representation yes so we need to
wrap these into the items
keypath to match our
payload contract exactly that's the root
node right so let's create our
itemsJSON which is
a dictionary with the keypath items and
it's an array
with item1JSON and
item2JSON yeah that's it
and now we can use our expectation
expect sut
to complete with success
with our item1 and item2
right when
the client completes with 200 and our
JSON data
yes so we need to create our JSON data
and I think we can use JSON
Serialization here right data with JSON
object
items JSON yeah and we need to try that
yes because it throws and since we know
this is a valid JSON
we can force try it I think that's the
test
yeah and it's failing fantastic so now
it's time for us to
deserialize these items yeah decision
time
and we can use Decodable yes
the FeedItem can be extended
to conform to Decodable and we can then
decode the JSON and return the Feed
Items
in the FeedLoader since this array is
inside
the item's keypath we need to create this
root node
first of all and we can make it private
so it should have an array of items
and it should be Decodable
so we can now use our JSONDecoder
to decode our root
element from the received data
and if we have a root node we can
complete with a success
with the items inside the root node but
you get the
Decodable implementation for free so the
compiler can
implement it for us the FeedItem also
needs to implement Decodable
yes and since our keys do not match
the JSON keys we will have to
implement the CodingKeys
enum for the imageURL
okay because in our FeedItem model we
call it image
URL yes JSON it's just image so they
don't match
okay so we need to provide some mapping
instructions
right and with Decodable we do it with
our CodingKeys
so id is fine it matches
description also matches location
matches
but the imageURL does not match so we
need to tell it
what is the key we want to map yes and
its image
okay let's run the test now
okay passes now fantastic all right
let's commit
and clean up the mess so delivers
items array on 200
HTTP response with JSON
items so we have some cleanup to do here
but something that also bothers me is
this key
image there is an API detail
leaking in this FeedItem model
that should be agnostic about the API
module
right so the FeedItem belongs in the
FeedLoader module as we have in our
diagram
and it shouldn't know any sort of
implementations from other modules
like the API for example there are no
arrows
coming from the FeedLoader pointing
to the RemoteFeedLoader or the API
module
which means we don't want the Feed
Loader module here
the Feature module to depend on
implementation details
of the API for example we might create
FeedItems from
the LocalFeedLoader representation and
you might need to use Decodable as well
right but if something changes in the
API for example
they rename these to image-url at some
point
we might break other modules yeah if we
keep the knowledge
of this keypath in the shared module
and we don't want to break the UI or
Database because of API changes
right and then the question will be I
guess are we going to do that for just a
simple string there
just this image string absolutely
okay so let's fix the test first and
we'll get there
so I think that's a lot of setup for one
test and we can definitely simplify by
providing some sort of a factory method
for the FeedItems
okay let's start here then so factory
method
makeItem yeah I like that
and it needs a UUID, a description
right which I guess it can default to
nil a location
same and image
URL and this is going to return our
FeedItem yeah okay so we can just
create our item yeah with those
given values
and return it okay but it's not gonna
save a lot of
lines of code right what if this method
also created
the JSON right so we can return our
model
and a JSON representation which is a
dictionary
string any yeah I like that because
the JSON is a mirror of the actual
native
model and we get all the values here so
we can do that
so it needs the id it needs the
description
the location and the image
URL yeah that's it now we return the
item
and the JSON very nice
okay but since the description and the
location
are optional I see yes the type
is not matching here right we can reduce
it into a new dictionary and remove
the new values yeah so we can reduce
into a new
dictionary with the right type String
Any
and we can get our accumulated new
dictionary
and the element if
there is a value in the element tuple
we add it to the accumulated dictionary
otherwise we don't so all we're doing
here is removing the new values
and in Swift 5 there's a new compact
Map that does exactly that
but we don't have this yet that's fine
maybe the compiler will warn us in the
migration
so now we can use our new helper method
yeah make item and we don't need the
item JSON anymore
or the description and location in this
case and the item
to have all of them but we don't need
the dictionary very nice
I think we can also put this into one
line great
but now it's item1.json
and item2.json and this is item1
.model
and item2.model you can even
put this into a variable
as well okay that's much shorter
I like that what do you think yeah
absolutely
I think it's much cleaner anything else
we can do
we can get rid of the JSON
Serialization there I think it's an
implementation detail for the test
maybe we can have a function that hides
how
we serialize JSON, okay something like
makeItemsJSON
yes yes that will receive an
array of right
items JSON yeah and return
data so now we can move
the items JSON and the serialization
in here so we just replace this with the
items array
yeah can we return yeah that's it
even use a short name yeah here I like
it okay
one line beautiful so we can now say
make items JSON we don't need this
anymore let's see if it still passes
fantastic I like this test it's
short again and very descriptive very
descriptive yes
I was about to say that okay let's
commit this
so create factory methods to simplify
test setup all right anything we can
refactor
more before we deal with the Decodable
FeedItem
not sure one thing is bothering me is
that we're not using the response ever
so right but why is that
yeah and basically we don't we're not
using the status code there
that's true yeah but we have a test for
this yeah
so this means that if we complete with a
valid JSON
but with the wrong status code we will
map it so we're just ignoring the status
code and that's not what we want
so let's have a look at our setup
okay we give a default data here and
that's the problem
right so let me remove this and see
where it breaks
yeah yeah we should be more explicit
with
which kind of data we are passing when
we have a wrong status code
right so we need to pass some data now I
guess we can pass valid JSON here
and this will force us basically to
check that hey we need this 200 status
code there
it doesn't matter if we have just
valid JSON we need both
okay so we can use the makeItemsJSON
that creates a valid JSON
yeah just with no items very simple it's
valid but
there's nothing to map there I like that
I think that should do it
yes oh and it's failing fantastic
beautiful so let me get the response now
and let's check the
response status code is 200
and we can map it alright
now I'm happy with this let's commit
so use explicit JSON data
for non 200 HTTP
response tests just to make sure we are
doing the right thing here
all right now it's time for us to deal
with this Decodable thing
yes as we said this image
keypath this string leaks an
implementation detail of the API
into the FeedItem model and this is API
specific
if this changes in the API we might
break other modules that have nothing to
do with the API
so I don't think this knowledge of the
keypath
should be in the module the problem is
that if you implement Decodable into
your types
you can only implement it once right so
you mean
you can't have an extension of Decodable
let's say in one framework
and another extension of Decodable in
another framework
not for the same type yes and that's a
problem so
the advice here is to create a separate
model that represents the API FeedItem
right and keep that knowledge in the API
domain and I think we can do this
without breaking our tests
because at the end of the day we want
this module to generate FeedItems
but internally we can use a transitional
representation of it absolutely
absolutely from the API
FeedItem representation into FeedItems
so I would like to
get rid of this Decodable implementation
here
and we can do so by creating our own
private type here
just like we did with the root element
right
but now this one has the right name that
matches
the API JSON representation right
so this Item is the internal
representation of a FeedItem
but for the API module and this is going
to be Decodable now right
exactly I like that and the Root will
generate
an array of items and we need a way to
map
our Item into a FeedItem and we can use
a
computed var to do so right so here we
can return our
FeedItem with the same id description
location and imageURL right
and all we need to do here is to map our
items
into FeedItems right
that's it let's run the tests boom
still works fantastic so look at that we
have our
own items that represents the API Feed
Item in this context
so the FeedItem has no knowledge of the
API
again even with the keypaths because you
can say it's just a string
but no it's an implementation detail
that is leaking into a more abstract
higher level module yes this FeedItem
has an imageURL property which as we
saw
before if we were to implement Decodable
then we would have these CodingKeys and
we would have to
give mapping instructions to the
compiler to map the image
JSON property to imageURL but now
with the Item struct the internal
representation
of a FeedItem from the API we don't
have to do that
and as you can see we didn't break the
test right that was a easy
change to make and we keep our modules
abstract
exactly and this shows you how the tests
they don't contain
any internal implementation details and
it's basically input output
and they just check the behavior I really like
that let's commit
move Decodable logic to a new private
Item
struct to decouple the Feed
Feature module from API
implementation details look at that
that is fantastic
but to be fair I don't like this
implementation anymore there's too many
things going on
in this RemoteFeedLoader so why don't
we
refactor this a little bit by creating
maybe a new type
we can extract some stuff lighten up the
FeedLoader
so we can create a private class for now
let's say
a FeedItemsMapper
and we can have a it can be a static
function we don't need an instance of
this
no, a map function the
receives Data and
response yes HTTPURLResponse
and it can throw if you cannot map it
and it returns
an array of FeedItem right so we want
to assert that
the response's status code is going to be
a 200 so we can use a guard statement
yeah
yeah typically we use the guard
statement there
and if it's not 200 well we we throw
invalid data
okay so RemoteFeedLoader.Error.invalidData
yep else we
can use this logic here yes exactly copy
and paste
we decode our Root item but we want to
return
well the mapped items yes the mapped
items
okay so now we can use the FeedItems
Mapper
instead yeah
and we pass data and response we
complete
with the items if succeeded
perfect you can even use the do
catch syntax
if you want
so there you go if you prefer do catch
or if let
it doesn't matter much and we can even
hide
those representations privately inside
our class so no one has access to it
you can even add those structs
inside a method signature it also works
right
but I prefer to keep them into the class
scope
because of the namespacing yeah it's
just a preference
there's a lot of dots in this syntax as
well if you want you can create a root
element and map it we are free to change
this implementation because
in this episode we followed a classicist
approach to test-driven development
where we are not mocking
anything for mapping items all we are
doing is testing through the public
interface that if I pass this data
I get an error or I get a mapped array
of items
so we are free to change the
implementation without breaking the
tests
which is a big win but now we also
testing things in integration so when it
fails it might
be harder to find out where the issue is
precisely
yes but for starting out
I think this is a truthful approach
you know for certain input we get some
certain output
this is a very good point that you make
with integration sure
perhaps we're gonna have to revisit this
solution
but until then I'm happy to go with this
so let's commit yes so
we moved mapping
logic to a new type Feed
ItemsMapper yeah that's it
so a bunch of important lessons in this
episode yep first of all
being careful with the Decodable design
because it can
couple modules this is a true test of
discipline here
because it's so easy to overlook this
and just say you know what like this is
gonna be Decodable it doesn't matter
I'm gonna have this CodingKeys there
you know because for now
it will facilitate you to do whatever
your task is gonna be
but it has implications and
as I said you need to be disciplined to
understand these implications and to
resist
by finding a more modular solution to
your problem
also the classicist approach where we
kept adding tests and refactoring
mercilessly and the tests are still
passing everything is fine
I think there's a big win but this
integration like
tests might bite us in the future so we
need to keep an eye on them
agreed for now I'm happy with it we saw
some great refactorings as well
in my opinion and the tests are very
readable
exactly for example expect sut to
complete with a failure
invalid data when we complete with 200
status but
invalid JSON I think that's very nice
yeah so I think another refactoring we can do
here is to also use the
makeItemsJSON with empty dictionary
here so we
remove this data implementation detail
from our test setup
which can make it easier to read
let's commit replace hard
coded JSON with helper method
also the code here is pretty clean I
think we should start moving
some types to their own files but we can
do this in the next episode
yeah I think we should start the next
episode with a little cleanup
some people don't like those hard-coded
values in here
right so we could create some kind of
DSL here like okay 200
right so it's not a magic number
anymore it has some sort of context
exactly
so replace magic number
with variable given extra context
yeah and we're free to change this
implementation without breaking the test
which is very nice so next episode we
should start moving those types around
to clean up those files yeah
we'll see you next time bye y'all, see ya