Hello Mike, hey Caio, so in the previous
episode we promised to start some tidy
up
in the code so it's time yep let's
organize the project
first thing we mentioned is to move
those types into separate files
right so we have the HTTPClient and the
HTTPClientResult so I think
both of these can go to a separate file
exactly since they are related
they're both HTTPClient types let's
keep them together for now
yep let's see if we can still build yeah
perfect and the test is passing let's
commit
move HTTPClient to its own file
that's it what else can we fix here
I think the FeedItemsMapper is a good
candidate
okay it's a private type but our code
could be tidier
if we move it to a separate file right
and
this will become an internal type since
we move it to a new file
and I think it makes sense to be
internal because this Feed
API folder we have it's meant to live in
its own
framework in its own module and the Feed
ItemsMapper
would be internal to this module it will
not be accessible by
any other module so I think that makes
sense for now and we don't have to add
internal here because that's the default
scope right but I think it's nice
definitely I like it
we can also make this class final
exactly this is not meant to
be subclassed so I like the final
attribute as well
and since we're adding the scope
everywhere
should this be internal or private yeah
I think the static var can be private
but the map function is used by the
Loader so it needs to be internal
as well yes but no other module has
access to it perfect
okay test is passing let's commit
move FeedItemsMapper to its own file
let's have a look at the RemoteFeed
Loader I think it's much better now
yeah much shorter only 40 lines of code
in this file but this method looks a bit
messy
right there's a bunch of things going on
here maybe we can extract
some logic into a helper function yeah I
think it makes sense
we can extract the success there with
the mapping
in its own function
so we can move the data and the response
and it should return
Result then we can move this logic
in here instead of completing we just
return
the result
then we just need to complete
by mapping the data from the received
response right let's see if it passes
it is passing however
now we are capturing self in this block
yes
is this what we want probably not we
might have a retained cycle here for
example
depending on how this client is created
right
exactly but all the tests are passing
and that's problematic
yes because we are not covering memory
leaks
so I think we should add some kind of
safeties in our tests to check this
yes exactly let's do it so in every test
here we need to check
for memory leaks because different
actions can generate the memory leak
right so we can either add assertions in
every test
or we can find a place where we can edit
and it's going to cover
all scenarios like the makeSUT
helper yes every test use the makeSUT
function
and yeah I think that's a good place to
edit
so we need to run this assertion after
the test
finished right and we need to make sure
that the sut
was deallocated from memory and one way
we can run
those assertions after a test is passed
is to use the
tearDown method but there's an extra
facility that the exit test case
class give us which is to add a tearDown
block
which is run after each test right so
when every test finishes running then
the tearDown block
is invoked yes yeah that should do it so
what we need to do is to assert
nil sut right we need to make sure
that the instance of the system under
test
is gonna be nil after each test runs
yes and let's set a nice message here so
instance
should have been deallocated potential
memory leak right I like that but now we
are capturing
sut strongly inside this block so this
would never
be nil yeah exactly so we can just
capture it
as weak yep and I expect to see a
failing test now because we introduced
that
strong reference to self inside the
block yeah a bunch of failing tests
actually
yes there there you go so looks like all
the tests are failing that's great
wow that's great but I would like to see
this message in the right
line where it failed so we can use the
same trick
we used in the previous episode and we
can pass the file
and the line to the assertion
okay now we can see the failures
exactly where it happened very nice
but we need to solve it and I think for
now we can just
undo our change here let's run the test
yes it's passing
or should we check for the client as
well yeah I think so
okay so we can either add another weak
reference here to the client
or we can just create a helper function
something like
track for memory leaks
and we can pass the instance and it
needs to be
AnyObject let me pass the file and line
as well
so we can move this logic to this helper
function
and now we weakify the instance
and now we can run for sut and for the
client
as well yeah looks good hopefully it's
going to pass
fantastic let's commit but I don't want
to commit
the production code yet
so add memory leak detection
great now back to the production code
you can put it back but actually we
could make this function static
right so we don't need to have an
instance
to run this code that wouldn't require self
and we won't have to
weakify self exactly
fantastic which even makes me think if
this function should be a static
function
in the FeedItemsMapper right since
it's a mapping function and we already
have a designated place for all the Feed
Items mapping
we perhaps could move it there let's
give it a try
let's make it internal now so the logic
is still the same
we need to check for this status code
so here I think we can return invalid
data yeah
a failure with invalid data oh
and it doesn't know what is the Result
because it needs the namespace yep
RemoteFeedLoader.Result great and I
think we can move this logic
to the do catch block
and we don't need this function anymore
let's see
yeah it's passing but we have this
duplicated failure
we can simplify it using a guard let
let's see
so the response needs to be 200 and we
need to be able
to map the JSON otherwise it's invalid
data
so now we don't need a catch block we
don't need to do block and we don't need
the root
that should do it fantastic and I think
we can even move this mapping logic
to a computed var like we did with the
item right so we can have some kind of
feed which is an array of FeedItems and
we can just move this mapping logic here
so return items.map
so here is just root.feed
beautiful very nice
anything else I don't see anything else
so let's commit move all
mapping logic to the FeedItems
<apper that's it that's much nicer
look at this yeah very clean
and I like the static function there we
don't have to capture self
inside the block well another way we
could do it is to have a weak
self here and use a guard let
if we had the helper method for example
and here we could use self
and not hold a strong reference to it
right or we could also use the unowned
reference which would be implicitly
unwrapped right
but this guard let is very different
than using a static method it looks the
same but it's not
there is more to it than just weakifying
self
there's the problem is when we make
something weak and you return
it means that this block would not be
executed if the instance
has been deallocated but if I'm using
the static method as we are here
even if the instance of the RemoteFeed
Loader
has been deallocated this block may still
be invoked
and we might still call the completion
block right because we don't know the
implementation of the client maybe it's
a Singleton
and it lives longer than the Remote
FeedLoader exactly
and this might be a bug because
consumers of this RemoteFeedLoader
may not expect the completion block to
be invoked after
the instance has been deallocated and that
might be a problem
so we need to instruct the RemoteFeed
Loader
to prevent this behavior from happening
yes
and we can improve this behavior with a
test and I think that's a good idea
yeah definitely so let's create our test
here
load and what is the behavior well it
does not
deliver result after the
sut instance has been deallocated
yeah so what we need is to create an sut
and we're going to have to force its
type to be optional so we can
deallocate it by setting it to nil
so what do we need to create a Remote
FeedLoader we need a URL
and we need our client so let's do this
so the client is an HTTPClientSpy
that's easy
and the URL is any URL
fantastic so this is our setup
our given right and we want to assert
that our capturedResults let's say is
empty
after some action yeah so the action is
you set the sut to nil
first of all which means this is going
to be deallocated it won't be in memory
anymore
and we want our client to complete with
anything right
after the sut has gone away we want the
client to do something
yes it could be an error it could be a
response
with a valid JSON invalid JSON doesn't
matter you should not complete with
errors and you should not complete
with success it should not complete at
all
yeah so we need to capture the results
and I think we can copy these from our
previous setups yeah right here
fantastic
so that's the setup we capture all the
results where we expect
to not have received a result
boom failing test we just proved that
we are always completing regardless if
the instance
has been deallocated or not and I don't
like this behavior
so we can fix it and it's a very easy
fix
for example we can just get a weak
reference to self and check that
self is not nil else you just return
okay problem solved and this is a very
common bug I see in codebases
instances are deallocated right but
unexpected behaviors
start happening for example some UIView
Controller has been deallocated but some
strong reference to a
label or a collection view was inside a
block to get executed
after the fact and it's so hard to debug
this
yeah because I think we are conditioned
to think about the class that we're
building
and we don't think about the
collaborators how they might behave
so it's easy to miss this for sure
and now we left a trail we left a test
that
it's some kind of documentation telling
the next developer that thinks about
removing that line of code to remember
that
it is there for a reason yeah that's my
favorite part of all
that as you said this is
self-documenting right there it says
we are checking we are thinking about
this behavior I really like that
exactly and if we wanted it to complete
after the instance has been deallocated we
could add
the inverse test by checking that even
though the instance was deallocated
we got a result back so in this case we
don't want it to happen
but if you want it to happen you can
also add a test for it I think these are
also the dangers when
you're dealing with asynchronous code
it's the essence
and the element of time basically that
you don't know what's going to happen
you don't control that
so you need to think about all these
edge cases
and you need to prevent them I've dealt
with this bug so many times
that I learned my lesson yep exactly so
let's commit
yep guarantee we do
not deliver a result
or invoke the completion
closure after the Remote
FeedLoader instance has been deallocated
beautiful one last thing I see is the
fact that the
RemoteFeedLoaderTests is alone in the
EssentialFeedTests folder
I think we can encapsulate it in a Feed
API
folder so we can mirror the production
side
okay Feed API good catch
let's run the test okay
let's commit move test file to a group
to denote its module right
and it's the Feed API and this makes me
think also
the difference in file count if you see
the production side
we have three files in the Feed API but
only one file
in the test side in the Feed API folder
yeah and that's
fairly common actually it's never one to
one
but if we check the coverage I'm pretty
sure it's close to 100%
or 100% yep because you don't need to
test things like one by one
for example we are testing the Feed
ItemsMapper in integration
as we mentioned in the previous episode
so I'm pretty happy
with the results so far not only that we
should say that
we started with a one to one ratio right
we had just the RemoteFeedLoader file
and the RemoteFeedLoaderTests file but
as we followed the process
and we started refactoring we then
ended up with these three files there
which I think is a good practice
this is what we needed when we started
out this is what we need right now
so the project always changes and it
changes to facilitate our needs right
we want it to change we want it to be
flexible yep
beautiful okay let's have a look at the
updated diagram
we are done now with the RemoteFeed
Loader
we just need now to implement the
interfaces here
right and since now we have more than
one type in this component
I think we can even call it Feed API from
now on yes
exactly and the FeedLoader can be the
Feed Feature
module yep what do you think
this is a modular view yes
we can have a more granular view later
on by adding all the types
absolutely all right so next episode we
are going to implement the Feed
Loader protocol awesome all right see
you next time
bye y'all