Hello Mike, hey Caio so in the previous
episode we finished the
RemoteFeedLoader implementation and
now it's time to make it conform
to the FeedLoader protocol in the Feed
Feature module
yep so the FeedLoader protocol has a
function
load with completion and the LoadFeed
Result
type right and our implementation is
very similar but we use the
Result type here and our own domain
specific Error type right but the
FeedLoader Error type is just the
Swift Error protocol this might cause
some trouble
well we could move the FeedLoader Error
type to the Feed
Feature module exposing this API
implementation detail in the shared
Feature module
and I don't like that no since the Feed
Feature
is agnostic module doesn't know if the
error is going to be
connectivity, invalid data meaning coming
from an API
or local from a database or future
implementations as well
right so we don't want any kind of
knowledge of the Feed Feature
for the provenance of the errors not yet
maybe in the future we're going to
notice that there's some similarities
and we can create a domain
specific error for the Feed Feature
module right but I'm not feeling
confident
still to do it yup so what would take us
to make this use the LoadFeedResult
let's see first of all this is a public
method
so we need to make it public
and we call this success and failure
but here is success and error I think I
prefer failure to be fair
yeah I agree okay but now since the
LoadFeedResult exposes the Swift Error
protocol
we need to give it some more type
information here right
so this error is the domain level error
for the RemoteFeedLoader
and now the FeedItemsMapper is using
the RemoteFeedLoader.Result right
I think we can fix that by using a type
alias
then yeah so we can make this Result
type just a typealias
for the LoadFeedResult so the other
components that are using Remote
FeedLoader.Result can still
work exactly it's an abstraction
okay we solved the return issue but now
we also need to add some
type information now yeah some
instructions there
okay looks like we solved all the
problems in the production module
now in the tests file we have a bunch of
issues as well
yeah we need more instructions there for
the errors
and we're using assert equal which will
force our
enum to be Equatable right but the Error
is generic and we don't know if
the passed error conforms to Equatable
right
well one solution is to use generics
here
yeah and have our own generic type
now we can create an extension on the
LoadFeedResult
where the Error is Equatable so if the
Error is Equatable
this can also be Equatable and the
compiler can synthesize the Equatable
implementation for us
which is very nice but now we need to
carry type information here
what kind of Error right well I don't
know I want the errors to be generic
so we can also define our own associated
type in the protocol
yeah and this is starting to get messy
yeah to say the least
especially for an implementation that is
not being used yet
yes so we can define now
our LoadFeedResult with our domain
Error type
we can just use the Result typealias in
the return type
and it's passing now and with these type
alias and the generic
Rrror type I think we can even get rid
of the
extra type information we added yes
you can probably do the same in here
since the types are now
annotated so this is a working solution
but look at this we are only making the
LoadFeedResult Equatable
because of the tests and this is
production code
yeah exactly and we had to add these
associated types
generic types, type constraints and
I think this complicates a lot our
production code absolutely
we have constrained our types and our
code just because
of the test and I don't like that yeah
the production code has no requirement
for it to be Equatable
yep but since it's passing I think we
should commit and rethink this
implementation
exactly I agree this is a working
solution so
I think we should commit and try to find
a better one
by the way have you noticed that you
didn't require any changes in the tests
right so kudos to the Swift type
inference in there yep
so replace RemoteFeedLoader.
Result enum with the pre-defined
LoadFeedResult enum
from the Feed module and this is in
preparation to conform to the
FeedLoader protocol
so that should be enough for us to make
the RemoteFeedLoader conform to the
Loader protocol
and it is perfect let's commit this as
well yeah for sure and
this was our goal right yes we made the
RemoteFeedLoader conform
to the FeedLoader protocol
we achieved the goal for this episode
but we are not happy with the
implementation yeah
or I am not happy with implementation
right no I'm not either
but we follow the same principle
as we've done in test-driven development
so far which
is make it work and then make it pretty
or make it faster
optimize and I think this is the same
case here
we made it work if we were to go back to
our diagram
we can connect the right arrow from the
Feed API
to the Feed Feature this is done exactly
so what we want to do is to remove these
type constraints and we only have this
because of the Equatable requirement
from our tests
so if you can get rid of this Equatable
requirement
we should be able to get rid of the
generic constraints
exactly that's the goal now that's a new
goal so let's see where it breaks
exactly where we expected in the assert
equals
yeah the thing is we are not going to
capture results anymore
and compare the values we're going to
have to unwrap
the result type and compare the values
inside
the result right so there is no capture
results anymore
what we get here is the received
result and we also have an expected
result yep and we need to compare them
so we're going to have to unwrap
the enums yep both of them and we can
use pattern matching here which is a
very nice
Swift feature so we can combine these
two in a switch statement
and use the pattern matching here to
unwrap when
both of them are a success which means
they they match their cases
so we're gonna get in a success case the
receivedItems
and the expectedItems on the right side
and then we can compare them
that's it so this is the success case
yep but we also have
the failure case where we get a received
error and an expected
error we do something similar we can
just compare the two
receivedError expectedError but
maybe we were expecting success but we
got failure or we were expecting failure
and we got
success so we need to have a default
case right which means that cases don't
match
and we should just fail straight away we
always expect a failure there yeah
so expected result and expected
result we got received
result instead you can also add the file
and line so we get a nice
error message in the right place
beautiful but since this is
asynchronous
we need a way to make sure that we got
inside this closure
and also that we only got there once and
we can achieve the same behavior by
using
expectations which is a nice feature on
XCTestCase
wait for load completion is our message
and we are going to fulfill
regardless of the result and we just
need to wait
for the expectation with a timeout
let's run this test okay now it's
passing and we don't need
the Equatable anymore beautiful because
the way we are asserting this is
actually unwrapping it
we have a little bit more code in our
test module
but we simplify our production code so
often
this is a good trade-off at least in
this case I believe it was because it
was
complicating the production code this
feels like a bargain to me
it's basically nothing compared to all
the constraints we added
when we didn't even use them and we keep
the same behavior we are checking that
this was invoked because if we don't
fulfill the expectation we're gonna get
a failure here
right also we are unwrapping and
checking the values
inside the results and if they don't
match we're gonna get also a failure
with a very nice message telling us
exactly
where the problem is so I'm happy with
this and it's a trade-off
maybe in the future we will have all
those associated types
and generic types and then we can
simplify our tests
but only if this is a requirement of the
production code
agreed so let's commit
and we still have to remove those type
constraints but
we have passing tests no warnings let's
commit yep
so remove LoadFeedResult
Equatable conformance from production
since it's a test only
requirement that's it
yeah I think now it's time to get rid of
those generics
let's see if we remove these we can also
remove
the associated type
so we can remove the type annotation
here and we're going to have to be a
little bit more explicit
with our types
which is also a trade-off yeah because
of the
Swift generic Error type we are using in
the Result
enum okay same the tests
let's add some type annotation here to
help the compiler
and we also need to cast this yeah and
we can do it
using the pattern matching feature which
is gonna unwrap them
only if you can cast them otherwise it's
gonna
default to an error because they need to
match, fantastic
okay so that's the trade-off when using
the generic Swift Error
and maybe you need to add a little bit
more type information to help the
compiler
but I think it's paying off so far now
we can rethink this
in the future and maybe roll back we are
free
to do so that's one of the main reasons
we have git
exactly let's commit remove the generic
error type from the
LoadFeedResult to simplify
type constraints that's it
I saw the errors that you added there
these ones yeah
I think we can simplify them a little
bit maybe we can create a helper
function
so instead of .failure we can say
failure
and we can go back to just passing the
enum case
right exactly
so we can have our private factory
method
failure with the error and this returns
Result yeah it's a Result and then we
just
create the Result with that error yeah
let's see if the test passes
yeah I like it I think it's a nice clean
up
all right it reads nicely, expect sut to
complete with a failure
invalid data when something happens yeah
nice one
let's commit simplify type
declarations with a helper
function I think that's it right
yes and I'm pretty happy with the
results
I'm very happy with the result yes the
fact that
we got rid of these constraints yeah it
made me happy
you can also make the FeedLoader
protocol public so it can be implemented
by other modules it just happens that
everything is in the same module at this
moment
yeah that's a good catch there so make
the FeedLoader protocol
public, that's it
the RemoteFeedLoader now conforms to
the FeedLoader and we just need to
implement
an HTTPClient fantastic all right so
thanks for watching
and we'll see you in the next episode
bye y'all