Hello Mike, hey Caio
it's time to test-drive an
implementation of the HTTPClient
right so why don't we have an overview
of what we have so far
okay so I updated the diagram and so far
that's how our Feed API module
architecture looks like
we have implemented the RemoteFeedLoader
that uses the FeedItemsMapper
to map the response and it requests the
data from the HTTPClient
but we have no implementations yet right
so the implementation
of the HTTPClient protocol would be
responsible for communicating with the
network
with the backend exactly beautiful and
I think a natural choice here if you're
not going to use any kind of third-party
framework
is to use URLSessions exactly it is the
highest level API and we're not using
any third-party libraries
so I'm happy to go with the URLSession
for now okay so let's create a URL
SessionHTTPClient
okay and all we have to do is to
implement the method get
from URL with a completion block right
that might return
either a success with the Data and HTTP
URLResponse
or a failure with an Error exactly and
we have a bunch of ways of testing this
or
test-driving this one of them is to just
run
end-to-end tests right meaning we are
actually hitting the network
yes executing the HTTP request going to
the backend
getting the response back and then
asserting that we got the right response
I can see a couple problems there first
of all
we don't have a backend yes yet
and we don't want to be blocked yes
exactly we don't want to be blocked
because we don't have a backend the
other problem
is that they can be flaky they can be
flaky because they are
hitting the network and requests often
fail and what if you don't have
connection when you try to run your
tests
that's another good point well you can
make a point that who doesn't have
internet connection nowadays but
you don't want to be constrained right
and here we're talking about the
component level
which I don't think is the place for
end-to-end tests
right so we do need end-to-end tests but
not at the component level
exactly it would be more beneficial to
have end-to-end tests if it can test
more components in integration
exactly just to be clear end-to-end
tests is a valid solution
but since we have more reliable
solutions I think we should give those
better choices a go I agree okay so let
me create a test file here
URLSessionHTTPClientTests
okay so for the first test well we know
that we're going to request the URL
and we're going to use URLSessions yes
okay and what is the API
it's an instance method called dataTask
with URL so we pass the URL and a
completion handler and then we returns
back
a DataTask that we can resume or start
exactly and once the request is done the
completion handler will be called with
either
Data and URLResponse or Error yes
okay so to start with let's make sure
that we create a data task with the
right
URL yeah so we can have an assertion
like
session.receivedURLs
and it should be just one URL yes
exactly so we need a URL
it can be any URL so we need a session
yes
but the URLSession doesn't have
receivedURLs because that's a
test detail right we're spying so we
need to create
our own URLSessionSpy yes
so URLSessionSpy that is a subclass
of URLSession we can start here we're
going to have the received
URLs array that starts empty
and every time we invoke dataTask with
URL
and the completion block we will capture
the passed URL that's it we've done it so
many
times already we're capturing the URL
exactly but now we need to think about
what to return here because this method
returns a DataTask
yes and we don't want to ever execute a
network request
during the tests exactly we need some
sort of
a mock implementation of this DataTask
there
so we can create a FakeURLSessionData
Task
right we can just return it here
so this is the expectation this is the
setup but we need to
invoke the get method yes so if you say
get
from URL I expect this to happen
I expect the sut to create a data task
from the session
with the received URL that is correct so
what is the sut
it can be a new type URLSessionHTTP
Client
and we started with the session yeah
again
constructor injection as we've done
numerous times and this is
going to be production code so keep it
outside for now
and we can move it to production when
it's time
so constructor injection and a private
property
so get from URL so far we don't need the
block
so let's keep it simple okay looks like
the compiler is happy
let's see if we get a failing test and
we do
so now we can call the session data task
with URL and we can pass any completion
handler
we don't need it yet so let's see that
should do it
okay it's passing so let's name this
test
so get from URL creates
data task with URL I'm happy with that
name
so look at this approach we are
subclassing
URLSession and URLSessionDataTask
and this is often dangerous because we
don't own those classes
they are Foundation classes and we don't
even have access to their implementation
yes and if you start mocking classes we
don't own
we can start creating assumptions in our
mocked
behavior that could be wrong yes big
time
plus these types contain
a bunch of methods that we're not
overriding here
exactly look at this bunch of methods
we don't care about exactly and you
never know how
these methods might be interoperating
between them so I see it as a risk
personally
I think we are making big assumptions
here
but so far so good that is true so let's
just separate our helpers from our tests
and I think we should commit
yes it is a working solution we should
commit
so creates URL
Session data task with URL
on URLSessionHTTPClient
.get from URL
okay so this is the first step we are
checking that we are creating
the data task with the right URL but
next thing that needs to happen
for the data task to start is to call
resume
yes so let's set a test for that I guess
we can use the
same approach and spy on the data task
now
okay so get from URL resumes
data task with URL what we need
now is to somehow be able to assert that
the task
was resumed only once yes
otherwise there will be an error so we
need a task
and so far we have our Fake
URLSessionDataTask we could create
another one
there is a URLSessionDataTaskSpy
yes and we can have our variable
resumeCallCount that starts with zero
and every time we call resume
we increment by one that's it
but now we need to tell the session to
return our task
for a given URL so we can create some
kind of stubby mechanism
so stub URL with a task
yes and how can we do that stub URL
with task and the task is a SessionData
Task
somehow we need to have a collection of
stubbed
behaviors I guess this could be a
dictionary
yes it is a key value sort of collection
meaning
for a specific URL we're going to have a
specific task
so what we need to do is to get our
stubs URL
equals task I like that so when
the production code asks for a task we
can return
the stubbed task for URL if there is
none we return the fake one
exactly okay
failing test as expected beautiful now
we just need to call
resume and
okay we got a crash here that's good
because we returned
in the first test a fake URLSession
that does not
override resume so we can just override
and do nothing let's run again
and it passes now perfect
which means if we remove the resume I'm
going to get a failing test again
look at that there you go but the
problem with those tests
when we use mocking especially of
classes we don't own is that
look how our test is tied to the
implementation
this implementation here should be
private we should test just the behavior
but because of the the mocking strategy
we chose
we end up having to test every
interaction
exactly which API is being called with
exactly which parameters at which time
and that might be what we need but that
might couple the tests
with production code so every time you
want to refactor the code you break the
tests
and that might be a problem the tests
are checking
exactly the implementation of these APIs
and we don't want that as you said we
would much rather
have checking the behavior of loading
the URLs
and the completions if possible if
possible
yeah and it is possible and we're going
to show you yeah I absolutely agree
and just the fact that we had to
override the resume method
in the FakeURLSessionDataTask
this shows you how fragile these APIs
can be
when utilized for testing purposes and
solely for testing purposes in this case
right
exactly what about other methods we are
not
overriding that might generate problems
in the future
so we need to keep an eye on this for
sure but let's commit
so far it's working yes let's do that
so resumes data task on creation
and now that we're stubbing I believe
the first test
is redundant that's true since we return
a task
for a specific URL in the stub we are
already testing the we are
invoking the method with the right URL
so this is irrelevant now
it was a good start but we often end up
deleting tests
as we learn more about the APIs so we
don't need the receivedURLs anymore
yeah much lighter
let's see if it still passes fantastic
remove redundant tests
great finally we have the API sorted
now we can actually test the behavior we
care about
so get from URL fails
on request error let's handle the errors
first
I always like to start from the error
yeah same for me sad path
get them out of the way don't have to
think about them later
so I think the setup is very similar so
let me copy this
but instead of a task now I want to stop
it with an error
yes exactly we want to stop it with an
error and
make sure that we are completing with
the same error
we can just use any error
so I still want to have the task here
because of the first test
but I can give it a default value I can
also have an error
with a default value of nil right and we
need to combine somehow now
the task and the error right we could
use a tuple or
a simple struct can we make it private
yeah
we call it stub it has a task it's a URL
Session
DataTask it has an error there is an
optional
Error okay so now we hold
stubs let's wrap that
task error
well now we need to know if we have a
task in there so
we can use a if let stub or guard yeah
then we return the stub.task and we
complete
with well data is nil response is nil
and error is the stub error
now comes the question should we
complete
in the other scenario right no we never
want that to happen so we can use a
guard let instead
okay and we can leave a nice message or
a nice crash
yes because that's a developer error in
the tests
so if we don't have a stub I want to
leave a message
so couldn't find stub for the given URL
perfect I think that's it for
our spy so carry on with the tests what
do we expect
here well we need to get the result and
make sure that we got the error
right so first of all we need the
completion block
yes so the get
from URL now needs the completion block
and
we return an HTTPClientResult
right and we can import the module
let's see okay so of course this test
now needs to ignore
the value
now we can investigate if we got the
result we expected
so if we unwrap the result we expect to
get a failure
with an error we want it to be an
NSError
so we can compare it with the given
error
that was created right here right
otherwise
we want to fail yeah any other result is
wrong so expected failure
with error got
result instead alright
but this is an asynchronous block right
so we better
guarantee we go inside the block and as
we show in the previous episode we can
use
expectations wait for completion
okay so we can fulfill after we
assert the values we can wait for the
expectation with a timeout
one should be enough more than enough
should do it yeah
we should get a failing test hopefully
hopefully
we do we never got inside the block
perfect so now it's time to call
completion
with the error and the error is the last
parameter
right in the data task completion block
but it's optional
so we need to unwrap it yeah and we need
the completion to be escaping
as well okay
right and this needs to be wrapped in a
failure result
alright it is passing now fantastic
to the git okay so let's commit then
delivers failure with error
on request error
that's it so I think it's time to get
rid of those URLSession
mocks I'm really not feeling confident
about them
and I think the natural next step is to
actually use
protocols right there are some
trade-offs there but
one gain is that with protocols
we only care about the specific behavior
this data task with URL completion
handler and yes
don't care about any other methods there
so that's a common technique
that people have been using that it's
pretty much copying
the exact API and put in a protocol
right so in production we would have a
protocol for example
HTTPSession
and we only define one method so we
eliminated the problem
of having the class with a bunch of
methods we need to care about and
override
so we can guarantee that production code
only has visibility to this method
so we only need to mock this method and
we don't need to care about the other
ones
yes so if we replace the URLSession
with HTTPSession now
it should be an easy change
so this will be an HTTPSessionSpy
conforming to HTTPSession
so it doesn't need to override anymore
it just implements it from the protocol
okay but we still have a problem here
we're still using the URLSessionData
Task
right it has a bunch of methods so
we can do the same trick and create our
HTTPSessionTask with one method
resume and let's make the HTTPSession
return the task
so we can replace the data task with the
protocol everywhere
and it doesn't need to override anymore
it just implements it
so now we just need to use the spy in
the test
yeah I think that should do it boom
easy so we replaced the subclassing
strategy
with a protocol-based strategy for
mocking the URLSession
how do you feel about that I think it's
an improvement in the sense of
hiding all those details about URL
Session we don't care about
right now we can limit the APIs we have
access to
but we added some cruft to the
production code
we have this extra protocols that
matches exactly the same interface
exactly and that's a smell for me we
introduced these two new types
for the sole purpose of testing these
are not abstractions that are meant to
be used right now
by other clients they are abstractions
for the tests I don't like that
well it's a valid solution right I've used
it before
yeah it works and I'm inclined to even
commit this
I think it was a little improvement
improved our tests but I think it
made our production code more
complicated than it should be
so there's a trade-off here that I'm not
sure if I'm
willing to make but I'm happy to commit
and see where this goes
I agree so refactor
URLSession subclass
mocking with protocol based
mocking great okay so we talked about
end-to-end testing we showed subclass
mocking
protocol-based mocking and now we want
to show another option
that often I prefer when testing HTTP
clients
and this strategy will keep our
production code clean
and keep our tests more decoupled from
the production code
absolutely and instead of mocking we're
going to be stubbing
intercepting network requests and
returning
stubbed values and there's a type in the
Foundation framework that will help us
do that
the URLProtocol APIs yes
or NSURLProtocol as formerly known
so let's have a look how this thing
works so every time we perform a URL
request
what happens behind the scenes is that
there is a URL loading system
to handle the URL request and as part of
this URL
loading system there is a type called
URLProtocol
it's an abstract class that inherits
from NSObject
and if we create our own URLProtocol
subtype and register it we can start
intercepting
URL requests for example we have HTTP
protocols we have HTTPS protocols but we
can create our own protocol our own
custom protocol
how cool is that yeah that's an obscure
part
of the system to say the least it's not
very known and you can do some
pretty tricky stuff and why would you do
that well there are a couple of cases I
just said one
custom URL protocols maybe you are
trying to communicate with a server that
has a custom protocol
also we can use it to implement a local
caching system
we can use it to get some data for
analytics purposes
for example how many requests we are
performing or even profiling how long
the requests are taking and we intercept
any URL request within the process the
application
all we have to do is to implement some
abstract methods
of the URLProtocol class because even
though it's called URLProtocol
this is a class exactly so the point is
in our case
we can actually create a subclass of URL
Protocol
implementing our stubbed behavior so we can
intercept your requests during tests
and finish it with stub requests so we
never actually go to the cloud
exactly which will make it faster and
reliable
we eliminate the flakiness of network
connections and we can hide those
details
from our production code as well and
the test code will never know if we're
using a URLSession
or another mechanism for fetching URLs
exactly we can be using frameworks AF
Networking
or URLSessions or even the legacy
URLConnections or anything that may
come up
in the future let's do this
okay so let's refactor our tests to use
the URL stub
first of all let's get rid of the
protocols
and let the compiler guide us
I need to put back the URLSession
and since we're not going to be mocking
this we can even give it a default
value yeah that's the shared URLSession
so we don't need to mock
a session anymore I'm happy to do that
and we don't need a task
we don't need to stop a task and since
we are not testing the implementation
anymore
I think we don't even need this test
it's irrelevant we don't want to mock
anymore
okay so in this test now we don't need a
session anymore
but we still need to stop the URL with
an error but now it's going to be our
URL
ProtocolStub and we don't need to give
it a session
so now this spy will be our ProtocolStub
that inherits from URLProtocol just to
make it clear one more time
we're subclassing URLProtocol here this
is a class
as you can see URL protocol is a class
that inherits from NSObject
yep don't let the name fool you
and we don't need the task anymore we
don't need the task
here anymore we need the error
and we don't need the data task method
anymore
let's get rid of those mocks yes they're
irrelevant
beautiful okay so as we said there are a
couple of methods we need to implement
if you subclass the URLProtocol class
and first of all
is the class method canInit
with request and it returns a boolean
so if we return true in this method it
means we can handle this request
and now it's our responsibility to
complete the request with either
success or failure it means we
intercepted this request
and we have control over its fate right
and how can we know if we can handle
this request well we can get the URL
from the request
if there is one and if there is no
URL in the request we cannot handle it
so let's return false
otherwise we need to check if we have a
stub
for that URL so we can return true
if we have it else we turn false so if
this is nil
we're going to return false and if this
is not nil we're going to return true
which means we have a stub for it
of course this is a static var now
and this is also a static stop method
because as you can see
canInit is called as a class method
so we don't have an instance yet exactly
the URL loading system
will instantiate our URLProtocolStub
only if we can handle the request so up
to this point we don't have an instance
yet
next we need to override another class
method
canonicalRequest for request
and we need to return a URLRequest
and since we don't want to do anything
with this request we can just return it
and finally start loading now this is an
instance method
it means that the framework has accepted
that we are going to handle this request
and now it's going to invoke us to say
now it's time for you to start loading
the URL
so again we need to get the URL for the
request
and request is an instance variable
and then we need to get our stub
for the URL else there's nothing we can
do we just return
yep so before we were completing
with an error
because we are stubbing with an error
and we can do exactly the same here
so if we have an error we need to tell
the URL loading system
that an error occurred and the way we
do it
is by using another instance property of
the URLProtocol
and it's the client as you can see the
object the protocol uses to communicate
with the URL loading system
so this client has a bunch of methods
and one of them
is to tell the URL loading system
that we failed with an error
and after we are done we need to call
client
and tell it that we finish loading
the last method we need to implement is
stopLoading
so we have no logical implementation for
it so we just don't do anything
right if we don't implement it then
we're going to get a crash
at runtime and that's a prime example of
an abstract class
here yes so this is all the
implementation we need
in the ProtocolStub now in the tests we
need to
register the stub in the URL loading
system
and to do it as we showed before we use
the Protocol
registerClass URLStub
and after the test is finished we need
to
unregister it because we don't want to
be stubbing
other test requests and this seems like
a good candidate
to move to a setUp tearDown pair of
methods
but since we have only one test I'm
happy to leave it
in this test for now and move the
registration/unregistration
when we have to exactly but one
improvement we could do here is to move
this registration to the
ProtocolStub then, we can create a
static
function startIntercepting
Requests and we can also have the
stopIntercepting
Requests where we can unregister
the ProtocolStub and also remove the
stubs
so now we can replace the registration
with the
start and stop intercepting requests
let's run the test now and if it passes
it means that we are intercepting the
requests
accordingly and returning the error
alright fantastic it is passing which
means we got
an error with the stubbed error using
the URLProtocolStub
so now our test is now using subclasses
to mock any kind of URLSession
which make our production code free to
be refactored in the future to use
AFNetworking or to keep using new APIs
from URLSession
or even use any kind of mechanism for
loading URLs that goes through the URL
loading system
so I'm happy with that awesome let's
commit
refactor URLSession mocking
strategy with URLProtocol
stubs to remove test coupling
with the URLSession
types yep that's it
so this scenario where we have a failed
request
with an error is a valid path it means
we try to execute a request
but something went wrong but in a
previous episode we showed
a table with all of the cases that can
be
represented by the three optional types
which means we have a bunch of invalid
cases an error
is not an invalid case although is the
sad path
so to be more explicit this case here
is the data is nil, response
is nil and we have an error value it's a
valid case but it's the sad path
and I like to be more explicit in the
test just like we have in our table
right here
so to stop this now we need data
response it's a URLResponse
and Error and we don't need the default
value
yeah that should do it
so we pass the data and response
to the initializer and in the start
loading
we can check if we have data
we can tell the client that we've loaded
this data and if we have a response
we can tell the client that we've
received
a response and the cache policy for this
case let's say not allowed we don't want
to cache
right we don't care about that okay
let's run this and it still passes
perfect and it's more explicit I prefer
it like this
let's commit add new data
and new response to the request
error test case to make the setup
more explicit looks great
okay so we've done a lot in this episode
already I think we finally found
the solution we want for stubbing the
requests
we don't want to use end-to-end tests at
this point
we don't want to use subclassing or even
protocol-based mocking
we found a way to keep our tests
decoupled from the implementation
and also keep our production
implementation agnostic
of testing or protocols or any kind of
mocking
mechanism and look into some more
obscure
places of Foundation as well I think
that's important
the URL loading system is something that
all professional developers probably
should be aware of and
should know how to use and utilize
depending the case
agreed so in the next episode we're
going to finish this implementation
by checking all the invalid cases and
the success cases
yeah see you next time, bye y'all, see ya