Hello Mike, hey Caio
so last time we started the URLSession
HTTPClient
and in this lecture we will continue
implementing it
so it's going to be a hands-on episode
and we'll be going fast
we'll show you a lot of code following
all the principles we've been exercising
throughout the case study
sounds awesome okay so to start with I
would like to re-evaluate
our choice of using a stub here by
showing
a downside of relying too much on stubs
to test the behavior we expect
okay so what would that be let's start
by making this test fail
let's say we have a wrong implementation
that somehow is using the wrong
URL right let me run the tests
and it fails perfect right
right but the problem is how can we find
out
that the problem was the URL right first
of all we are getting
a network error which means we actually
tried
to make a network request and it failed
but this test has nothing to do with
URLs
in the setup we are stubbing with an
error and we expect to get this error
back
and nothing in this assertion failure
tells us that the problem was the URL
I see so the only way to find out the
problem is to debug
the code and our tests can be more
valuable when they say precisely where
the problem is without having to debug
it
if you have to debug to find test
failure you are diminishing the value of
your test
exactly and in this case the problem is
that we only stub
specific URLs so if the URLs don't match
we are telling the URL loading system
that we are not going to handle this
request
so it goes through the normal URL
handling making a real HTTP
request so I think we can improve it by
removing this URL-based
stubbing and intercepting all of the
requests and adding a separate test
to make sure that we are passing the
right URL so if the URL test
fails we know the problem is the URL and
if the request error test fails we know
it's because of the
URL request's error so we need to separate
these two concerns
that sounds great so to do it we can
stop
investigating the URL in our stub and
intercept all of the requests by
returning true in the canInit
method so we don't need to pass a URL
anymore when we stub
and now our stub now doesn't need to
be a dictionary of URL and Stubs
it can be just a stub and we can make
it optional because maybe we
don't have a stub so in the setup of the
stub method
we can now just assign the stubbed data
to our stub property
and when we stop intercepting we remove
the stub
in the start loading method since we are
handling all the requests
we don't need to check for the URLs
anymore as long as we have a stub
we pass the data forward to the URL
loading system
otherwise we just completed with no
values okay
let's change the test
so the test is passing now which means
we are intercepting all the requests
regardless of the URL so we can focus
these tests on
handling errors instead of implicitly
also testing that we are passing the
right URL
and I think that's enough for us to
commit before we move on to the URL
test just to recap we're doing two main
things here
A. we don't ever hit the network
as we are always intercepting the
requests
regardless if they're coming from the
right URL
and 2. we want to have accurate
assertions
so when a test fails we want to know why
is it failing so we increase the value
of our tests exactly alright
sounds good so I'm going to commit to
the changes so far but I'm not going to
add
the wrong URL right everything else goes
so we made the URLProtocolStub
intercept every network
request instead of URL
based mocking since we don't
want to ever perform a network
request during tests also we
want our assertions to be more precise
about the error when they fail
yeah very descriptive as it should be
okay
but by doing this change we lost the
value of
checking the URL right but since that's
a different concern
we can move it to a separate test with a
more precise assertion
exactly we can test it in isolation
so get from URL performs
GET request with URL okay
so we need to intercept requests
and also stop intercepting requests
what we need to do is somehow observe
all requests with some kind of observer
closure right that we can get a request
in and we can run our assertions
for example that the request URL was a
given URL
and we can test that the HTTP method
of the request is GET so let's implement
this
observer, observe requests
so we can pass an observer closure
that is going to forward all of the
requests
it's a func yes and we can capture
the closure so it needs to be escaping
okay so we can define our static
variable request observer we can even
make it optional
like we did with the stub let's not
forget
to set it to nil when we stop
intercepting requests
and every time a request is initiated
we can invoke the observer passing the
request that should do it
okay the compiler is happy but we need
to define a
URL so I guess we can just copy the one
from the previous test
and since this block is invoked
asynchronously it's better
to make sure it was invoked with an
expectation
wait for request so we can fulfill
the expectation inside the block after
the assertions
and wait for the expectation with a
timeout
and we need to call our get method
exactly
if we don't call the get method this
would never
pass so we call it with the URL we
expect
and we can pass an empty completion
block so if we invoke get method with the
URL
we expect a request to be executed with
the right URL and method
I like that I think this test
complements very nicely
the previous one and if it fails as you
said before
we are going to get a tailored message
here showing exactly
why this test failed we can even show it
failing
by putting back the wrong URL
perfect tells us precisely where the
problem is
that's great okay so let's get rid of
this
let's tidy up the code a little bit
run the test again it's passing so we
separated the concerns of testing
the requested URL and handling the
request errors
I like that agreed so guarantees
correct URL and HTTP
method on get requests
so we can use the same mechanism to test
POST requests and also investigate the
body of the request
we can also investigate the query
parameters of the request any request
related
data that we care about can be asserted
through these observers
and without hitting the network exactly
which makes them reliable and fast
yeah moving on I see a bunch of
duplication here
yeah I think it's time and the start and
stop method invocations can be moved
to the setup and teardown so if you're
not familiar with
XCTestCase the setUp and tearDown
methods
are invoked for each test case so the
setUp
is invoked before each test method and
the tearDown is invoked
after each test method so we can safely
move
the start and stop to the setUp and tear
Down methods
you can do the same for this test and as
you keep adding tests
we can guarantee that we are
intercepting requests
in all the test methods alright
let's commit move start
and stop intercepting requests
choose setUp and tearDown methods
okay so we can move the sut creation to
makeSUT
factory right this way we protect our
tests from any
API changes okay so I think we can even
do the
get in one line I think so create the
sut
and we can do the same in here yep okay
so this guarantees that as we keep
implementing the URLSession if we ever
have to change its APIs for example
to add some dependencies in here we
don't break tests that don't care about
this dependency
classic factory method and another thing
that we could do here
is return the HTTPClient protocol
the URLSessionHTTPClient is supposed
to
conform to the protocol but it doesn't
yet yes unfortunately
but that's fine we will add a mental
note
and do it at the end okay as soon as
we've implemented the protocol we can
make the factory method return
an abstraction rather than the concrete
type so we can protect our tests from
implementation details as well
I really like that so move the
URLSessionHTTPClient well
the system under test or
sut creation to a factory
method to protect our tests
from breaking changes
that's it nice okay so since we're doing
this
we could also add the memory leak
tracking as we did in other tests
yep that sounds good track memory leaks
we have this method here we used in the
other component
let's just copy here for now yeah I like
that we can do it in two steps
so we can run the track memory leaks by
passing the sut
the file and the line so we can get a
nice assertion in the right place
which means we need to get the final
line in the makeSUT method
that's it that should be enough okay
let's commit add memory leak
tracking and since we have this
duplicated method we can move it yeah
it's being used in two test files
already so I'm happy to do that
so let me create a helper's folder in
the test target
and I'm going to create a XCTestCase
MemoryLeakTracking helper
okay so let's create an extension on
XCTestCase
and move the track memory leak helper
to this shared scope we can remove now
previous functions there very nice
let's run the tests alright they're
passing so let's commit
extract memory leak
tracking helper method to a shared
extension on XCTestCase
nice anything else you see
I think the URL creation is with the
same string so perhaps this can go in a
helper function as well
okay so since this is any URL
we can create a factory method and we
can even call it any
URL yeah it gives some context
in the test as well so let's use it
in the first test and in the second test
we can even move it inline I think it's
very explicit here
any URL it doesn't matter we are
stubbing so it doesn't matter
let's run the tests that looks neat
let's commit
move URL creation to a
shared factory method nice
very neat and you can see as part of the
process we keep refactoring
the production code and the test code
exactly
and we are protecting our code and our
sanity
with these changes here because it may
become
cumbersome and we don't want that we
want to be proactive
and take a few minutes and do these
changes now so we don't have to pay the
price later
exactly clean as you go so we don't
accumulate cruft
exactly so let's move on and implement
the invalid cases
so let me bring on the table with all
the invalid cases here
let's make some space here so as you can
see we have a bunch of invalid cases
that may never happen right but since
the URL system
APIs represents the output as optional
for example by combining the Data, URL
Response and Error and we only care
about cases where
we have an Error and no response and
Data
and when we have Data and an HTTPURL
Response and no Error
as you can see the URLResponse is a
class and HTTPURLResponse is a
subclass of URLResponse
that's unfortunate because it adds to
the complexity
look at all these cases basically every
time there's a URLResponse we need to
check
for an HTTPURLResponse as well because
it's a subtype of URLResponse
exactly so we increase the number of
invalid scenarios because of the
subtyping so we can make the case that
we trust the framework since those are
results that should never happen
but since it can be represented and
there is some obscure side to this
framework
since we cannot even see the
implementation of those types
we can add some extra tests to guarantee
that we are covering all the edge cases
so when using third-party APIs it's
advised to add extra tests
to validate assumptions plus when there
is a new version of
the third party framework we are using
we can happily upgrade and guarantee the
framework changes
didn't break our assumptions and
expectations
so let's start with the first one the
invalid case where we got
nil, nil and nil for the Data, URL
Response and Error
okay copy the test
so fails on
all nil values so we don't have an error
data is new response is new and error is
nil
now we don't have any kind of error to
check against
in this case we want it to be a failure
but
to be fair since it's an invalid case I
just want it to be a failure I don't
care about
which error got there there's no great
way of
handling or recovering from this error
apart from
retrying yeah it's an invalid case and
it should never happen
we don't want to pollute our tests with
specific error types there
I think and we also don't want the app
to crash
because although it should never happen
it may happen so
it should be a failure the user should
be able to retry it shouldn't crash
but I also don't care which kind of
error since this case would be a
programmer error or a framework
error so let's see our test should fail
yes it failed so that should be easy
to make it pass we can just create an
else case and complete
with a failure with any error here right
and we can create our own type there
so since this is an unexpected case
we can create an unexpected values
representation
ever yep exactly okay it can be
for example instruct the conforms to the
Swift Error protocol
alright let's see if it passes that should
do it I guess
okay it's passing beautiful so in this
case we chose not to check
the specific error because this is an
invalid scenario that can be represented
but if you really care about this
scenario you better add
a type check here in your tests but I'm
happy with this
so far and we can change our minds in
the future so let's commit
delivers unexpected values
error when request completes
with data, response and error
as nil, okay and it seems that we have
some duplication now with the two
failed cases so why don't we extract the
duplicate code
so we have different setups here but the
algorithm is very similar
okay so we can move this to a helper
method
yes so result
error for data
response and error
and it should return the error and it's
optional because if it was a success
result we don't have an error yeah
exactly
so let me copy this setup
let's see what we need to change here so
we need to pass the data the response
and the error we wait for the completion
that's fine
but now we need to capture the error
so receivedError is an Error optional
let's get the error
and we return the error at the end so we
need to keep the failed
assertion in the case that we got a
success
but we better pass the file and line
exactly since this is in a helper now
and it's going to be used a bunch of
times
from other tests we want to know exactly
where we're failing
otherwise the tests lose their
importance
and since the makeSUT also expects
file and line
to display the failed assertions in the
right place we better put this into a
variable
as well okay that looks like the setup
we need
now let's refactor the tests to use it
so in the first test
we don't need to invoke the stub anymore
we just need to get
the receivedError
when we pass nil, nil and the
error and then we can keep the assertion
that they receivedError but now we need
to cast it to NSError yeah
that's it basically is equal to the passed
error so let's give
even more context by saying request
error
nice it matches the name of the test as
well
exactly so failures and requests over so
here's the request error
we pass the error to the helper function
and we expect the received error
to be the same as the request error
let's see if it passes
it does fantastic what about the second
test
since we don't care about the error type
we just care that there is an error
we can use the assert not nil helper
by bypassing the result error for data
nil, response, nil and error
nil the match is the invalid case we
care about
so far let's see if it passes
it does that was a great refactoring
look how
simple the test method is now I think
that's an
extremely valuable refactoring alright
so
let's commit extract duplicate
code into a shared reusable
helper method to simplify
tests yep fantastic
should we add one test method for each
invalid case I think we can group them
in one test
and name it fails for all
invalid cases or something like that
okay so failures on all
invalid representation cases yes and we
can add all the assertions
here exactly exactly so here's for the
second
invalid case where we have new data we
have a response but it's unknown
HTTPURLResponse yes and
no error so it's the second case here so
what is a non
HTTP response it's a URLResponse
let's create one here with any URL let's
use our helper method
we don't need to give a mime type
content length or
encoding okay that's the second case
let's see if passes
it does fantastic so let's move on in
the same commit
so here we have a HTTPURLResponse
actually any
any, yes HTTP response should generate
this error so
let's create our HTTP response here
so we have again anyURL any status code
and we don't need anything else okay
this should pass as well
fantastic now next test
when we have data like any data but
everything else is nil
this is also an invalid case so let me
create our any data
value any data it should pass
because it returns an error fantastic
now the next case we have any data
and an error but no response
okay so any error let's say it's an
NSError because it's easy to create
any error it should pass because we are
returning an error for this case
as well fantastic
now it's the case where data is nil we
have a non HTTPURLResponse
and we have an error it should also be
invalid
passing moving on next case
we have nil data we have
a HTTPURLResponse but also with an
error
this is invalid so we should pass
fantastic okay next case we have
everything
any data we have a response but it's a
non HTTPURLResponse and we have an
error
this is also invalid it should pass
fantastic the same but now it's an
HTTPURLResponse
also invalid case fantastic
now it's the last scenario where we have
data a non HTTPURLResponse
and no error this is almost correct yeah
it's close
but the only problem is that it's not a
HTTP
URLResponse not quite there yeah okay
they are all passing so we are covering
all invalid scenarios now
fantastic let's commit delivers
error on all invalid or unexpected
representation cases that's it
okay finally we are done with all the
invalid scenarios
validating our assumptions about the
framework yeah
but can we extract these constants into
helper functions as well
okay it's a bit noisy isn't it yeah I
think so
so we can create the anyData helper
that returns data
so now we can just use the helper
everywhere you can also do the same
with the error
and since this is an NSError I would
call any NSError
right very specific but it could also be
any error
yeah exactly but we are specific about
the type so let's be specific in the
name as well
okay so we can replace
two inline calls to the anyNSError
helper method okay so we can do the same
with the HTTPURL
Response anyHTTP
URLResponse
and just for completion sake let's do
the same with the non
HTTPURLResponse
non HTTPURLResponse returns a URL
Response
let's run the tests fantastic
much cleaner let's commit
extract test values creation
to shared factory methods that's it
we can even do the same in the first
test and use the anyNSError
right so in this case we can amend this
change to the previous commit
I'm happy to do it so since this is the
only change
we can add it to the stage and we can
amend
to the previous commit fantastic
okay it's time for the happy path all
right finally we're gonna deal with the
valid case
so test
get from URL succeeds
on HTTPURLResponse with
data
so we need to stub the protocol with
some data
with a response and no error
just like in this first valid case
so data is anyData and response
is also anyHTTPURLResponse
exactly okay so we need to make
our sut and say get from any
URL let's get the result
let's switch on the result and now we
care about
the success case with the received
data and received response
now we need to assert that we got the
right values so the received data should
be the passed
data and the received
response should be the response
else for any other case we should fail
yeah we expect success so we should fail
there
so expected success got result
instead nice let's fulfill
okay so it's asynchronous we need to
follow the same dance
let's wait for completion
and fulfill after
our assertions and then we need to
wait for the expectation to complete
with a timeout
fantastic let's run this test and we
should get
failing tests yes we expected success
but it failed
with unexpected values representation
because we haven't implemented
this behavior yet alright let's do it
we need another else case here if we
have data
and we have a response and this response
is an HTTPURLResponse
exactly then we can complete with
success
with the data and response
of course we need to name the variables
data and response
passed to the completion closure
oh it should have passed but we got a
failing test let's have a look at this
what happened there we got two failing
tests here
first of all the invalid case when we
have nil
data and an HTTPURLResponse started
failing
hmm we need to investigate this and the
next one was that
we didn't receive the same response
let's have a look at it right
so NSHTTPURLResponse is a class
as we already discussed and internally
the URL loading system
is somehow replacing the passed response
with their own response here
so it's comparing the pointers and they
are not the same
as you can see right the address is
different
so they are not equal because when you
compare classes they often compare the
pointer
so we can just check the values the URL
and status code for instance
that's what we care for now okay
that makes sense that should be enough
for us to make sure we got
a comprehensive response okay let's see
if we solve this problem now
alright we are getting the right
response it's just that
somehow the framework replaced it with
another instance
but the values are still the same so I'm
happy with it now let's have a look at
this failure
what is happening here what does the
error say
well we expected a failure of course but
we got a success
with data with zero bytes data and a
response
right okay so okay we thought
that this would generate an invalid
scenario but somehow the URL loading
system
is replacing our nil data with
an empty data of zero bytes in the case
where
we returned a valid HTTPURLResponse
right
we are completing with success from our
production side
yes so what we thought to be an invalid
case and it would be an invalid case if
the framework
ever delivered the nil data with an HTTP
URLResponse
is actually valid because the framework
replaces the nil data
with an empty data there is a real
instance of data here with zero bytes
and I believe this is a valid scenario
right but I don't want to deal with this
in the same commit
so one thing we can do here to make this
pass is just to check that the
bytes of the data the count is bigger
than zero so it's not empty
yeah I agree with that we shouldn't
commit a failing test
and I don't see the point of commenting
out the assertion or the whole test
there
so I like that
okay so delivers data and
response on successful HTTP
URL request
okay but of course we don't want this in
here right
so this is the invalid case that is
actually
made valid by the framework so let me
remove it and move it to a separate
assertion because we need to know what's
going on here
yeah for sure so let me copy this
and let's recreate this scenario so we
have
an HTTPURLResponse but we have no data
so I don't need this data here and we
expect
empty data in this case so the test is
succeeds with empty data
on HTTPURLResponse with nil data yeah
so this is an assumption we had about
the framework that was proven wrong
that's the value of adding the tests
alright it's failing because of our
condition here and I don't want this
condition here
because an empty data representation is
a valid representation yeah for example
there's an HTTP status code that
represents no content data
the 204 status code so empty data is a
valid HTTP
response so we better add the test
to validate our assumption about the
framework
so it's passing now and we removed the
conditional fantastic
but I would like to have some more
context about this data here
so let's create an empty data
just to give more context yeah what we
are asserting here it's an empty data
representation that matches the test
name it helps the developers and helps
ourselves if we ever have to maintain
this test in the future
exactly we're being a good citizen
here alright it's passing so let's
commit
you see how valuable it is to add those
tests
against the real frameworks so delivers
empty data and response
on successful HTTP response with
nil data since the URL loading
system completes the request with
a known nil empty data value
well zero bytes yeah which is a valid
case
for example HTTP 204
no content response fantastic and we
leave some documentation in our commit
messages as well
to explain this scenario okay and since
we have two
successful cases they're sharing code so
I think we can extract
the shared code as we did with the
failure case
okay so we can create another function
for example result
values right here we're returning the
success case
so we're going to have our received
values that we're going to return and
what is the type
of the received values it's a Data and
HTTPURLResponse tuple
yeah okay so let's
change our type signature here and this
is the
success case with data and response
so the received values will be data
and response so expected success
got result instead okay
let's see if we can refactor the test
now
so receivedValues is result values for
data nil, response and error
nil okay that's it let's replace it now
with the stub
we can just grab our assertions
and now check against the received
values
data receivedValues response URL and
receivedValues
response statusCode that's it let's see
if it passes
fantastic okay
for the previous test we can do the same
let me copy this setup
here but now we are passing the data
and we want to investigate the right
data here
so given, when
then, given, when
then yeah it looks very clean alright
it's passing
yeah but I think we're duplicating some
code in the test helpers now so perhaps
we can extract this shared code into a
new private function
okay so let's create a function result
for let me copy this signature here
but we are going to return the result
now HTTPClient
result and it's not optional because you
always have a result
okay let me copy this setup in here
so instead of received error we have
received result
that we are going to return and the
result is of type
ClientResult and since we don't have a
value
yet we need to force and wrap it in the
type definition
but it's safe to do so in this case
because we always get a result
we don't care about assertions in this
case we just get the result
we fulfill and we return the result
fantastic
now in this case we need to get the
result so
result is resolved for
data, response, error
file and line we don't need to stub
anymore
and just capture the error yeah much
simpler you can even just return
it straight away here
and we return nil in this case because
we have no error
exactly it is still passing
fantastic so we can use the same setup
for the result values for our success
case
okay we don't need this anymore we just
return
the success values or nil
in any other case
that should do it fantastic
let's commit extract duplicate
code into a new shared reusable
helper method to simplify tests
that's it and I think we are done with
all the cases yeah we
validated our assumptions about the
framework we
left a trace of documentation of how to
use this thing
I think it paid off we mentioned that
you can make the case that you don't
need to test the cases that are invalid
if you trust the framework but we kind
of learned a lot about
this third-party framework by exercising
our assumptions and expectations
exactly I think that's very important
there not just for
covering you know about these edge cases
but actually seeing how
classes that you don't own operate and
they behave
basically so I was very happy about our
decision to test all invalid states
because
they can be represented as we proved
exactly so now we can make the URL
Session
conform to the HTTPClient protocol
since we are done with the
implementation
alright and if you remember our mental
note we are going to make the makeSUT
function return the abstraction yes
and it should still pass because we
don't want the tests depending
on too much implementation details
fantastic
look at that let's commit make
URLSessionHTTPClient
conform to the HTTPClient
protocol okay and since this is done we
can move it to
its own file now so let me get rid of
this table we don't need it anymore
okay here it is so now access control
this is a public class public
initializer
this struct we don't need to expose it
yet so
let's make it private until we need it
to be exposed
I agree yes and the get function is
public
as part of the HTTPClient interface
let's see if the test has access to this
type and everything is still
passing ok it is fantastic
let's commit move URLSessionHTTP
Client
to its own file in production
fantastic and just to show the power of
abstracting
even your tests of the implementation
details is that we can easily
refactor this implementation to be just
an extension
on URLSession
so we don't need to use the session
instance anymore we can just call the
method on itself
yep so in our test we just replace the
makeSUT to use the
URLSession shared instance so I'm going
to remove the track
memory leaks because the shared instance
never goes away it's a singleton
yes let's run the tests
as you can see they still pass so look
how easily we refactored
a type into another type extension
without breaking any tests
just by replacing the factory method and
this is the power of
using abstractions even in your tests
how powerful is that
yeah I'd say especially in your test as
well
it's extremely important because you
want to be flexible you want to be able
to make these types of changes
at any given time so personally
I love this so I'm going to revert that
change
right
alright we are back with our adapter
type here
and if you prefer having an extension on
the Foundation type
URLSession that's fine as well I'm just
concerned that
we might have a method conflict at some
point
if they ever create a method called get
from URL it might never happen but
I'm cautious so it's my personal
preference to create my own
adapter types but you are free to make
your own choice
control what you can I guess and in this
case we can control
our class our new type so yeah I agree
with you I'm happy
to leave it as it is so that's it that
was a very intense episode
we've done a bunch of hands-on coding
and refactoring
don't forget to read the description to
learn more about the techniques used in
this episode
and we'll see you again next time bye
y'all
see ya