Hello Mike, hello everyone, hey
Caio in this lecture you'll learn how to
refactor
this composition from design patterns
to universal abstractions using the
Combine
framework and why would we do that
there's nothing wrong with design
patterns but some design patterns
are equivalent to universal abstractions
from category theory
which means we can seamlessly replace
some design patterns
with built-in Combine operators
that can help us compose our application
in the Composition Root
so you don't need to develop maintain
and test your own
implementations you can use the built-in
operators as building blocks fantastic
let's start okay so the goal is to
replace
those design pattern implementations
with Combine
so let's import Combine
and since we don't want to break our
existing code
let's do things step by step let's
create a factory method to create
remote feed loader with
a local fallback
but instead of returning a FeedLoader
we want to return a Combine Publisher
that produces
exactly what a FeedLoader would so in
this case
the FeedLoader produces results of type
FeedImage or Error right
so let's get this type signature and
let's return here a Combine Publisher
which could be on AnyPublisher that can
produce an array of
FeedImages or an Error
so let's copy the existing code in here
so we need to create a RemoteFeedLoader
with a URL
and a HTTPClient but our RemoteFeed
Loader doesn't know about Combine
so we need to lift this FeedLoader to
the Combine
world so we can wrap our FeedLoader in a
Combine
Publisher and there are many Publishers
you can create
one of those Publishers is a Future that
starts with a completion block
and once you're done with work you call
the completion with some result
what we can do inside this Future is to
actually invoke our RemoteFeedLoader
load operation and complete
with the completion because they have
matching types
remember we are completing with either
an array of FeedImages or Error which
is exactly the same signature
that our RemoteFeedLoader produces but
now the compiler is complaining that
Future is a different type that we
expect
in the return method so here we could
return
a Future the compiler will be happy
but using a Future is an implementation
detail
if you don't want to expose that detail you
can erase
ToAnyPublisher to hide from clients
which
Publisher you are using so when you
don't expose
the specific Publisher you are using you
can use type erasure
with the eraseToAnyPublisher operator
right instead of leaking the
implementation detail of
a Future Publisher that's it but there's
one problem
with Futures, Futures are
eager Publishers which means this block
will be executed as soon as you created
the Future so every time you call this
function
it will fire this block instantly
and this may be fine maybe that's what
you want but what we want here
is to only fire a request when someone
subscribes to it
not on creation of the Publisher so one
way
we can defer the execution of the Future
is to wrap it into a Deferred
Publisher look at that
we are wrapping Publishers into
Publishers
just like we wrap our abstractions
with the decorators, composites, adapters
and etc it's the same principle of
wrapping
the type into another type to change its
behavior
but instead of creating our own
implementations we can use
those universal abstractions they are
built-in
in the framework and since the types
match
between the RemoteFeedLoader completion
block
and the Future completion block we can
just pass
the load function for the completion
parameter
exactly okay so we lifted
our RemoteFeedLoader into the Combine
world we can now load
the feed using Combine Publishers
we can even extract this code into an
extension so we can make it easier to
read
okay so we can extend the RemoteFeed
Loader
with a function transitioning this load
function to the Combine
world so the load function now is a load
Publisher that returns AnyPublisher
of FeedImage or Error
okay but
since the RemoteFeedLoader defines its
own error
the types don't match here because here
we expect Swift
Error but here is the RemoteFeedLoader
Error
but we can use the module name to solve
this problem
that should do it alright so when
using a RemoteFeedLoader we can just
get
a loadPublisher now that will wrap
the load function into Combine
Publishers so we can even create a type
alias here
Publisher of type FeedImage
or Error
okay that looks clean
but this is just the beginning right we
just
wrapped the load function into Combine
Publishers
we still need to perform the composition
with the cache and with the fallback
so let's start with the cache decorator
so this FeedLoaderCacheDecorator we
created in a previous episode
exists just to inject a side-effect into
a FeedLoader
so every time we load something from
this FeedLoader we inject
the cache side-effect using map
so we inject inside-effect with map
and we can do exactly the same thing
with Combine operators
so let's create an extension on
Publisher
where the output is array of
FeedImage let's create a function
let's say caching to
a cache that's what we get here
that should return a Publisher with the
same type
and failure so we're not changing the
types
we just want to inject a side-effect
into the chain
and just like we did here
let's copy and paste the map operation
and in this case we don't need self
because we have access to the cache
directly and again we need to erase
to AnyPublisher okay that's it
this is literally a copy and paste of
what we're doing before
exactly because when you use a decorator
to inject a side-effect
into a polymorphic interface you can
always replace that with
map and in fact since we are not
transforming
the value we are just injecting a side
effect
we can use a different operator that is
built-in
specifically for injecting side-effects
which is the handleEvents operation
where you get an output and you don't
need to return
anything because you're not supposed to
transform
this value that's it look how we can
inject
side-effects with much less lines of
code
that's a built-in operator we don't need
to develop
test and maintain it
okay and since the received output
closure has the same signature
as the saveIgnoringResult function we
can pass it directly
look at that okay
beautiful so this whole class can be
replaced
with this function, a one-liner
basically
okay let's move this
back to the SceneDelegate file
now we can just add it to the chain
caching to a feed cache and what is the
feed cache here
the LocalFeedLoader okay
the cache decorator is done now we need
the fallback logic
let's follow the same idea
and create an extension on Publisher
so what we need here is to load from a
primary
Publisher first and if it fails
we want to try to load from a fallback
Publisher
right so we need a primary and a
fallback
so let's create here our fallback
function
so fallback to fallback publisher
which needs to be a Publisher as well
but the problem is that you cannot use
the Publisher protocol
as a parameter because it has associated
types right so for now let's set it as
an Any
Publisher but let's keep the same
generic types Output and Failure
now we want to listen to errors and if
there's an error
if there's a failure we want to load
from a fallback in this case we want to
replace
the chain with the fallback publisher
and there's an operator for that
which is the catch operator the problem
is that
catch is a keyword in Swift right
so the compiler is a bit confused here
but we can use
self.catch that will help the
compiler understand
we want the catch function not the catch
keyword
and the catch function expects a closure
that receives an Error
and returns a Publisher so we can also
make here
an Error closure and pass to the catch
function and eraseToAnyPublisher
but in our composite we ignore the error
in the failure case
so we can even ignore the error here
like this right
so the catch operator in Publisher is
equivalent
to the fallback composite we created
it's a way of
injecting fallback logic into Publishers
and it's a reusable way of doing so
so again you don't need to implement
maintain and test that logic
okay let's move that to the Scene
Delegate file
and carry on our composition
so now we need to chain here the
fallback
operation and the fallback
is the local feed loader loadPublisher
but the LocalFeedLoader don't have a
loadPublisher
so we can either duplicate this
extension but for the
LocalFeedLoader or we can simply make
this extension
open for any FeedLoader yeah
we can do that look at that now any Feed
Loader
can be wrapped into Combine Publishers
which means we don't need this Swift.
Error anymore
and that's it that's the composition
with Combine
those chained operators are equivalent
to this composition
with the fallback composite and the
cache decorator
injecting the cache side-effect so now
we can
replace the design pattern
implementations with Combine
in the composer as well so instead of
passing
a FeedLoader we can pass a function
that creates Feedloader Publishers
but before we can do that we need to
create one more
operator an operator that dispatches
work
in the main thread so let's undo
let's check the main dispatch decorator
again let's import Combine here and
let's
replicate this logic using Combine
operators so the logic is when
dispatching work
if we are already on the main thread
complete immediately
otherwise dispatch to the main queue
asynchronously
so extension Publisher
let's call it dispatchOnMainQueue
that should return AnyPublisher
with the same Output and Failure it should
not change the types
should only inject this dispatch
decorator
and there is an operator for dispatching
on any queue
in Combine which is receive on a
scheduler
and DipatchQueue implements the
Scheduler protocol
so we can use the dispatch queue main
scheduler
to dispatch work to the main queue
but there is a problem this operator the
dispatch queue main
scheduler will always dispatch
asynchronously
it will not check if you are already on
the main thread and complete immediately
so the behavior is different when using
the dispatch queue main
scheduler and we want to keep the same
behavior
right if we are already on the main
queue we want to complete
immediately so we can do is to wrap the
dispatch queue
main scheduler into our own
scheduler okay so let's create
our ImmediateWhenOn
MainQueueScheduler which needs to
implement
the Scheduler protocol that is defined
in the Combine framework let's have a
look
so we need to define some associated
types and we need to provide those
implementations
okay so since we are wrapping the
dispatch queue main
into this type we can literally use the
same
DispatchQueue types
so now it's going to be this DispatchQueue
main
now the minimum tolerance
is the dispatch queue tolerance and here
is the method
we care about the schedule method that
performs
the work right so here we want to add
our logic if we are
already on the main thread we complete
immediately otherwise
we schedule using the DispatchQueue
main thread scheduler that's it
now if we're using the scheduler to
schedule something
after a specific date we cannot execute
it immediately
so we just forward the message to the
main queue scheduler
okay let's now create a static immediate
WhenOnMainQueueScheduler
and we can use it now to make sure we
keep the same behavior we have in the
app
right now so that's it a MainQueue
DispatchDecorator
can be replaced seamlessly with the
receive
on scheduler operation
so again let's move that to the Scene
Delegate
keep all operators in one place for now
now we have everything we need to
replace the FeedLoader with the
Publisher
in the Composition Root so here instead
of
wrapping the FeedLoader in a decorator
we're going to dispatch
on the main queue
look at that fantastic
so the presentation adapter don't get
FeedLoaders anymore
it gets Publishers so we need to replace
this code with the Publisher
syntax which we can use
sink to subscribe to the Publisher and
start the operation
so if we receive a completion
or if we receive values
we need to perform exactly the same
logic
so when we receive a successful value
we tell the presenter that we finish
loading the feed
and if the publisher completes it either
completes
with a finished case which in this case
we don't want to do
anything or
a failure case with an error
where we want to tell the presenter
about the error
so we need to weakify self okay
so we don't need this load anymore
last thing we need to hold the result of
the subscription which is a Cancellable
because if you don't hold the Cancellable
it will be deallocated
and when the Cancellable is deallocated
it cancels the whole subscription
alright now we just need to update
our Composition Root with the Publisher
chain
so we don't need the RemoteFeedLoader
or the URL in this function anymore okay
last build error we need to import
Combine
let's run the tests and we got a build
error
because we now need to inject the load
Publisher
instead of injecting FeedLoaders that's
all you need to change in the tests
let's run the tests
it's passing which means the composition
works
okay and how easy was it to replace
decorators and composites
with Combine without breaking tests
without breaking other modules
so we don't need the FeedLoaderWith
FallbackComposite
if we are using Combine yeah we also
don't need the FeedLoader
CacheDecorator
and we don't need the FeedLoader Main
QueueDispatchDecorator
extension as well
so we don't need the tests as well right
much less work using these built-in
universal abstractions with Combine
okay let's commit okay
replace FeedLoader composition with
Combine
operators and let's do the same thing
for the FeedImageDataLoader
so the FeedImageDataLoader produces
either
Data or Error and it needs a URL
to perform the requests so again we wrap
the operation in a Deferred Future
and we execute the loadImageData from
URL
with the completion block of the Future
but the loadImageData can be cancelled
right
so we hold a reference to that task
and if you receive a cancel event we
cancel
the task so again we are using the
handleEvents
to inject a side-effect into the chain
and the side-effect in this case when
there is a cancel
event is to cancel the running task
that's it and we also need to inject the
caching
side-effect into a FeedImageDataCache
so again we use the handle events to
inject side-effect
into the chain
and we can now create a makeLocal
ImageLoaderWithRemote
Fallback function that takes a URL
and returns a FeedImageDataLoader
Publisher so here we need
the remote and local image loaders
and the logic is to first
load from local image loader and
fallback
to the remote loader right so it's the
inverse
of the FeedLoader where we first load
the remote and then the local
so load first from the local with the
load image data
from URL Publisher
and we fall back to the remote image
loader
load image Publisher
caching to the local image loader using
the URL and that's it the same
composition
with Combine as we have with the
composite and decorators
so now we can inject a closure receiving
a URL
that produces FeedImageDataLoader
Publishers
again we need to decorate with the main
queue
we can reuse the dispatchOnMainQueue
operation
let's import Combine and Foundation
and replace the imageLoader with
a subscription to the Publisher using
sink
so if the completion is just
a finished case we break
but if it's a failure we pass the
failure
to the presenter
and if it's successful value result
data we also pass the value to the
presenter
of course we also need to hold the
cancellable
which previously was a task
now we need to fix the test
by passing the Publisher instead of the
loader
so from the tests it's passing
fantastic which means we don't need
the fallback composite for the image
data loader as well
and we don't need the ImageDataLoader
CacheDecorator
as well so we can delete the MainQueue
DispatchDecorator too
we get all this behavior for free with
universal
abstractions that Combine give us for
free
look at that so much cleaner let's run
the test again
passing let's commit
so replace FeedImageDataLoader
composition
with Combine operators
okay now we can move these Combine
helpers to a separate file
let's run the tests passing let's commit
move Combine helpers to a new
file so all the tests are passing
let's run the application
and it still works fantastic
that's how we can use Combine to compose
your application
with universal abstractions in the
Composition
Root and the idea is similar to some
design patterns
where you wrap your types using a
polymorphic
interface so some design patterns are
equivalent
to built-in universal abstractions like
map, flatMap, catch, handleEvents
and etc so you don't need to reinvent
the wheel okay this is going to do it
for this lecture
we'll see you again next time bye y'all
see ya