Hello Mike, hey Caio
in this lecture we'll create our main
iOS application project where we're
going to compose
all the modules and the only thing
missing is the implementation
of the FeedImageDataLoader exactly
which also needs to be moved into the
Feed
Feature module along with the Feed
Loader
protocol and the FeedImage data model
and that's because it basically doesn't
belong in the UI
it doesn't belong in the Presentation
yes it's an abstraction
over a core feature of the Feed Feature
module
loading image data thus it can be moved
along with the Feed Feature module
awesome
and just like we have a remote
implementation of the FeedLoader
and a local implementation of the Feed
Loader we also need
a remote implementation of the Feed
ImageDataLoader
to fetch images from the network and a
local one
to fetch it from the cache exactly
so let's have a look at the protocol
first of all we moved it
to the Feed Feature folder so when it's
time we can move it to its own
package along with the other feature
abstractions
so the FeedImageDataLoader protocol
has only one method
load image data from URL and a
completion block
with a Result type of either Data
with the image data or an Error and it
returns
a Task that can be cancelled okay
and just like we created use cases for
loading
the feed we have also created use cases
for loading
the image data so first use case
loading image data from remote the data
provider to the use case
is just a URL in the happy path we
execute the load image data command
which is the method in the protocol then
the system downloads
the data from the URL validates the
downloaded data
and delivers the image data pretty
straightforward
if you cancel it the system should not
deliver
any result it should not deliver image
data nor
error if the data is invalid
the system delivers invalid data error
or if there is no connectivity the
system delivers
connectivity error exactly
so let's have a look at implementation
of this use case okay
so we created a new DataLoader the
RemoteFeedImageDataLoader
class that conforms to the use case
abstraction the FeedImageDataLoader
and since it's a remote component
it is grouped in the Feed API
folder along with the other remote
components
so the RemoteFeedImageDataLoader
performs HTTP requests
so we are using the same HTTPClient
that we used in the RemoteFeedLoader
exactly the HTTPClient is just a
protocol and it's been reused now across
components
the FeedLoader and the FeedImageData
Loader because they both perform GET
requests
so the implementation now of the load
ImageData from URL command
it's very simple we create a task that
can be cancelled
we start the HTTP GET request for the
URL
and when we get the result we complete
the task with either
a connectivity error if there was an
error or we validate
the response it should be okay and the
data should not be empty
if it's valid we compete with success
with the image data
or failure with invalid data and that's
it
awesome very simple stuff
in the next use case the load feed image
data from cache
use case which again you start with a
URL
to identify the item in the cache
we execute the load image data command
with the URL
the system should retrieve that data
from cache and deliver it
to the client, if the client cancels the
request
the use case should not deliver any
result so it should not deliver image
data nor
error if there's a retrieval error of
course we deliver the error
and if the cache is empty that's also a
sad path we deliver not found
error result exactly so let's have a
look at implementation
so LocalFeedImageDataLoader
implements the FeedImageDataLoader
abstraction
starts with a Store which is a new
where you can insert data for a given
URL
you can retrieve data for a given URL
so the loadImageData from URL command
will create a task that can be cancelled
it'll start retrieving the data from the
store
when we get a result back we complete
the task with either
a LoadError.failed or if we found
the data we complete with success
otherwise
with a not found result okay
and that's all and we also implemented
the FeedImage
DataStore infrastructure with a Core
Data
implementation which is very simple
the insert data for URL performs the
task
in a background context all it does is
to find
the first feed image that matches the
URL
if it finds it it stores the data with
that image model
and save and the retrieve data for URL
simply try to find a feed image
with a given URL and return its data
that's it so we added the data optional
property
only for the Core Data model because
that's a detail of how we are storing
the data
with a Core Data implementation
so the FeedImage model stays intact
it doesn't need to know about this Core
Data implementation detail
that's why it's important to separate
models because every module
may change for different reasons the
Core Data module now
had to change to accommodate this new
requirement but the other modules don't
need to know about it
so we don't need to recompile redeploy
all the modules because of this change
exactly that's pretty important okay
let's have a look at the dependency
diagram now
so in the middle we have the Feature
abstractions
the FeedLoader protocol with the Remote
FeedLoader implementation and the Local
FeedLoader implementation
and we also moved the FeedImageData
Loader abstraction
the protocol to this Feed Feature module
and we implemented the RemoteFeedImage
DataLoader
that shares the same HTTPClient
abstraction
as the RemoteFeedLoader and we also
implemented
a LocalFeedImageDataLoader they also
talks to an abstraction
the FeedImageDataStore that is
implemented
by the CoreDataFeedStore and as you
can see the CoreDataFeedStore
class implements both the FeedStore and
the FeedImageDataStore
so different than the Feed API module
where we share the HTTPClient
between these two components in the
cache
module we do not share the same store
because they have completely different
interfaces because they don't share the
same operations
right so this is a prime example of the
ISP
the Interface Segregation Principle
although
both sets of behaviors have to do with
storing
data into the cache we are separating
them
into two protocols, yes because although
we are
storing data in both cases one we are
storing
the feed data and the other one we are
storing the feed image
data as we can see here the FeedStore
allows you to insert feed with a
timestamp
retrieve the feed and also delete the
cached feed
it's a very specialized interface for
the client
and the FeedImageDataStore only
expose the operations
the use case needs in this case
inserting the data for URL
and retrieving data for URL we don't
need to delete
for example exactly infrastructure
abstractions should have exactly what
the clients
need and in this case we just want to
insert
and retrieve that's it
if in the future we need to delete
inside the use case
we might add a delete method here but
only if required
by the client and that's it we have all
the implementations we need
now it's time to create the main iOS app
application awesome let's start by
creating a new project
let's select the iOS single view app
template
let's call it EssentialApp
okay there it is we don't want landscape
let's run and see if we have an empty
application
okay there it is an empty app
so let's commit
add empty EssentialApp project
that's it but all of our modules
are in a different project so we need to
combine
these two projects into a workspace yes
so the EssentialApp will depend
on the other modules and the way to do
it
is to drag an Xcode project into
another
so in this case we are going to drag the
EssentialFeed project
into the EssentialApp project then
Xcode is going to ask you
if you want to create a new workspace
because you cannot add
projects inside project but you can
create a workspace that combines
multiple projects that's it as you can
see in the same workspace we have
the EssentialFeed project and the
EssentialApp
project now in the EssentialApp project
we can add our modules as embedded
frameworks so we need to add the
EssentialFeed
and the EssentialFeediOS frameworks
that's it now from within the Essential
App project we have access
to the EssentialFeed components now we
can compose
all of them to run an application with
the EssentialFeed
awesome let's commit and start composing
our app
so create the EssentialApp workspace
combining
the EssentialApp and EssentialFeed
projects
that's it so let's compose
the feed into the application so we need
to import
the EssentialFeed and the Essential
Feed
iOS modules so let's create the
FeedViewController using the FeedUI
Composer
and here we need a FeedLoader and an
ImageLoader
so the ImageLoader let's use the Remote
Feed
ImageDataLoader yeah and we need a
client
okay and the FeedLoader is a Remote
FeedLoader that needs a URL
and a client so let's create the client
it's the URL
SessionHTTPClient that needs
a session let's create a session
which is a URLSession with
configuration
and let's use an ephemeral configuration
because we have our own caching
strategy awesome finally we need a URL
which in our case it's this long URL
alright now we need to put this on the
screen so let's put it
on the window as the root view
controller
let's run now
boom okay so the whole composition works
it loads the feed and the images
and as we scroll it loads the images
and pre-fetches the images as well yep
animation works as well
it's awesome but we are composing only
the remote side the Feed API module
with the user interface exactly but we
have the other side
that we like to compose as well so if
the internet connection
fails we can load data from the cache
exactly of course we can't do that yet
because we need a new type that composes
these two
and then inject this composite into the
Feed UI
exactly we need a component that
references
both the RemoteFeedLoader and the
LocalFeedLoader and
it contains the strategy for when to use
the remote and when to use the local
and the same thing for the FeedImage
DataLoader we need to compose
both the remote and the local one into a
new type
with the strategy to decide which one to
use
depending on the case so since we have a
good abstraction in between
those components we can add this
behavior
without having to change the remote
loaders or the local loaders
we can compose them differently with a
new type
and get different behaviors that's the
Open Closed
Principle exactly that's the power
of the Open Close Principle so that's it
the next step
is to create those strategies or those
composite types
fantastic this is going to be the topic
of the next lecture
we'll see you again next time bye y'all
see ya