Hello Mike, hey Caio
in this lecture you'll learn how to
compose
objects that share a common interface
with the Composite design pattern
okay so the goal is to compose both the
remote
and LocalFeedLoader and the logic
is try to load from remote first
if it fails try to load from local
that's it
and they both share a common interface
the FeedLoader protocol that they both
implement
and the idea is to create a new component
that share the same interface
with the logic we want but the clients
don't need to know about the composite
they're going to treat
this composition uniformly as a Feed
Loader with the common FeedLoader
interface exactly
and the same thing for the FeedImage
DataLoader
with the difference that we probably
want to first
check if we have an image locally before
loading it from remote right so it's the
inverse logic basically
exactly because images are quite
expensive to download
so try to load an image from the local
store if it fails
you go to remote but the idea is that
they also
both share a common interface and we can
create a composite
they also implement the interface so
clients don't need to know about the
composition
they can treat the whole composite
uniformly
with the FeedImageDataLoader protocol
exactly so let's start with the Feed
Loader
we need to load from remote and if it
fails
it loads from local okay as always
let's start with a test alright so
let's create
a RemoteWithLocal
FallbackFeedLoaderTests
and as you said we want to deliver a
remote feed
when the remote loading succeeds first
okay
so first test when we try to load from
the composite
it should deliver the remote feed if it
succeeds
to load from remote and so far we've
been testing our components
with spies but this time let's try
a different kind of test double a stub
okay so let's create our assertion
so we expect to load a feed so let's
have a received feed and we're going to
be comparing it
with a stubbed result let's call it
remoteFeed okay so
the received feed should be the same
stubbed
remote feed exactly so to capture
the received feed we need to first
invoke load
in the system under test the sut and we
get a result back
and to capture the received feed from
the result
we need an external property a variable
of type array of FeedImage because
that's the feed
a feed is an array of feed images okay
and here we can capture the received
feed so if we get a success
with the feed we can capture a received
feed then
we can assert it is exactly the same
as the stubbed remote feed exactly and
if it fails
we want to fail with a message expected
successful load feed result
got result instead that's it
and since we have the fail assertion in
the switch statement
we can move the assert equal statement
in the switch statement as well
yeah let's just rename the feed and we
don't need this external
variable that's it but since we are not
capturing a value of course now we need
an expectation
so we can fulfill it here and wait
for the expectation with a timeout thus
we are sure at the end of the test
that the closure was executed otherwise
we're going to get
a failure exactly finally
let's instantiate our system under test
which is going to be a RemoteWithLocal
Fallback
FeedLoader so we need to start with a
remote
loader and a local loader
so next step we need to create our type
the RemoteWithLocal
FallbackFeedLoader okay and here we
get the RemoteFeedLoader and the Local
FeedLoader
as dependencies so we need to import
EssentialFeed because
that's where the RemoteFeedLoader and
the LocalFeedLoader live
exactly so we are passing the concrete
types here
the concrete RemoteFeedLoader
and the concrete LocalFeedLoader
so we need to create our remote loader
which is the concrete
RemoteFeedLoader but now we need to
create the dependencies
for the RemoteFeedLoader it needs a
URL and a client so we need to create a
URL
now we need to create a client now which
client should we create
we don't want to use the real HTTP
Client
and actually perform a request exactly
we have already tested the RemoteFeed
Loader
and we don't want to test again exactly
we want to test the RemoteWithLocal
FallbackFeedLoader
in isolation so in the future
if the RemoteFeedLoader needs more
dependencies
I don't want to break this test yes
exactly if for example we want to add
any kind of access token dependency to
the RemoteFeedLoader
we would break this test we need to come
here and give a mock
token even though this test doesn't care
about access tokens
so every time we change the RemoteFeed
Loader or the LocalFeedLoader that has
its own dependencies as well
we might break this test that is
completely unrelated
and that's why we need to test against
abstractions
rather than concrete types otherwise we
end up with integration tests
exactly sure they have their value but
it's not what we want in this case yes
we are testing the RemoteWithLocal
FallbackFeedLoader at the unit level
thus we do not want concrete details
that can break this test
in the future we want to test against
abstractions
to test this component in isolation
exactly
and we have an abstraction already the
FeedLoader
protocol
so we don't need to expose the concrete
types here
we can just use the abstraction the
protocol that's it
now we don't need to use the real Remote
FeedLoader
while testing instead we can create
a stub or a spy or a mock
this way we protect this test from
future changes
we are testing the RemoteWithLocal
FallbackFeedLoader
in isolation yeah but there is another
problem now
we can get the order of the parameters
remote and local wrong and the compiler
will not help us it will not guide us as
to what is what
right so this is clearly the wrong
order but the compiler is just fine with
it
because we are using the abstraction
here not the concrete type
yes exactly and what do you do
when you don't have compile time
guarantees
you write tests exactly and that's
exactly what we're doing we are writing
tests
so tests can guarantee the correct order
because you're testing the behavior
if you mess up the order the behavior
will be wrong
that's it so it's a trade-off here we
could go
with the concrete types but then our
test will be
tied to concrete types and every time
those concrete types change
we break those tests and if we go with
the abstractions
we may lose a little bit of compile time
guarantees
but since we have tests I'm happy with
it yes
exactly we could also create specific
abstractions
denoting the remote and local
provenance of the feed right we could
create a RemoteFeedLoader protocol
that inherits from the FeedLoader
protocol exactly and could create a
local
FeedLoader protocol they also inherit
from the FeedLoader protocol
and we could annotate this here that's
it
so now you get back compile time
guarantees and we could create
two types of stubs the RemoteLoader
Stub
and the LocalLoaderStub one that
implements the RemoteFeedLoader
and other one that implements the Local
FeedLoader
yes now the compiler is going to tell us
the order is wrong
and we have to fix it there you go
yes so this solution solves
the concrete implementation problem it
also
solves the order yes now
we have these types just to annotate
that these two components are different
components
and we can make the concrete types
implement
those protocols with extensions
so the concrete type is in the Essential
Feed module so we need to
add the module name EssentialFeed.
Remote
FeedLoader when we mention the concrete
type
and we can make it implement the Remote
FeedLoader protocol
that's it you can do the same thing with
the Local one
and that's it now you are back with the
compile time safeties
and as you can see they have the same
name as the concrete types the Remote
FeedLoader and LocalFeedLoader
but since they are in different modules
we don't have naming collisions
I just don't think we need it because we
have tests
yes but it's nice to know that you can
use this technique
to have type annotations so we can catch
mistakes
with the help of the compiler but since
we are following TDD
I am happy to go with the simpler
solution and just use the abstraction
here
what do you think agreed I think it
gives us
much more freedom than creating new
types
and we have less components at the same
time
exactly less components means less code
less complexity
simpler yep and since we don't have
the compiler guarantees anymore I would
even want to rename
those properties yes because there is no
remote anymore there is no local anymore
these notions went away when the
concrete types went away
exactly which means we have much more
flexibility now
with the abstractions what we have here
actually
is a primary loader with a
fallback loader that's it
which means we have a primary loader
instance
and a fallback loader instance
by using abstractions we make our code
more flexible by naming things
differently we also make our code more
flexible
that's why naming is so important
exactly
so why don't we rename the class as well
so it's not a RemoteWithLocalFallback
anymore
it's much more abstract than that we can
compose
any kind of FeedLoader and give it a
fallback
so a good name could be FeedLoader
WithFallback and as we said this is a
composite so I'm happy to add
as a suffix Composite, FeedLoader
WithFallbackComposite that's it
look at that now instead of tying our
implementation to
concrete types we have a much more
flexible
composite that can compose any Feed
Loader
with another FeedLoader as a fallback
exactly
it's pretty powerful so let's also
rename the test
alright FeedLoaderWithFallback
CompositeTests
and also let's rename the remoteFeed
property
because this is a primary feed now and
let's
rename the test deliver
a primary feed on primary loader
success that's it now back to the test
the compiler is still complaining that
we don't have a load method
in the system under test because we need
to conform to FeedLoader
and implement the load method okay
and finally we need to create the
primary feed
which is an array of FeedImages
which can be any unique feed
because we also will need a fallback
feed to make sure we got the primary
feed instead of the fallback feed
we need to create unique values because
they are the stubbed
result we will use in the LoaderStub
that's the predefined value that's it
so let's implement the unique feed which
is simply creating
a unique feed and the UUID
makes it unique in our LoaderStub
needs a result so every time we call
load we complete
with the stubbed result that's it and
that's the difference
when we use stubs you set the values up
front
and with a spy you capture the values so
you can use it
later exactly so stubs are much simpler
but less precise about what happens
during tests
that's why they are more flexible
now let's run the tests and we should
see a failure because we never complete
the load so the expectation should not
be fulfilled
there it is unfulfilled expectation we
never
executed the load completion fantastic
let's implement the load method to make
the test pass
so we need to load from the primary
source from the primary
loader which means we need to capture
the primary
FeedLoader now we can load
and for now we can just pass the
completion just forwarding the message
that's it now the test should pass
and it does okay so that's what a stub
does
we set up the primary loader to succeed
with a primary feed
and a fallback loader to succeed with a
fallback feed
and we expect our composite to complete
with the primary feed
proving that it loaded it from the
primary loader
fantastic let's commit
FeedLoaderWithFallbackComposite
delivers
primary feed on primary loader success
that's it so stubs are very simple and
very useful
but we had to make a lot of upfront
decisions
when you have a simple use case stubs
are much more flexible
so I'm happy with it yes we can go with
it for this
test case okay but before we carry on
let's create our makeSUT factory method
okay so we can create our primary loader
and fallback loader
in here and simplify a little bit the
instantiation
here so we make the sut with the primary
result
and a fallback result that's it let's
commit
extract system under test creation into
a factory
method now the next test
so if the primary loader succeeds we
just complete with the primary
feed but what happens if the primary
loader
fails then we need to deliver the
fallback
feed exactly that's the strategy here
so that's the next test so we create the
sut
with the primary result of a failure and
a fallback result
as a success the fallback feed
and we expect to receive success
with the fallback feed which is
different from the first test where we
expected the primary feed
in case of failure again we have a nice
assertion
to help us identify the issue
let's create the anyNSError factory
helper
just create a simple error
and let's run the test should fail
there you go expect a successful load
feed result
got failure okay let's go back to
production
so now we need the fallback loader
yes and it's time to unwrap the primary
loading
completion because we need to examine
the result
exactly if it is success
we simply complete with the result
that's it
now if it's a failure we load
from the fallback but of course
let's weakify self here
let's run the test
now it's passing let's commit
FeedLoaderWithFallbackComposite
delivers
fallback feed on primary loader failure
that's it it's time to remove some
duplication
exactly look at this expectation wait
load, expectation
wait load as always you can go into
a helper that creates a reusable
way of loading and asserting the
received values
and now we can simplify this logic we
expect
sut to complete with success
fallback feed look at that adding the
first one
we expect sut to complete with
success primary feed so that's it
if there is a primary successful result
we expect
to get the primary successful result if
the primary result
is failure and the fallback is a success
we expect to get a successful fallback
result
that's it awesome let's run the tests
passing let's commit
extract duplicate load logic into a
helper
method that's it
now what happens if both fail
so it should deliver an error it should
deliver an error
exactly so delivers error on both
primary and fallback loader failure
so we stub both loaders to fail
and we expect our system under test to
complete
also with a failure that's it
passing fantastic let's commit
so delivers error on both primary
and fallback failure okay
and that's it that's all that's how
simple
it is but how powerful this composite is
we can compose infinitely FeedLoaders
with a fallback because we can compose
composites as well because the composite
implements the same
interface the same protocol we can
compose composites exactly
as we said it's pretty powerful and we
keep the clients
and the FeedLoader implementations
agnostic
of fallbacks agnostic of other concrete
types
we have ultimate freedom to compose
FeedLoaders
in any way we want if you want to load
first from the local loader
and then from the remote we can compose
them like this
if you want to load first from remote we
can also compose it like this
awesome let's move the FeedLoader with
FallbackComposite to production
and now we need to deal with access
control so this is a public type
so that test has access to it
and the tests don't have access to this
type yet because we need to import
the module where this type is which is
not the EssentialFeed
it's the EssentialApp
okay let's run the tests
fantastic it's passing awesome
let's commit so
move FeedLoaderWithFallbackComposite
to production
okay and we need to do the same thing
for the FeedImageDataLoader protocol
we want to be able to compose image data
loaders
with fallbacks but since it's very
similar we're going to do it off camera
and we believe you should implement it
yourself to practice how to create
composites
and here it is the FeedImageData
Loader
WithFallbackComposite also using
abstractions
the FeedImageDataLoader protocol thus
we can compose
any data loader with a fallback and
compose
composites as well exactly
so in the load image data we create a
task wrapper
we start loading the image data from the
primary loader
and we hold a reference to the task so
if we cancel
the operation at this stage we cancel
the primary
load image data then again if we get
success
we complete with result if it fails
we try to load the image data from the
fallback data loader and now we hold a
reference
to the fallback task so if we cancel
during a fallback load we cancel the
fallback load
that's it as simple as that and we can
reuse these
infinitely awesome and as you said
it's up to whoever composes this type to
compose it accordingly with the primary
and fallback sources and this can scale
infinitely
that's it so let's see it in action
let's create our RemoteFeedLoader and
ImageLoader with the URLSession client
and also let's create a LocalImage
Loader in a LocalFeedLoader
with the local CoreDataStore
and now we can compose them using the
composite
so the FeedLoader is the FeedLoader
WithFallbackComposite
where the primary loader is the Remote
FeedLoader and the fallback is the Local
FeedLoader that's it and the image
loader
is the FeedImageDataLoaderWith
FallbackComposite
where the primary source is the local
image loader and the fallback is the
remote
image loader okay the opposite here
but we could invert it freely as needed
we can even have another composite there
loading from an in-memory cache before
going
directly to the persistent store exactly
the fallback for the FeedLoader for
example could be another composite
where the primary could be an in-memory
store
with a fallback if it fails of a local
FeedLoader so we can compose the
composites
yes infinitely and look how nicely the
nested code represents the steps of the
algorithm here
the primary step and the fallback step
which has a primary
and a fallback again that's it it's
beautiful
so let's go back RemoteFeedLoader has
primary
and the LocalFeedLoader as a fallback
let's run the application
and it works there you go awesome
you can even implement a retry strategy
with this composite
for example if you want to retry twice
the remote loader
before going to the fallback you can
create a composite
with the primary as the RemoteFeed
Loader
and the fallback of the LocalFeedLoader
so now it's going to try
to load from remote fallback is going to
try to load from remote again
and then it's going to go for the
fallback how awesome is that no counters
needed
no state, nothing and that's it you can
keep composing these things infinitely
as much as you want and when you need
this kind of freedom
in this kind of composability that's a
great way of doing it
awesome so that's it at the end
we created a much more flexible
composite
simple yet powerful we could go with the
concrete types
but again we would tie our test code
with concrete implementations
so we would end up with integration
tests that are fragile
it's much better to test things in
isolation at the unit level
and then you test things in integration
at a higher level
we also demonstrated how to test things
with a stub as you saw
all these options have merits but they
also have
their disadvantages nothing is perfect
the more techniques you know the more
options you have to solve different
problems exactly it's all about managing
the trade-offs
that's it okay and let's set up the CI
pipeline
exactly now that we have a new project
we need to add it to the CI pipeline
what we can do here is to migrate our
CI_iOS
to the workspace so let's select the
workspace as the container
for the CI_iOS scheme
let's select the test configuration
let's add
the EssentialAppTests target let's
randomize
the execution order as always
let's include the EssentialApp target
for gathering coverage
okay let's update the CI configuration
file
okay so now we're not using a project
anymore for the CI_iOS scheme
it's a workspace in the workspace is the
EssentialApp
xcworkspace
okay let's have a look at the dependency
diagram
that's it we have two new types the
composite
that implements the FeedLoader and
composes any type of FeedLoader with a
fallback
and a FeedImageDataLoader with
FallbackComposite
that implements the FeedImageData
Loader protocol and composes
other types that implement the Feed
ImageDataLoader with
a fallback there you have it no more
arrows to concrete types, so that's it
for this lecture
okay a long one but an extremely
important one
we'll see you again next time bye y'all
see ya