Hello Mike, hey Caio in the previous
lecture we created
the loader composites to compose the
Remote
with the LocalFeedLoader or any kind
of FeedLoader
so we can load from a primary loader in
this case
remotely and the fallback is the local
cache
but we never add anything to the cache
exactly we do not save the feed
thus if it fails to load from remote it
will never load anything from the cache
it would always be empty that is correct
and that's because we are separating
queries
from commands so loading is a query
exactly whilst saving implies
side-effects because it mutates the
state
exactly so we don't want the load
operation
to perform mutation or change the system
state
but we want to compose loading with
saving so every time we load something
from remote
we can save it to the local cache or to
an in-memory cache or to any kind of
cache we can create
to fulfill our use case okay
so we're talking about intercepting
the loading here and injecting
the side-effects of saving in the
composition
exactly and we have already implemented
the use case for saving so all we need
to do
is compose it with a loading
exactly the LocalFeedLoader holds the
implementation
for the cache logic yes so we need to
compose
the remote load with the LocalFeed
Loader
save operation exactly but we don't want
the RemoteFeedLoader knowing about the
LocalFeedLoader
to respect modularity they should not
know about other concrete components
exactly so we could do this at the
composite
level for example we could make the
fallback
be the concrete LocalFeedLoader
and we could perform the side-effect
here
so we could save the feed we get in a
successful load
right but now our composite
would not be very composable yes
because it can only compose a concrete
LocalFeedLoader
exactly so that's a solution but not a
very composable solution
so let's try something else another
solution would be to add
a save method to the FeedLoader
protocol
but again a FeedLoader should only load
exactly because not every FeedLoader
is capable of saving for example
the RemoteFeedLoader would not be able
to save
by adding this save function in the
FeedLoader protocol
we are violating the ISP the Interface
Segregation Principle
and potentially the LSP the Liskov
Substitution Principle
exactly so another thing we can do is to
create a new type
that intercepts the load and injects the
mutation side-effect
in the composition so in other words
we'll be intercepting FeedLoaders and
adding
a new behavior into it
and how do you add behavior to an
existing type
without altering that type
by decorating it right so we need
a Decorator awesome
so the goal for this lecture is to
intercept the load
of the remote loaders and when we get a
successful result
we save it and we're going to add this
behavior
with a decorator as always let's start
with the test
so this new type will decorate the Feed
Loader protocol
by adding the save functionality to it
so let's call it
FeedLoaderCacheDecorator
so the FeedLoaderCacheDecorator will
also be
a FeedLoader it will implement the Feed
Loader protocol
like any other decorator it maintains
the same
interface as the decoratee and we want
to maintain the same load behavior
but inject the save operation that
mutates the system
so let's start by testing that the
decorator maintains the same
load behavior as the decoratee
so the expectation is that the system
under test
should complete with a successful feed
when the decorated loader succeeds
with the given feed so we're just
testing that
we maintain the same loading behavior by
decorating
the loader and we can use the same
helpers
from the previous lecture we just need
to import
EssentialFeed okay
now let's create our new type the
FeedLoaderCacheDecorator
so the FeedLoaderCacheDecorator is a
FeedLoader
and you instantiate it with another
loader which is the decoratee
the loader we are decorating and step by
step
we are going to inject the save
operation
into it fantastic let's run the test
first
it should fail because we have no
behavior implemented
yet failing okay
to make it pass we need to forward the
message
to the decoratee proving that we are
maintaining the same load behavior
let's run the test again passing okay
so our test is only checking for the
success behavior what about the error
case
exactly we can increase the coverage by
adding a test that also checks
what happens in the failure case so if
the decorated loader
fails the decorator should also forward
the error
proving that it maintains the same load
behavior
and it should pass because we are
forwarding the message
let's run the tests passing okay
let's commit so FeedLoaderCache
Decorator
delivers the decoratee loader result
that's right for both cases either
success or failure
that's it but now we have duplication
as this loader is exactly the same as
the one created in the previous lecture
for the FeedLoader composite okay we can
extract that
in a test helper okay so since this is
going to
a shared scope let's give it a better
name this is a
FeedLoaderStub because it implements
the FeedLoader protocol
and let's move it to the helpers folder
and we can reuse it in the composite
tests
let's just rename this to facilitate
now we can delete run the tests
passing okay let's commit
extract FeedLoaderStub into a shared
scope
to remove duplication
you can also move the unique feed
factory method
to the shared test helpers let's make it
internal now
okay let's import the EssentialFeed
module and we can reuse it
in both tests let's run the test
passing so extract
unique feed factory helper into a shared
scope to remove duplication
and finally we can also reuse the expect
helper method okay but the expect method
is using XCTest instance methods
exactly the expectation and the wait
belong to XCTestCase instances
so we can move it to an extension
of the XCTestCase class so
XCTestCase+FeedLoader
okay so let's move this to an extension
of the XCTestCase class
but it should not be private yeah we
also need the EssentialFeed
okay and now we can reuse this helper in
both the composite and the decorator
tests
let's run the tests
passing awesome however now
every XCTestCase instance have
access to this method even the ones that
don't care about
the FeedLoader protocol so we are
exposing methods that are not
necessary for all XCTestCases and
that's not ideal
right so we want multiple XCTestCase
to have access to this method but only
the ones that care about
the FeedLoader protocol so one way to
do it is to
create a subclass of XCTestCase
like a FeedLoaderTestCase
and then we add the extension only for
that
class type and we need to make our tests
be a subtype of FeedLoaderTestCase
that works but the problem is that in
the future we might want to compose
this class with other operations
that can be reusable
but you can only inherit from one class
so
class inheritance is not composable you
can only inherit from one class
yes however there is another solution
and that is
to use protocols and protocol extensions
exactly a class can conform to
many protocols and inherit
implementations from their extensions
and you can constrain a protocol to a
specific class
so this protocol is composable but can
only be inherited by
XCTestCase subtypes exactly
that's a very nice Swift feature that
allows us to do so
that's it so our test cases need to
inherit from XCTestCase again
but they also get the protocol
extensions
because they conform to the FeedLoader
TestCase protocol
so that's why protocols in Swift compose
much better than classes
you can confirm through multiple
protocols and inherit all of their
extensions awesome let's run the tests
it's passing so we eliminated all the
duplication
yes quite important frankly you don't
want to skip the refactoring phase
you need to remove duplication both from
the production
and the test side, exactly so let's commit
extract FeedLoader test helpers into a
shared protocol extension
to remove duplication
and as always before we carry on let's
create the makeSUT
factory method to remove more
duplication
let's run the tests it's passing
so don't forget keep refactoring
production and test code
want both to be clean let's commit
extract this sut creation into a factory
method
that's it okay so our test so far
just proves that the cache decorator is
a FeedLoader
and it maintains the loading logic of
the decoratee
now it's time to test the actual
mutation side-effect
the saving operation okay
so load caches loaded feed
on loader success and to cache the
loaded result
we're gonna need the new component
responsible
for caching and we can call it
cache and we want to assert that
after loading successfully the cache
received a save message
exactly this is important because
the decorator doesn't cache the decorator
coordinates the loading and the caching
exactly it intercepts the load and on
success it needs to send a message
to the cache to save the loaded feed
that's it
but during tests we're not gonna use a
real cache we are using
a spy here that will capture all the
received messages
and at the end of this test we want to
assert that we received the save
message with the given feed and when
should this happen
after loading a successful result
that's it so we stub the loader result
with a successful feed
the same feed we expect to be saved in
the cache
so we need to create a CacheSpy to use
during tests
and we need to pass a cache to the make
sut
and since we don't want to break the
other tests let's give a default value
now we can pass the cache to the
decorator
and now we need to think what kind of
cache do we want here
do we want the LocalFeedLoader that
implements the cache use case
right we could but we don't want that
and that's because the local FeedLoader
is a concrete type
and it has dependencies so we would have
to create
all these dependencies inside our test
and if one of those dependencies changed
it would break our tests, so we could test
this decorator
integration with the LocalFeedLoader
concrete class
but our tests would be more fragile and
this decorator would be
less composable we want to test the
decorator
in isolation and we want to have an
abstraction
that also allows more composability
exactly just like we have the Feed
Loader abstraction
for loading we can have a new
abstraction
for saving we can call it a FeedSaver
or a FeedCache yeah I like FeedCache
alright and which methods the Feed
Cache
should have so the FeedCache is an
abstraction for the cache use case
and we already have an implementation
the save method
so that's the interface we want
we want a save method where we pass a
feed
which is an array of FeedImages and a
completion
closure with the Result type which is
either
success Void or an Error
okay so the spy needs to conform to
FeedCache
otherwise it's not going to compile okay
and the implementation for the spy is
simply to
capture the message that's it let's run
the tests
and it should fail because we are not
performing the save operation yet
fantastic failed the cache did not
receive
the save message so let's implement it
so now when we load the result
from the decoratee loader
we need to cache a successful result
otherwise let's just pass an empty array
for now
okay just to satisfy the compiler and of
course
forward the completion
let's capture the cache in a property
and let's run the tests
alright passing fantastic
let's commit so the FeedLoaderCache
Decorator
caches the loaded feed on loader success
that's it and we also need
a case on a loader failure
exactly so load
does not cache on loader failure we
should only mutate the system state
on success so again we create a cache
we stub a loader failure we execute the
load
operation and we expect no messages
in the failure case let's run the tests
okay it failed because we are
saving regardless yes in the failure
case
we are just saving an empty feed that's
not what we want
let's use an if let instead if we can
get the feed
out of the result then we cache it
only in the success case let's run the
tests
passing let's commit
FeedLoaderCacheDecorator does not
cache feed on loader
failure any refactorings we can do here
yeah we could eliminate the if statement
and use a map instead okay
if you really don't like if statements
you can use a map
so we map the result which is only
called
in the case of a successful result
and we can add the side-effect here save
feed
and we return the feed to maintain the
same
Result type that's it
okay test passing
if you want eliminate if statements from
your code that's one way of doing it
let's commit replace if try statement
with map but if you prefer if try
statement
that's fine as well what is important is
that the behavior is correct
and the tests are passing exactly
and we are done that's all the decorator
needs to do
it just injects the save operation
into the decorated loader
so the loader doesn't need to know about
saving or caching
and the cache doesn't need to know about
loading our composites are
still composable they don't depend on
concrete types
and the decorator is also composable
because we are depending on abstractions
look how simple those tests are that's
all we need
that's it let's move the type's
production now
okay where should we move the FeedCache
the abstraction
so I think the FeedCache can go close to
the FeedLoader
it does not depend on any other module
alright so the FeedLoader is in the
Feed Feature
so that looks like a good place to add
the FeedCache
so it's a public protocol because it's
implemented by other modules
yes let's run the tests
still passing let's commit
move FeedCache to the Feed Feature
production group
okay and we can also make the Local
FeedLoader implement the FeedCache
abstraction because it does implemented
the FeedCache
abstraction already the cache use case
yes exactly that's it run the test again
it's passing let's commit
make the LocalFeedLoader implement the
FeedCache protocol
so we can be composed with the
decorators awesome
alright should also move
the cache decorator to production in the
EssentialApp module
for now
so it's going to be public the
initializer
is public and the load function is
public
but the dependencies are private
okay so since we moved it to the
EssentialApp
module we need to import the Essential
App
module let's run the test again
passing let's commit
move FeedLoaderCacheDecorator to
production
any refactorings here looks pretty
clean to me
let's check the production side as well
looks good
apart from this closure here
we don't care about the result of the
save there's nothing this decorator can
do
when the save fails right
we are ignoring the error but for a
reader of the code
it's not very clear why so why don't we
create an extension instead
to clarify that that's what we're doing
we are ignoring
the result so save
ignoring result
so this is called as documentation yes
we don't need this method but it
clarifies
our intent we want to ignore the result
we don't care about the result I'm a big
fan of this
because it makes the code so much more
readable
especially when you come back
later exactly otherwise you might think
it was a mistake
not to handle the result exactly
you are making a little gift to your
future self
or to others if you're working in a team
that's it
let's run the tests passing
okay let's commit so create
saveIgnoringResult method to clarify
intent okay and that's it for the
FeedLoaderCacheDecorator
and you should do exactly the same for
the FeedImageDataLoader
exactly so again you can couple your
modules
and add this side-effect into the
concrete types or you can
follow the command query separation and
separate loading from saving
and then compose these functions it's a
choice
and you as the engineer you're supposed to
make this decision
when to use one or when to use the other
if you need modularity
you can decorate and compose your
components
when you don't need it a simple use case
maybe you can go to the more concrete
monolith approach okay
so let's compose our types and see what
it looks like
so every time we load from remote we
want to save
the received feed into the LocalFeed
Loader
that's it so we need to decorate
the RemoteFeedLoader with the Local
FeedLoader as the cache exactly
and that's it let's run the app and see
if it works
okay it's loading so we got this feed
from remote
and we expect it to have cached into the
local loader
so let's also compose the remote image
loader
but this time with the FeedImageData
LoaderCacheDecorator
so we are decorating the remote image
loader with
the local image loader as the cache
let's run the application
still working so we are saving the
result
of the RemoteFeedLoader into the Local
FeedLoader
and the result of the remote image
loader into the local image loader
and to prove this since we already
cached the result of this remote request
we can stop running the app and we can
run the application again
by composing only with the local loaders
so if the cache succeeded by running the
application with the local loaders
should show
the cached data there it is
awesome so that's it when you want to
add
a new behavior to a type without
changing it
you use a decorator when you want to
compose
types that conform to a common interface
you use
composites so let's have a look at the
diagram
with the decorators we introduced the
FeedCache
abstraction that the LocalFeedLoader
implements just like the LocalFeed
Loader also implements the FeedLoader
and we could break this down into two
components in the future one that
implements the FeedCache and one that
implements the FeedLoader
and the decorators decorate any
implementation of the FeedLoader
with any implementation of the FeedCache
on the image loading side we added the
FeedImageDataCache protocol
that the LocalFeedImageDataLoader
implements just like it implements
the FeedImageDataLoader and we could
break this down into two components in
the future
and the FeedImageDataLoaderCache
Decorator decorates
any FeedImageDataLoader by adding the
save functionality
of any FeedImageDataCache
so this code is super composable and
when you need this kind of composability
that's how you do it that's it and the
downside is that
your composition may start getting more
complex
that's why you also should test the
whole composition
to prove the types are composed
correctly
exactly this is going to be the topic of
the next lecture
we'll see you all next time bye y'all
see ya