Hello Mike, hey Caio in the previous
lecture we finished composing the
application
and we proved that it works by running
the app
but we have no automated tests to prove
that this composition
works right so although we can run the
app
and see it working we want to automate
some checks
and there are many ways we can do that
we can do it with unit tests with
integration tests
and even higher level tests that go
through the UI
and we can follow our BDD specs
right as acceptance criteria
exactly just very high-level tests
proving that we fulfill all the
acceptance criteria
so we have the online customer and the
offline customer
and we can use UI tests going through
the user interface
to test the app composition okay so
we're going to be testing the
application from a higher level
like a black-box exactly
and as always let's start with a test
first so I'm going to discard the
changes in the Scene
Delegate because we're going to test
drive this composition now
so we need to create a new test target
it's an iOS target and we can use the UI
Testing Bundle template
let's call it EssentialAppUI
AcceptanceTests okay
make sure the target application is
correct we are testing the EssentialApp
application and also let's configure our
schemes
first of all the UI tests that we
created to test the EssentialApp
was added to the EssentialApp scheme
which means every time we run the
EssentialApp tests it's going to run
the unit tests and the UI tests but we
don't want that
we want to be able to run the unit tests
in isolation
because they're much more reliable and
fast and we'll be running it
very often but UI tests are usually slow
so we're going to run them less often
exactly
when we hit Command+U we just want some
blazing fast tests to run
exactly just the unit tests so let's
remove
the UI tests from the EssentialApp
scheme
let's go to manage schemes and let's add
a new one
for the UI tests so we can run the UI
tests
in isolation yeah I like that it's much
cleaner
let's move it to the workspace container
alright now let's configure the CI_iOS
let's add the UI tests so it also runs
in the CI server let's randomize to make
sure
there is no order dependency between the
tests
every test should be independent and
that's it
okay we're good to go let's commit
so add UI test target for running
high-level acceptance tests that's it
and let's add our first test so first
test
from the acceptance criteria on launch
it should display
the remote feed when the customer has
connectivity
so we're going to be running the app
we're going to launch the app we want to
make sure that we loaded the feed
how can we do that well we get a JSON
back
in the current remote feed with a couple
of items
and if I count the number of items we
have
22 images so we could just check that we
22 cells okay so we can
check against the cells count yes if we
have 22 cells it means that
we loaded the 22 images from remote
so app cells count should be
22 when
we launch the app
that's it so with this test we can
guarantee that
we loaded the feed with 22 cells but we
don't prove that we loaded
the images for each feed item
yes we just prove the cell count
so we could also check
for the images count okay but the
problem is that the images are inside
the cells and with UI tests we can query
how many cells we have on the screen
even though the cells
are off screen the problem is that the
images are inside cells
and you cannot count items like images
inside a cell
that are not on screen so if we check
the image count
we can only count the ones that are on
screen which in this case will be only
right and on a smaller screen size
device
it could be even 1 yes so maybe let's
just make sure that we loaded at least
1 image
so we can get the first cell and make
sure
it has 1 image okay this way we can
test that
we are loading the feed with 22 images
and we load at least
the first image for the first feed item
so let's run this test and it should
fail let's select the right scheme
EssentialAppUIAcceptanceTests and
let's run it
so this UI test is gonna actually run
our application
and investigate things on the screen
as you can see we loaded an empty
application
and of course it couldn't find the cells
or the first image
okay let's implement the SceneDelegate so
let's import
the EssentialFeed and the Essential
FeediOS
let's just add the code to make this
test pass
we need the RemoteFeedLoader for loading
the feed from remote
and an image loader for loading the
image exactly
the current test doesn't mention any
local or cached feed
so let's run it it's going to run the
app again
but this time it loads the cells and
loads the image
passing ok let's commit
displays remote feed on launch when
customer has connectivity
that's it okay so this is working but
it's a bit fragile because
we may add more cells to this
application there are not actually
feed image cells right so just counting
any cell is not a good way of asserting
those values
so we could use an identifier to
identify the correct cells
we really want to count so we can find
cells with a specific identifier
feed image cells and then we count only
the cells that match this identifier and
should be
22 and then we can do the same for the
image
we get the first image with identifier
feed
image view and then we just need to make
sure that
it exists let's run again and it should
fail now because we don't have
such identifiers in our views
failed okay so let's set
the identifiers and we can do it in the
storyboard
or if you're using code you can do it in
code as well
so let's select the cell let's add the
identifier
feed-image-cell let's select
the image and let's set feed-image-
view identifier go back to the tests
run the test again
passing so now we are proving that we
are loading 22
feed image cells and then we load at
least
one feed image which means we are
testing the
remote feed loader and the remote
feed image data loader okay
quite an improvement so let's commit
so improve coverage by using identifiers
for finding the feed image
cells so that's it
for the online scenario when the
customer has connectivity
now what happens when you don't have
connectivity
we have two branches if you have
something in the cache
it should show the cached feed otherwise
show an empty feed so the first one
on launch should display the cached feed
when the customer has no connectivity so
this is the scenario where you have a
cached feed
but no connectivity how can we simulate
this scenario
well first we need to load something
into the cache
and to load something we need
connectivity so we can launch the app
with connectivity which should load and
cache the items
then we can launch the app again but in
this case we need to control
if we have connectivity or not we need
an offline
application and there's no easy way of
doing this with blackbox UI testing
but we can pass launch arguments to the
application
so in this case we are going to pass a
connectivity argument with the value
offline and then we can check that we
should have
22 cached feed cells on screen
and that it loads the image as well so
we are testing
that we are composing the remote feed
loader with the local feed loader
and the remote feed image data loader
with the local feed image data loader
but for this to work we need to control
the connectivity
state of the app okay based on the
launch arguments
yes in our SceneDelegate can create a
function
makeRemoteClient so if we get
a connectivity value and it's offline
we can use an always failing HTTPClient
for example
that fakes the offline state of the
application
okay otherwise it just uses the real one
and we can use this very handy
functionality of UserDefaults
they can read the launch arguments for
us and convert
to strings booleans integers and etc so
in this case we want to string
connectivity and if it's offline we
return this AlwaysFailingHTTPClient
which is a very simple implementation
it's an HTTPClient
that always fails instantly that's it so
if we pass the
offline connectivity flag we can fake an
offline
application let's run the tests and it
should fail
because we're not handling the cache yet
there it is there was nothing in the
cache
so there were 0 cells when we
expected 22
now to make this pass we need to compose
the remote with the local
loaders let's import Core Data
let's instantiate the local loaders
and now can compose them as before
let's run the test again
okay it's passing so we are controlling
the connectivity
state of the application yeah this is
important to understand
by launching an offline application
it means that we already have cached
the feed from the online version
of the application that's it
there are two steps for this test we
launch it with connectivity and we
launch again with no connectivity
we expect to have cached the results we
got from the online application and
display it
from the cache in the offline
application awesome
and those are very high-level tests only
testing
the least amount of details possible the
more details you are testing high-level
tests
the more fragile and slow it is
so you want to limit that and since we
already tested details in isolation
in unit tests let's focus only in the
high-level
details awesome let's commit
so displays cached feed on launch when
customer has no connectivity
that's it so what happens if the
and no cache okay so in this case we
should display
an empty feed so on launch displays
empty feed when customer has no
connectivity and no cache
so if we load the application with
offline connectivity
we should have 0 cells because we
didn't launch the app before as we did
here
with connectivity thus it should have
nothing
in the cache let's run the test
and it fails so we expected to have
0 cells but we have 22
and that's because we loaded previously
in other tests right
so one of those tests added something to
the cache
and this is persisted in the application
across
launches so those tests are not
independent
a previous test changes the result
of another test and this is dangerous we
want our tests to be independent
so they can run on their own or in any
order otherwise they are flaky
they are fragile every test should be
independent
yes that's the very definition of side
effects here one test
affects the execution and the result of
another test
exactly so we need to reset the state
for this test we can do it by passing
another flag
and that's one of the downsides of UI
tests it is very stateful it has
loads of side-effects the persist across
application
runs every time you launch the app you
might have
state from a previous test and we need
to give some directive
so the application can clean its state
for us
because from the point of view of the UI
tests we don't have access to any
internal details of the application
that's why it's called black-box testing
exactly
you only access it from the outside as
the customer would
so if we pass a reset launch argument
we can investigate that in our Scene
Delegate
so if CommandLine arguments
contains -reset
we are going to delete the local store
so it's going to
clean out the cache and the CommandLine
arguments is a different way of getting
launch arguments in this case since
reset has no value we can just
investigate that
this argument was passed but if you care
about the value
you can use the user default helper
that can convert the values to strings
booleans, integers, etc
okay let's run this now and it should
pass
because now we are resetting the state
and it should have no cache
and if it has no connectivity and no
cache it should show an empty feed
and it's passing now awesome
let's commit displays empty feed
when customer has no connectivity and no
cache
that's it okay
so this test is independent from every
other test because it resets the state
but the other tests are not resetting
the state which means they may be
affected by a previous
test run and we don't want that so let's
make sure to also reset
the state in every test so in this case
when we run the online app we want to
reset the state
but we don't want to reset the state in
the offline app launch
otherwise we're going to erase the cache
created in the online app
exactly so this test is still independent
because the first launch
resets everything and starts from a
clean state
and finally the first one as well let's
reset
to make sure that there is no shared
state across tests
let's run all the tests
and you probably noticed how slow those
tests are
they need to launch the application over
and over
but it's passing let's commit
reset cache in every test run to make
sure tests run in a clean state
and don't influence the result of other
tests
so the tests are independent you can run
them in any order
you can run all the tests or you can run
a single test
and it should pass regardless alright
so this is working but we added test
code
in production yes
the SceneDelegate now which is
production code
it has some test logic and we don't want
to
deploy test code because you can even
have security
implications for example a malicious
user can launch your application with
arguments and take control of the state
of the application
this can be problematic so we don't want
this code
in production only when we are running
tests but since we are using UI tests
the black-box tests we cannot control
things like connectivity or cache state
from the test point of view we need to
inject this code
in production so the minimum we should
do here is to add
some compilation directives to prevent
this code from being deployed
in production so we can surround it with
the compilation directive
if debug so this code is only going to
be added to debug versions of your app
for example when you're testing
or running it with a debug configuration
now if you want to run UI tests with the
production
app you need to create your own
directives for example you could create
an if testing
that you can set in your production
build configuration
so every test code should be in between
compilation directives
to prevent it from being deployed in
production
so in this case we can replace the
switch statement with
an if statement and our
fake HTTPClient as well so now at least
this code is not going to be deployed in
production
so let's run the tests
alright it's passing okay
let's commit add
if debug compilation directive to
prevent
test specific code from being deployed
in production
that's it but we still have
all these compiler flags and the test
code
yes and this is still a small
application as we add more features
imagine how this is going to grow and
become a super unmaintainable
mess full of compiler directives
test code production code yeah and
that's the problem with
black-box testing basically yes
if you need to have any kind of control
to test some edge cases
you need to inject code in production
and since we don't want to deploy this
code to your customers you need to add
all those flags
but there are other ways we can do that
to eliminate
this noise from the production code so
all those if debug flags
could be moved into another class
so we can create a debugging
SceneDelegate okay
and this class is a subclass
of a SceneDelegate and then we can add
all the debugging logic
to the subtype so we are extending the
SceneDelegate
and moving the debug logic to the new
DebuggingSceneDelegate
exactly so we can copy this code
into our DebuggingSceneDelegate
to override the functionality of the
super class
the SceneDelegate and we can remove all
the parts we don't need
and keep only the debug code so in this
case we only keep
the reset logic and we forward
the message to the super class yeah
I like that and then we can also
override the remote client
and if we get the connectivity argument
we replace it with the always failing
client otherwise we use the super
implementation
so we need to expose the local store URL
in the super class and the make remote
client
as well
so the make remote client now needs to
be internal
and we can remove the debug code
we can also remove this debug code from
here
we just need to expose the local store
URL
finally we move the always failing
client as well
let's import EssentialFeed
and that's it we move all the debug
logic to a new class
only used while debugging exactly and
now we can even wrap the whole class in
an
if debug compilation directive
that's it so this is still code that
only exists
in debug builds but it's contained in
its own file in its own class
so the SceneDelegate is clean has only
production code
however now we need to tell our
application
to use the DebuggingSceneDelegate in
debug mode
and we can do it in the AppDelegate
exactly the application delegate will be
the decider
on which SceneDelegate it should go
with
exactly if we implement the
configuration for connecting
the scene session we have a chance of
creating
our own configuration and replace the
delegate class
for the scene configuration so if we
have a debug build
we are going to use the DebugScene
Delegate
otherwise it just uses the default one
that is set in your Info.plist
which in our case is the SceneDelegate
so this is a much cleaner way of
containing this
debugging or testing logic from your
production code
exactly so let's run the tests
still passing fantastic
let's commit move debug
code paths from the main SceneDelegate
to a new DebuggingSceneDelegate
subclass
to separate and debug and test specific
code
from production code that's it
I really like this separation the Scene
Delegate remains clean
with no debugging code and we have
extracted
any test related code to its own place
exactly so we have a lot of trade-offs
when using black-box testing because we
need to have
test code in the production target but
at least we can strip that code from
the production binary
and also separate it with our own
subclasses
so at least you contain the downsides in
a centralized place
there's one more thing we can do to
improve the UI tests
so so far we are checking that we are
loading the 22
feed cells and that we are loading at
least the first
image but the problem is we are loading
this
from remote from a server a server that
we have
no control over what if tomorrow the
server starts returning
23 or 50 or 100 or
0 right what if the server is down
what if you don't have internet
connection when you run the tests
so all those questions could lead your
tests to fail
so this test is flaky it cannot pass on
its own it depends on some external
systems
being in a specific state you expect so
this is fragile
ideally we should be able to run this
test over and over and over and always
get
the same result we want to reduce and
eliminate
flakiness so we need to decouple our UI
tests
from the specific backend and we already
have a mechanism for doing that
we can tell the app to be offline we
could also tell the app
to be online and have some canned
responses
thus we wouldn't need internet
connection or it wouldn't be dependent
on the server
state because we already tested the
end-to-end communication with the server
in the API integration tests we don't
need to test this again
in the UI tests, UI tests should not test
low-level details you should test high
level
acceptance criteria so we need to
control
the connectivity state for the online
state
and we could do so by passing
connectivity
online for example and have some
pre-defined
responses for that so when we're only
tests we get a reliable
result and now we have a place to do it
the DebuggingSceneDelegate
so if connectivity is set
we create our HTTPClient with
connectivity
so we should probably rename this
because it's not always failing anymore
it depends on the connectivity argument
so Debugging
HTTPClient
and now depending on the connectivity
state we can
return some predefined responses
so in the online connectivity state we
complete
with a successful response for the given
URL
else we complete with an offline error
okay so make successful response for URL
it creates an HTTP URL response status
success and we create data for URL
and if it's an image request we create
some fake
image data which is just a red image
otherwise we return the feed data
response which is just a JSON with 2
items
so we just need to change our tests to
expect 2
items instead of 22 but we could use
4, 5 or as many as we want
let's run the tests now and it should
run and pass without making
any network requests everything is
self-contained
look at that it loaded the red images
we created in the DebuggingHTTPClient
passing so those tests don't depend
on the server state or the network
connectivity
state anymore they are much more
reliable
they won't fail because of external
systems
we can run this test over and over and
over
and always get the same result yeah
that's fantastic
let's commit intercept
HTTP requests with canned responses
during UI tests
to eliminate network flakiness
we can now run UI tests without internet
connection
awesome alright
so we're running these UI tests that
traditionally are very flaky but we
created a very
reliable solution because we control
the infrastructure state the network
and we are only testing high-level
details
we're not checking the values in the
cell
the text and things like that all those
things have been tested
either in isolation with unit tests
or in integration, UI tests
they actually run the app they should
only test high-level acceptance
criteria now to make sure
you are not mocking too much in your UI
tests
you should only replace infrastructure
details
for example the HTTPClient
we are not changing the application
behavior we always keep
the current behavior we add
functionality
when debugging for example we reset
the cache state that doesn't affect the
application
functionality and also replacing the
HTTPClient doesn't affect the
application functionality
exactly we still use the SceneDelegate
because we are subclassing it and using
the Debugging subclass
during tests the whole composition is
the same
the only thing we are replacing is the
infra
structure the HTTPClient and this is
key
you don't want to mock or replace business logic
only replace infrastructure details
like network clients that's how you
maintain the confidence that
you are testing your real application
and we have the confidence because we
have API end-to-end tests
talking directly with the back end so we
don't need to test this again
with UI tests, UI tests we just test the
high-level acceptance criteria
through the black-box and that's how you
make your UI tests
reliable however there's another problem
with UI tests
they are super super super slow
how slow let's see
it took 29.8 seconds to run
3 tests right
30 seconds for 3 tests, 10 seconds
per test which means you won't be
running those tests very often
you're probably only gonna run them on
CI
yeah otherwise you're not gonna be very
productive if you run them often
yes and the more features we add the
more
this is gonna grow so it's very common
for UI tests to take 5 minutes, 10
minutes
30 minutes, hours to run that's why we
want to
minimize the number of UI tests just a
few
super high-level testing only the
acceptance criteria
all the details should be tested in
isolation exactly
and they're not part of your Command+U
process
no they are in a separate target for
slow tests
that's it and do you always need UI
tests
no but if you do you need to make them
as reliable as possible
and as fast as possible so again
low-level details your tests in
isolation and only test
very high-level acceptance criteria
through the UI tests
if needed and if you need to take
control of
any aspect of the application create a
clean separation
between the debugging code or the
testing code
from the production code, awesome
this is gonna do it for this lecture
we'll see you again
next time bye y'all, see ya