Hello Mike, hey Caio
in the previous lecture we tested the
acceptance criteria
with UI tests and they work just fine
but there are
two problems with it first
we ended up with test code in our
production
target right
and second and most important those
tests
are extremely slow we have 3
simple tests and they already take
around 30 seconds
to run so 10 seconds per test
right so adding more features will make
this testing strategy
unsustainable because of the time the
tests
will require to run yes
if we keep adding features to this
application and testing them with UI
tests
very soon will take half an hour or even
an hour to run
and that's not sustainable as a
development process because we want our
iterations to be fast we want to merge
code
several times a day but if our
continuous integration pipeline takes
hours to run
this is going to become a bottleneck
that's exactly right
so we need a better strategy for testing
the acceptance criteria so in this
lecture I'm going to show you how to
test
the acceptance criteria of your
application the whole composition
with integration tests which are much
faster
and doesn't require you to add test or
debug specific code
to production exactly and the Scene
Delegate
and the AppDelegate are like any other
class
if there is code in there you can test
it
exactly we can create
a SceneDelegateTests
and test the SceneDelegate like any
other class in our system
so for example we need to test that when
a new scene is going to connect
to the scene session we need to
configure the window
root view controller of the application
with the feed
user interface right so we can write
a test like scene will connect to
session configures the root view
controller
so we need an assertion what do we want
to happen when this method is invoked
well
we want to set the root view controller
over our window
and in the UI specs the feed view should
be embedded
in a navigation controller so the
assertion we need
here is that our root view controller is a
UINavigationController
when we invoke the scene we connect to
session
method so let's import the EssentialApp
module so we have access
to the SceneDelegate okay but the Scene
Delegate is not public
so we can't access it directly yes
so we either make it public or we import
this module as testable
in the test case right the SceneDelegate
APIs don't have to be public
because nobody else references the Scene
Delegate
right so the SceneDelegate is part of
the Composition Root
which is the root module no other module
references
the Main module exactly thus instead of
making the SceneDelegate public
we can import the Main module as
testable
because we don't want any other module
having access to this module
so when testing a root module we don't
need to expose
any root types publicly that's it
now we get autocomplete so we need a
scene
a session and options
so a scene is a UIScene
and the scene needs a session and
options
so we need a session a session is a
UISceneSession that inits with coder and
it's failable initializer
because it can fail so this is getting
trickier now
what kind of coder should we pass here
let's try an empty coder
and then we need options which is a
UIScene
ConnectionOptions but this class
doesn't have
a public initializer right so if you
cannot instantiate
a parameter of a method we cannot invoke
that method
and that's common when using frameworks
so how do you test a method you can't
invoke
well ideally the framework should give
you the tools
to test your code right
but when they don't there is something
you can do
when you cannot invoke a method what you
can do is to move
all the logic within the method you
cannot invoke into a method you can
invoke
okay the method that you cannot invoke
should only do one thing
call the method you can invoke right
it's not perfect but it does the job
yes ideally you want to call this method
but when you can't you shouldn't give up
on testing you move the logic
into a method you can invoke
so now we call just configure window
and we don't need all this code here and
before we run the test we should also
set
a window otherwise the window will be
nil now let's run the tests
failing fantastic
to make it pass let's embed the feed UI
in a navigation controller run the test
again
passing fantastic we should also check
that the top view controller in the
navigation stack
is a FeedViewController exactly
just checking the navigation controller
is not enough
because we want to make sure we have the
right composition which is
a navigation controller as the root and
a FeedViewController as the top
controller of the navigation
so we need to import the EssentialFeed
iOS
module to have access to the FeedView
Controller type
run the test again and they should pass
because the composition
is correct fantastic
but if we break the composition
we should now have a failing test
there it is okay expected a feed
controller as top controller
but got a UIViewController instead
fantastic let's test again
passing let's commit
so configures feed navigation as
window root view controller
so that's it the SceneDelegate or the
AppDelegate they are just normal
classes
that you can test with unit or
integration tests right
so the idea now is to translate those UI
acceptance tests
into integration acceptance tests that
don't need to
run the app and investigate elements on
the screen
with the slow UI queries
we can investigate the UI state like we
did
in the EssentialFeediOS integration
tests
we can even reuse the same helpers for
simulating
UI events so simulating a feed image
visible or counting the number of feed
imageViews on screen and although
those helpers are in the EssentialFeed
iOS target they are testing the
composition
of the UI and integration and those are
composition details
and composition details should be in the
Composition
Root so let's move this composition
details
to the EssentialApp target in the
Composition Root
which will also give us the ability to
reuse
those helpers for our acceptance tests
now all integration and composition
details live
in the Composition Root okay but we have
a bunch of build errors
so we need to fix the import statements
and any access control required exactly
now that these
composition details are moved to another
module we need to import
the EssentialFeediOS target so those
components have access
to the feed UI types like the FeedView
Controller
so the FeedViewControllerDelegate needs
to be public now
because it is implemented by types
outside this module
so the delegate needs to be public as
well
next let's import the EssentialFeediOS
module everywhere that references
the feed UI elements so the
ImageCellDelegate also needs to be
public because it can be
implemented by types outside this module
and finally the table model setter needs
to be public
but instead of making the setter and
getter public we can make it private
and create a public method to set it
okay so now the adapter can just call
display instead of setting the property
directly now in the test target
we also need to import the EssentialApp
module where the composer lives now
okay all tests are passing okay
let's commit so move
Feed UI composition details to the
EssentialApp
module in the composition route that's
it
alright so all composition details are
now
in the Main module the EssentialApp
target okay so now we can create the
feed acceptance tests exactly but
instead of UI tests
it is just a simple XCTestCase
and we already have the acceptance UI
test so we can just
paste the tests here right we want to
test
exactly the same criteria but we don't
need to run the app
to do so yes so let's delete
this implementation and let's re-implement
this
yes one by one the first test
on launch it should display the remote
feed
when customer has connectivity exactly
by creating the SceneDelegate directly
we give it a window we configure the
window then we get the FeedView
Controller
which is the top view controller of the
root and we can use the helpers
from the integration tests to validate
that we have rendered
the two feed image views and that both
images were rendered on the screen
right but to do so like we did in the UI
tests
we need to control the infrastructure we
need to control the HTTP
requests so ideally we would inject here
an HTTPClient and
a store which during tests don't need to
be a real client in a real store
exactly they can be an InMemory
FeedStore and an HTTPClientStub
so we can control the unreliable
infrastructure
components we want those tests to be
fast and reliable
thus we don't want to make real HTTP
requests or fetch things from the
database
exactly we want deterministic results
and that's exactly what the in-memory
FeedStore and the HTTPClientStub
provide
so we need to import the EssentialFeed
module
so we can stub the HTTPClient and the
FeedStore
and the client stub is a very simple
implementation
where we give it a stub closure that
will return
a result for any given URL
and we can give a default offline
implementation that always
fails and an online implementation that
always succeeds
with the given stub for the URL
and the in-memory store literally just
stores the values
in memory in a property
so in this test we want an empty
in-memory store and we need
an online HTTPClient
and we need to give a function that maps
a URL to a successful
response we have such a function already
it was used in the DebuggingScene
Delegate so in the DebuggingScene
Delegate
we have a function with the exact same
signature it receives a URL as parameter
and returns a successful response so we
can
use exactly the same in the integration
acceptance tests
we can even make this shorter and call
it response for
URL and since we are in the test target
we can use our helper UIImage
make with color red much simpler
okay so this is an HTTPClient with the
response
function we just created which is going
to map the URL
to a successful response that's it now
we just need to add
a convenience initializer in the Scene
Delegate so we can pass the dependencies
right so convenience
initializer where we receive the
dependencies
so the HTTPClient is an HTTPClient
and a store is a store that conforms to
both the FeedStore and the FeedImage
DataStore protocol that's it but we
want to have default values
for those dependencies so instead of
making them
lets we can make them lazy vars
so if they are not set we have a chance
of instantiating them
lazily so the HTTPClient is the same as
created here
so we are moving the creation into the
lazily
loaded property and the same
for the store
so if we provide one we're going to use
the provided one
otherwise it lazily loads as needed
that's it let's run the test now
okay it's building and the tests
are passing because this behavior has
already been tested
and implemented with the UI tests
exactly
as you can see we have much more control
with integration tests
than with UI tests we don't need to add
this code
in production exactly and we can even be
more thorough with those tests
instead of just checking that the image
is not nil
can even assert the exact value that was
rendered
in each cell exactly
we're not checking just the existence of
the images as we did with the UI tests
but here we can test the consistency of
the images as well
which gives us much more confidence that
this feature is working
as intended because we are comparing the
value that was rendered
with the data that was returned in the
successful
HTTP response
we can even create a helper to simplify
this code
like renderedFeedImageData at index
look at that much nicer
still passing one more refactoring we
can do
is get all the setup code and move it
into a function
right something like
launch with the HTTPClient and store
and we move all the setup logic in here
that's it now that's it
on launch displays remote feed when
customer has connectivity
so we launch the app with an
online stubbed HTTPClient
then we test that our feed loaded
the images let's run the tests
passing yeah I really like this
refactoring because
the test now is completely decoupled
from the implementation details
of the SceneDelegate exactly
let's commit displays remote feed
on launch when customer has connectivity
so the next test on launch displays the
cached
remote feed so there is a cached feed
and no connectivity
so just like in the UI test first we
need to populate the cache
in this case we launched the app with
connectivity
and a shared store and then we make sure
that the images
became visible which loads the images
and then we launched the app
as offline but with the same shared
store
to make sure that we loaded the items
from the cache so we should still show
two images and render the image data
let's run my tests passing
ok let's commit displays
cached feed on launch when customer has
no connectivity
and finally on launch displays empty
feed
when customer has no connectivity and no
cache
so if we launch the app offline and
with an empty
store well it should show an empty
screen
that's it let's run the tests
passing ok let's commit
displays empty feed on launch when
customer has no connectivity
and no cache
okay so we migrated the UI tests to
integration tests
validating exactly the same scenarios
but we haven't seen
any failing tests because this scenario
was already implemented
right so why don't we change the
composition just to make sure
the test would fail with the wrong
composition
for example if we just compose the UI
with the RemoteFeedLoader without a
fallback
and the same for the image
let's run the tests
okay it's failing but it's failing
with an exception because our tests is
trying to investigate a cell
that does not exist so we're getting an
index out of range exception
instead of a fatal error it would be
better if we get an assertion
error so let's look at the stack trace
to find which method invoked the cell
lookup
and it was this test helper the feed
image view
at row so here we need to check
if we are requesting a cell within the
collection of cells
if it's not we just return nil instantly
which means there is no cell at that row
right let's run the test again
now we get failing assertions rather
than a fatal error
as you can see since we've removed the
composition with the cache
the test that checks the offline
behavior start failing
fantastic yes the tests now fail
instead of crashing and they don't
interrupt the flow
which is a much better feedback
mechanism that's it
let's bring back the right composition
run the test again
now it's passing
and any different composition here
will make the test fail
there it is so the acceptance tests
give us this high level confidence that
the system does
what is intended to do and we don't need
to do it
through UI tests if you write good
integration tests
you can have the same confidence and
without adding
test code to production or running super
slow tests
so let's commit our last change so check
number of cells before fetching cell
at index to avoid
out of bounds exception
and now let's delete the UI acceptance
test target
because now it is redundant
so let's make sure we delete the scheme
for the acceptance test as well
and remove it from the CI scheme
okay let's build and run the test again
passing let's commit so
remove EssentialAppUIAcceptanceTests
in favor of faster and more precise
integration tests
now finally we can remove the Debugging
SceneDelegate
from production and we don't need to
swap
our delegate class for debug builds
anymore
which means we don't need the make
RemoteClient function anymore
which was overridden by the debugging
delegate
you can just use the HTTPClient
directly
same goes for the localStoreURL
these can now be a private detail
that's it much better encapsulation
let's run the tests still passing
let's commit remove unused debugging
code
that was previously used during UI tests
gone no more test coding production
fantastic
so the FeedAcceptanceTests in an
integration style
can be a better alternative to UI
tests yeah and we can even be more
thorough
and test one use case that we couldn't
actually test
with UI tests and that is when the app
enters
background we want to validate the cache
exactly we implemented the validate
cache
use case but so far we are never calling
it
this use case must be called every time
the app will enter
background now we can test this behavior
with the integration tests so if we
enter background
with an expired cache the cache should
be
deleted so it should be nil
but if it enters background with a non
expired cache
the system should keep the cache so it
should be not nil
exactly let's add the helper
enter background which simply creates
the SceneDelegate with the given store
and calls the delegate method
that is invoked when the app is
transitioning to the background
and we also need to add the static
helpers
that creates an expired feed cache so
it's a cache
with an old timestamp so distant past
and a non expired one with a fresh
timestamp
and now we need to implement the scene
we resign active
in the SceneDelegate let's run the
tests
failing it is not deleting the expired
cache
so we need to invoke the validate cache
method
implemented by the LocalFeedLoader
exactly
but we don't have access to the Local
FeedLoader in this
scope so we can make it
a lazy var instead so every instance
method has access
to this property that's it that should
do it
let's run the test again now it's
passing
so it is deleting expired cache when
entering background
but it keeps non expired cache when
let's commit validate feed cache
on entering background so that's it
an alternative to UI tests is to write
integration tests that can be more
thorough
and don't require you to add test code
in production
exactly they allow you to increase
the code coverage and of course they
come
at a much much cheaper cost than UI
tests
they are easier to write and they are
much faster
as you can see 5 integration tests
took only 0.2 seconds
to run in comparison to the UI tests
where
3 tests took almost 30 seconds
so that's at least 100 times
faster
exactly there is no comparison between
integration tests and UI tests when
it comes to speed these numbers speak
for themselves
and it's important to think about the
future of the project as well
the next added feature how much would
that
increase these times so when possible
use integration tests rather than UI
tests
to improve your coverage and make your
development process
faster okay this is going to do it for
this lecture
we'll see you all next time bye y'all
see ya