Hello Mike, hey Caio
in the previous lecture we validated the
acceptance criteria
with integration tests and in this
lecture we're going to show you how you
can validate
your user interface with snapshot
tests okay so in the EssentialFeed
iOS module let's create a new
test file FeedSnapshotTests
and the idea with snapshot tests is that
we are going to render
the user interface and take a snapshot
exactly
so first of all the simplest view is the
empty
feed right so we're going to instantiate
a FeedViewController
which is going to be the system under
test and we are going to take a snapshot
of it after rendering an empty feed
that's it so we need to create our
system under test
as always with the makeSUT function
which is very simple
we just need to instantiate the
FeedViewController from the storyboard
and load the view so it's ready to be
rendered
and the FeedViewController lives in the
EssentialFeediOS module
so we need to import that alright
and the display method takes an array
of FeedImageCellControllers
so an empty feed would be simply
an empty array of FeedImageCell
Controllers
yes that's it the test reads very nicely
alright now we need to take a snapshot
of the view controller
and to do so we can introduce an
extension on UIViewController
with a method snapshot that returns
a UIImage so the idea is to render
the view of the view controller and take
a snapshot of that view
exactly so let's render it with a
renderer
which is a UIGraphicsImageRenderer
so the bounds is the view bounds
exactly because we want the whole view
here
and we return the renderer image
by rendering the view
in the action context
alright that's all that's how we can
take a snapshot of a view
so let's see if the snapshot is working
let's capture the snapshot
let's add a breakpoint here let's run
the test
and let's investigate the value of the
snapshot
there it is an empty screen okay
might not have a lot but that's exactly
what we want
that's it when the feed is empty we see
an empty screen
that's it okay so the snapshot is
working
but the idea of snapshot testing is that
we take a snapshot
we store the snapshot to the File system
and then we can compare new snapshots
to the previous stored snapshot
so now we need to record that snapshot
or
save it to the File system and we can
create a new function
called recordSnapshot
and we can give it a unique name so it
doesn't conflict with other snapshots
okay so here it is the record function
takes a snapshot
which is a UIImage and a name so first
thing we need to do is to convert
our UIImage snapshot into data that we
can store to disk
and we can use a PNG representation if
you fail to create it
we fail with an assertion failure and a
nice message
okay next we need a path for storing it
and we can use the file path to create
the URL
as the file parameter holds the path to
the current file
exactly ideally we should store the
snapshots
close to the test file so we can use the
current file path
which is the FeedSnapshotTests file
as the base path for our snapshots
exactly and storing it in the same
directory as a test file
it means that we can add it to git as
well
exactly those snapshots should be stored
and pushed
to git so others can validate their
changes
against the stored snapshots so that's
it
let's create a URL for the snapshot with
the current file path
which will look something like this the
folder where the test file is
the EssentialFeediOSTests and
the file name
so we can delete the last path component
which would give us
the folder where the file is which
is the EssentialFeediOSTests folder
and we can append a path component to
create a new folder structure
for the snapshot that's it and finally
we can append the name of the file
which in this case is empty feed so we
would end up
with a file path like this the base
folder
plus the snapshots folder and the file
name yes
alright now we have the data to store to
disk
and the URL where we want to store it so
next
we need to make sure that this folder
structure exists
in the File system so we can use the
FileManager to create the folder
if needed and if it fails to create it
again we get a nice
assertion failure with the error
finally we can save our snapshot data
let's run the test okay
it's passing which means it should have
stored it to disk
so let's have a look okay it created the
directory
and it stored the image look at that
that's awesome
EMPTY_FEED.png fantastic
so let's commit okay
as you can see in the git diff we now
have the
empty feed image so our peers can also
use it to compare
with their changes so record empty feed
snapshot commit
next test now
a feed with content the empty one
is too easy right now we need to create
FeedImageCellControllers and populate
it
with an image so the
FeedImageCellController requests the
image
from its delegate right which should
call the display view model when it's
done requesting
the image so we need to create
some image stubs that we can use during
tests
we can simply render things on the
screen without any other
dependency okay I like that
so let's create a class ImageStub that
implements
the ImageCellControllerDelegate
which has two methods did request image
and did cancel image request
and when the controller requests the
image we need to tell the controller to
display
a stubbed view model so we need a
reference
to a controller but since the controller
has a strong reference to the delegate
we need to make the image stub reference
to the controller
weak to avoid any retain cycles
ok done then
we need a view model yes
which is a FeedImageViewModel
and we need an initializer that can
simplify that work for us
we pass description, location and the
UIImage
and that will create the view model for
us
so we now just need to import the
EssentialFeed module
where the FeedImageViewModel lives
however the FeedImageViewModel
doesn't have a public initializer
so we either add a public initializer or
we import
the module as testable so we can create
the view model struct adding it as
@testable
is fine for now okay finally we need to
create the feed with content
helper which should just
create an array of ImageStubs
so it has some long description, some
multiline
location string and
an image and we can use the helper to
just make an image based on a color
let me add it from the other module
make sure to copy the item if needed
that's it
now we just need to convert the Image
Stubs into the
ImageCellControllers so we're going to
map
the stubs and create a cell controller
for each stub
and set the stub controller as the cell
controller
finally let's call display cells and that
should do it
okay let's run the test alright
there it is empty feed and
feed with content without running the
application
awesome alright let's commit
as you can see again the image is also
added to the git history
so record feed with content snapshot
next let's render
a feed with an error message
let's run the test
okay there's the error message and we
can even test it against the multi-line
error message exactly it's a good idea
to test labels with multiple lines
especially because some translations
might be
longer than others exactly so this is a
multi-line
error message let's record the snapshot
again
let's see, a-ha, look at that
it is cropping the error message and we
don't want that
no we don't and that's one benefit of
screenshot testing no other tests picked
that up so far
yes you cannot test these easily with
unit
or integration tests because they're not
meant
to test things on the screen exactly
let's fix it, Feed
storyboard let's select the error label
make sure it supports multiline and it
does
it has no limit of lines
but the view is the table
header view and table headers
don't play nicely with auto layout
right so we need to resize this header
manually no problem let's create a
helper here
UITableView+Header
Sizing so we need to check
if there is a frame change so we can
update the table header
manually let's update the FeedView
Controller now
so every time viewDidLayoutSubviews is
called
we need to resize the table header
manually
run the test again there it is
okay perfect so let's commit this
in parts first let's commit the fix
fix table header resizing for multiline
label
and then let's commit the snapshot
record
feed with error message snapshot
alright back to the tests
next test let's render
a feed with a failed image loading so it
should show the retry button
again makeSUT display the feed with
failed image loading
and record a snapshot
let's create now the factory method for
the feed with failed image loading
any image stub with no image should do
okay let's run the tests
okay boom there it is
that's it fantastic
let's commit record feed
with failed image loading snapshot
done okay the recording part is done
now it's the second part asserting that
the recorded snapshot
matches a new snapshot okay
because just recording the snapshot will
just override
the existing snapshot after we record it
and we are happy with the result we need
to assert
the rendering against the stored
snapshot
so we need an assert function
and the assert function will start the
same we need to get the snapshot data
and the snapshot URL but now instead of
storing
and overriding the current snapshot we
are going to load
the stored snapshot if it fails
we're gonna fail with an assertion and a
nice message
letting us know that we need to record
first before we assert
yeah that's very helpful I really like
that then
we need to compare if the new snapshot
data
matches the stored one
if they don't we have a problem right
and to help you debug this problem we
can create
a temporary URL where you can write
the new snapshot data so we can compare
visually against the other one
right and finally finish with an
assertion failure
that the new snapshot does not match the
stored
snapshot with the URL to verify
their differences let's run the tests
ok it's passing which means the new
snapshots
are exactly the same as the stored ones
but let's prove that it will fail
if we change this
and it does look at that and it gives
you
a nice URL where you can investigate
what's wrong
let's see look at that
an error message is the new snapshot
and the stored one of course is
different
so the test is telling us that
something's wrong
now if you think the new one is fine you
can just
record it exactly if it's not fine you
need to fix the problem
but in this case we're going to keep it
as a multi-line label
so let's run the test again and it
should pass so the assert function
does not override the stored snapshot
it just asserts against it exactly
and we can refactor the record and
assert methods by extracting
some of the duplication, this duplicate
code
can go into helpers makeSnapshotURL
and makeSnapshotData
okay much nicer
that's it run the tests again
passing let's have a look at our images
again
empty feed, feed with content, feed with
error message
and feed with failed image loading you
can keep rendering this view
with any data we want without having to
mock
any network connection or database we
check
just the rendering of the user interface
without any other collaborators
because the idea with snapshot tests is
to test just the rendering
do not test logic with snapshot tests
use unit and integration tests to test
logic that's it let's commit
assert snapshots match the stored
snapshots okay so
the infrastructure for recording and
inserting snapshots
is done and it's reusable we can
snapshot
view controllers or simple views
but this is a very simple implementation
we can make it more robust by allowing
some configurations before taking the
snapshot
for example rendering it in an iPhone 8
frame with a light style
and also render it in an iPhone 8
with a dark style we could also create
different configurations
like an iPhone 11 or the iPhone
SE or any frame we want
so let's delete the old ones let's
re-record it
with a specific configuration
so the snapshot extension now needs to
take
a snapshot configuration where we can
define a size
the safe areas inset, the layout margins
we want to use
trait collection and etc
and we can define some predefined
configurations
as we said the iPhone 8 with a given
style
so we set the size for the iPhone 8
the safe area insets, the layout margins
and the trait collection where we set
the given style so light
or dark and of course you can use any
configuration for
your use case exactly and to override
the current configuration we need a
custom window
and we use this snapshot window just
during tests to override
the view configuration so now the
rendering happens in the window
exactly so the renderer doesn't happen
in the view controller anymore
we need to embed it into the snapshot
window
and then take a snapshot of it right
okay let's run
look at that we have now the
dark representation of the empty feed
and the light one
and the same for the other tests both
dark
and light and as you can see there are
some things we need to improve
to support dark mode here right but
before we do that
I would like to remove the scroll
indicators
from this snapshot yes we want our
snapshots clean
there is no reason for the scroll bars
to be there
we can just set the show scroll
indicator to false
let's record the snapshot again
now it's gone okay
okay now let's fix the layout
to support dark mode let's open the Feed
storyboard again
let's select the interface style to dark
and let's fix the colors first of all
the table view
background should not be white let's use
the default
system background color
the same for the footer
now the pin container also needs the
system background color
the description label should be the
secondary label color
much better the same for the location
now the image container background we
can use the
secondary system background color
finally the retry button can be the
system
background color okay
let's run the tests and record the new
snapshots
fantastic let's see the light one
nice, the dark also looks nice
same for the message, the feed with
content
and the empty feed okay
let's commit first just the storyboard
add dark mode support
now back to the tests
now that we are happy with the recorded
images
we can change the function now to assert
so we stop overriding it and start
asserting the snapshot
rendering let's run again
passing fantastic that's it
so that's a simple implementation of
snapshot testing
you can find frameworks out there but if
you just need a simple implementation
you can have
your own the concept is to record
a snapshot in the File system keep it
under
source control and assert against it as
you refactor your code to make sure
your views are rendering as you expect
and again you should not test logic with
snapshot tests only the user interface
the visuals exactly if you want to check
the logic
use unit tests or if you want to check
the logic in integration
you can use integration tests alright
that's it let's commit assert
snapshots for light and dark mode
using an iPhone 8 configuration
and that's snapshot testing it's a very
simple
idea and it's very helpful for
validating the rendering of your views
it can pick up details that is not as
easy
to do with unit tests or integration
tests
and it can assist the collaboration with
the designers
because you can actually show them
images not code
exactly the images now are part of the
git history
which means you're constantly validating
them in your merge requests
and you can show them to the designers
to validate your implementation before
pushing the code to production moreover
if you create nice snapshots you can
even use them
as screenshots when submitting new
versions of your application
exactly but use it with care do not test
logic with snapshot tests
just the rendering so that's it for this
lecture
we'll see you again next time bye y'all
see ya