Hello Mike, hello everyone, hey Caio
in this lecture we are going to fix a
potential bug
in the did end displaying cell method
okay so what is the problem the way
table views work
as you render cells on the screen for
example as you are scrolling
the table UIKit will call cell for row
at indexPath to create the cell then
before adding it to the view hierarchy
it will call
will display cell for row at indexPath
and when the cell is being removed from
the table view hierarchy
for example as you scroll and the cell
gets out of bounds
out of screen it will call did end
displaying
cell and in the did end displaying cell
we cancel loading the image for that
cell
at indexPath which gets the model
at that indexPath and cancels the load
so that's very efficient because as this
cell gets out of the view hierarchy
we stop loading the image because we
don't need it anymore
yep the problem is that UIKit also
calls did end displaying cell
when you call reload data
so for example imagine we create the
view controller
and we tell it to display 2 cells so
we pass
a model with 2 cell controllers
then we call reload data and we are
going to render
those 2 cells but now let's say the
user requested
to load the feed again but now we get
0 cells back so an empty array
for example if someone removed images
from the feed
then when we tell UIKit to reload the
data
it will remove the 2 cells that were
there on screen
and call did end displaying cell for
both indexPaths but now
if we try to cancel the load request
for that specific cell controller this
will crash
because we have 0 cell controllers
in the table model array that's it UI
Kit will call ddn displaying cell
after the model was updated and it's
empty now
so we transitioned from 2 items to
which means we will try to get a value
for an index that doesn't exist anymore
and that's gonna crash
with an index out of bounds error yep
so this is not crashing right now
because we cannot delete images
from the feed but we cannot assume that
the backend will always behave like
this
okay we need to fix this but first let's
prove that this bug exists with a test
okay so here's the test where we prove
that we are rendering
the feed successfully on the screen so
let's duplicate it
and let's call it render successfully
loaded
empty feed after non
empty feed makes sense
yep that's it and we don't care about
values
in this test so let's just create 2
images
let's load those 2 images in the first
load
and then if we load again but we receive
an empty
array of images it should render an
empty
feed, that's it, it shouldn't crash
let's run a test and it's passing
so we do have that problem but this test
is passing
okay how is that possible well again we
need to understand how UIKit works
when you tell a table view to reload for
performance
reasons it doesn't do it immediately
so when you're running tests and you
want to ensure
that you are actually rendering the
table view cells
we need to force the table view to
layout
by calling layoutIfNeeded
and let's run the main RunLoop
okay let's run the test again
boom now it crashes exactly where we
want
look at that yep fatal error
index out of range so now with a test we
were able to replicate
exactly the problem we would have in
production
if the server ever returns a response
with less items
then we had before on screen that's it
the simple way to solve it is to add a
guard
to check the bounds
okay the test is passing now but this is
not exactly what we want
since UIKit calls did the end display
in cell after we changed the model
it means that we would be calling cancel
on the new models not on the old ones
yeah
exactly that's not what we want that
solves the problem
but maybe it's better to get a reference
for the currently loading view
controllers
okay so let's create a new property
private var loading controllers
which can be a dictionary of indexPath
as key
and FeedImageCellController as value
and every time we get a new model to
display
we reset it
and cancel now will be the loading
controller
at indexPath if any
and we can set it to nil because after
you cancel
you don't want to hold a reference to it
anymore okay
now we also need to hold a reference
to the cell controller and we can do it
here
controller is the cell controller at
indexPath
in the loading controllers
all right let's run the tests
it's passing okay let's commit
okay so fix a potential bug
when cancelling requests in the did end
displaying cell method
this method is invoked after calling
reload data
so we would be cancelling requests in
the wrong models
or crash in case the model has less
items
than the previous model yep so you need
to be careful
when canceling requests in the did end
displaying cell
method of a table view
and that's the process for fixing bugs
in your codebases
prove the bug exists with a failing test
make the test pass
and refactor without a failing test you
cannot prove
the bug exists you cannot prove that you
actually fixed it
exactly that's precisely the TDD process
all right so that's it for this lecture
we'll see you all again
next time bye y'all, see ya