Hello Mike, hey Caio
in this lecture you'll learn different ways
to organize
a modular project so let's start with a
quick review
of the current design of the Feed
Feature
so at the core we have the Feed Feature
core module
that defines the models and the service
interfaces exactly so we have models
and abstractions yes that represents the
domain
so we have a protocol defining a way to
load
image data, another one to load the feed
and we have a domain model representing
the feed image
so this core module does not depend on
any other module
there are no arrows from this module
pointing
to other modules on the contrary other
modules
depend on the core module
for example the Feed API module
has implementations of the services and
the use cases
exactly and the same for the Feed Cache
module
again we have use case implementations
validating and controlling the cache
based
on business rules exactly
so the Feed Cache also depends on the
Feed Feature
and then we have the Feed Presentation
module which
also depends on the Feed Feature module
and the Feed Presentation module
translates
feed images to presentable data
that can be displayed by the UI
and finally we have the UI the renders
the feed image view model on the screen
exactly and specifically it's a UIKit
implementation
for iOS so since this is a modular
design we could easily
replace this UI with a SwiftUI
implementation for example without
changing
anything in other modules exactly
and that's the power of modular design
so at the bottom
we have platform specific modules and
components
and all of those modules on the top are
platform agnostic
they can be used cross-platform you can
reuse
all those modules in macOS, watchOS
tvOS, iPadOS and etc
but you couldn't use it on Linux
or Android or on Microsoft platforms
because we have Core Data in the cache
module
and URLSession in the API module right
and URLSession and Core Data they are
somehow platform specific because they
only
work on Apple platforms
so if you're only delivering Apple
applications
that should be fine but if you want to
use these modules in other platforms
like Linux or the web you would have to
take this implementation out of the
module
and since no other component depends on
it that's an easy change
we simply move the class into another
module
exactly you extract
database infrastructure in this case
and the same thing with the URLSession
that's an easy change
as you can see no other component
depends on it
we can easily replace Core Data with
other frameworks
for example Realm, SQLite or an in-memory
database
exactly or in the case of the Feed API
we can change the infrastructure from
URLSession
to AlamoFire or some other framework
that Apple might release in the future
or on a Linux application you can use a
Linux
networking framework that's it so that's
the power of modular design
as long as no other component depends on
frameworks
we can replace them easily exactly and
let's zoom out a bit and observe just
the modular dependencies
so the core module it does not depend on
anyone
the Feed API depends on the Feed Feature
but it does not depend on any other
module
and the Feed API infrastructure which in
that case would be the URLSession
or AlamoFire or some Linux framework
depends on the Feed API but only on the
Feed API
exactly the same holds for the Feed
Cache with the Feed Cache infrastructure
module
and the actual database infrastructure
might be
Core Data, Realm, SQLite or
another implementation and on the
Presentation side
the Presentation depends on the core
module as well
and the iOS module depends on the
Presentation
so we can change the Presentation and
the UI without affecting any other
module
we can change the API without affecting
any other module
we can change the Cache without
affecting any other module
we can plug new user interfaces we can
plug new Cache infrastructure we can
plug new API infrastructure
because our modules are decoupled at the
center we have only
domain specific service abstractions and
domain models and around it we have more
specialized
implementations and on the outer layers
we have infrastructure implementations
and in an even outer layer we have
frameworks
and that's how you protect your code
base from external
influences exactly so we can represent
these layers
in a circular form the infamous
onion architecture that's it
and now we're going to understand why
they call it onion architecture
so at the center we have the core
models and service interfaces
this is platform and framework agnostic
then on an outer layer we have the use
case implementations the service
implementations
and in our case the presentation as well
but notice how
the Feed API doesn't know about the Feed
Cache the Feed Cache doesn't know about
the Presentation
they are independent they only know
about the direct
inner layer the Feed Feature in this
case
and then in an outer layer we have the
infrastructure
adapters that will provide the
communication with external
frameworks so the infrastructure
adapters
are platform and or framework
specific so the Feed Cache infra
might depend on Core Data, Realm, SQLite
to provide the infrastructure
implementation
for the Feed Cache exactly as you can see
they're all
in the same slice but
the Feed Cache does not know about outer
layers
outer layers know only about the direct
inner layer so the Feed Cache infra knows
only about the Feed Cache
module and the Feed Cache module knows
only about the Feed Feature
module so inner layers don't know about
outer layers and outer layers only know
about their direct
inner layer so what does that give us
is that we can easily peel this onion
and take pieces off and replace them we
can take this entire block the cache and
the infra
and replace with something else or
simply remove it without affecting
any other part of the application
we can also replace the infra with
something completely different we can
take this slice off
put a new slice here and the rest of the
application will be unaffected
exactly the same in the API infra here
you can have
Firebase, URLSession, AlamoFire you just
peel the onion and you can put something
in place in the Presentation
same thing we can completely remove
the Presentation slice and replace it
with something else
we can plug in new user interfaces to
this Presentation
like the macOS AppKit UI, WatchKit
UI, SwiftUI, UIKit UI
you can replace these layers remove
layers easily without affecting the rest
of the application yeah we're talking
about
ultimate plug-ability, ultimate freedom
when it comes to change and another way
of seeing this
is in this stack of layers from high
level
at the top to lower level at the bottom
so every layer stacks on top of each
other
we have the models and service
interfaces
at a higher level and below it we have
the use cases
and service implementations
infrastructure adapters and
the infrastructure frameworks so high
level layers
at the top and as you start going down
you go
to lower and lower level layers that's
it
it's all about slicing your application
into layers and managing the
dependencies
between them high level modules should
not depend
on lower level modules exactly
but how can we now organize and separate
those modules
in your project let's have a look first
and see how the project looks like right
now
so currently we have a workspace
with two projects, one project
is the EssentialFeed project that
represents the Feed Feature
and inside the project we have two
frameworks
the EssentialFeed framework for
platform
agnostic components so the Essential
Feed
works for both macOS and iOS and then
we have a platform specific
framework for iOS specific components
like the user interface
and the other project is the application
specific
project so we have one application
target
that depends on the Feed frameworks
so here in the EssentialApp we have the
Composition Root that composes
the platform agnostic with the platform
specific modules
exactly so right now we have one
workspace
two projects and three targets
the EssentialApp has the application
target and the EssentialFeed
have two framework targets the platform
agnostic
and a platform specific
so here we have the platform agnostic
modules at the top
and the platform specific the iOS module
at the bottom
that depends on UIKit so although we
have different colors here
the platform agnostic types all live in
the same module
and that's the EssentialFeed yes
so our separation right now pretty much
looks like this
everything in red represents modules
that live in the same framework
the EssentialFeed
purple is the iOS module
and green third-party frameworks
so all those modules right now
live in the EssentialFeed framework
target
exactly and although all these modules
live under the same
EssentialFeed target they're separated
into folders
so they still keep this modular
separation
because we keep them separated yes
we separate them into folders here
we make a conscious effort of
maintaining the types
separated but there is no physical
separation
so if you keep a bunch of modules in the
same
framework it requires a lot of
discipline not to couple them
because you have access to all
components exactly the compiler will not
prevent you
from crossing boundaries exactly
so keeping things in the same framework
is easier
to set up but then it requires a lot of
discipline
to keep your components decoupled yeah
and it can be a great way to start off
your project
and then break the modules down into
their own frameworks
as needed so how would it look like
if we break down the Feed API for example
into another framework to create a
physical
separation between these modules okay
we would first create a framework
let's call it EssentialFeedAPI
so we have a new target for the
EssentialFeedAPI framework
and the API is platform agnostic so
let's add support
for the iphonesimulator and the iphoneos
okay and
the Feed API module depends on the Feed
Feature module
so we need the EssentialFeed as a
dependency here
so now we can see this direct dependency
exactly the EssentialFeed does not
depend on the API
but the API depends on the Essential
Feed
just like in the diagram exactly this is
a modular dependency
of the Feed API to the Feed Feature
module so now we would just drag
the files to the new EssentialFeedAPI
module folder let's select
all of them and make sure they are in
the right target membership
so they should be in the API now
let's move the tests as well so the Feed
API tests
go to the new FeedAPITests
folder let's also make sure
the files are in the right target
membership
they should now be in the FeedAPITests
so the EssentialFeed module does not
need the Feed API
empty folder anymore
so now that we have a new framework
target
we also gain a new scheme
so let's try to build this new framework
and we got some failures okay
we do not have access to the FeedImage
DataLoader anymore
because the FeedImageDataLoader lives
in the EssentialFeed module
so we need to import EssentialFeed
in every file that depends on types of
the Essential Feed
module and that's the physical separation
between them
now we need to import that module to be
able to access the types
which will help you enforce a clean
separation between them
okay let's run the tests
and it's passing fantastic
so we extracted this new framework out
of the core framework
so now we have this separation here the
Feed API module
lives on its own but what about
the application that composes them
if we try to run the application now
we're going to get build errors as well
exactly this module doesn't know about
the EssentialFeedAPI
module so now the application
target needs to also depend on the
EssentialFeed
API
so in our Composition Root
can now import the EssentialFeed
API and we should be able to run the
application
there you go fantastic
there it is we separate our modules and
we decouple them
but at some point we need to compose
them together and we do it
in a centralized place so this is the
Composition Root
and you can see here in the Composition
Root all the imports
exactly so you can break down your
application
into many modules and compose them in a
centralized place
so the Composition Root is the only
place that we import all the modules
to compose them and that's how you keep
the modules
agnostic of each other and still combine
them
exactly so you can have a separation
like this
your feature projects with the separator
modules
then you can have an application
specific workspace
composing all the projects and modules
in the Composition
Root that's it you can follow the steps
we just
did and break down every module
into separate frameworks and at the end
it would look like this ok
the EssentialFeed will only contain
the domain service interfaces and domain
models
so it does not depend on anyone
the EssentialFeedAPI contains domain
service implementations
based on the use cases and it depends on
the EssentialFeed module
only and then on the outer layer you
have the API infrastructure
with the infrastructure implementations
so it only depends on the Feed
API just like here
the EssentialFeedCache follows the
same principle
it depends on the EssentialFeed and
implements the service
based on the use cases for caching and
the infrastructure
implements the infrastructure adapters
and depends on the Feed
Cache like here and the Feed
Presentation
depends on the EssentialFeed module
like here and the iOS
module depends only on the Feed
Presentation
like here so that's a choice
if you want to enforce that physical
separation between the modules
you can break them down into separate
frameworks but they can still live
in the same project representing a
feature
and then you need a Composition Root to
compose all the modules
together so the EssentialApp target
depends on all separated modules
so we can import all of them and compose
all the modules
in a centralized place the Composition
Root
but as you can see this will be harder
to maintain
than having things in the same framework
so you need to balance the trade-offs
so we recommend you to start simple and
only break down
into physical separated modules when
needed
exactly and there are other ways we can
do
the separation we can have a simple
setup
of one project and one target
yeah so in this example here we have one
project the EssentialApp project
and it has only one target an
application target that is
iOS specific and we just separate
our components virtually with folders
so it requires a lot of discipline to
maintain the features
modules and components decoupled because
there's
no physical separation and of course in
this case
the tests would run through the
simulator yes because the
EssentialApp is an iOS application
target so it has to run on the simulator
so this might increase test times and
build times because everything is in the
same
module exactly but it works fine
for small applications when you're
starting off it also works fine for
prototypes
and projects that you are going to
discard soon
another valid setup one project but
multiple
targets, one target per feature so if you
have a Login Feature for example you
have a login
framework and if you have a Feed Feature
you have a feed
framework and then you have the
application target
composing the two frameworks
but everything within the same project
only one project so now we have physical
separation
of the features but the modules within
those features
are not separated they are just
separated virtually with
folders so the Login Feature has a
bunch of layers inside of it
that's the horizontal slicing and the
EssentialFeed will also have
its own horizontal slicing
and EssentialApp contains the
Composition Root to compose
the features that's it so one project
one framework per feature
another valid setup is multiple projects
one per feature with its own target
and the EssentialApp iOS application
composes both frameworks in the
application target
but in all of those examples every
project lives in the same
repository which is the easiest way to
maintain
your modular application under source
control everything in one repository
separate projects, separate targets
depending on what you need
but all we think the same repository now
if you want to share code across
repositories
you can put down every feature or every
module into separate
repositories that's much harder to
maintain you will probably need
something like CocoaPods
git submodules, Carthage or
Swift Package Manager exactly
so our recommendation is for you to
start simple
and only separate things as needed
because it increases the amount of
maintenance you and your team will have
to
do around the projects very well said
you and your team need to run your own
individual cost/benefit analysis
and see what will suit your
needs and that's going to be based on
your architecture and design it's going
to be based on your team structure
if you have feature teams or remote teams
all of that influences how you're going
to organize your project
so you need to find a good balance
exactly
but as long as you achieve a clear
separation between
your layers that gives you this ability
to
slice and peel your architecture and
replace things easily
then you're good to go then your project
can grow easily
you can accommodate more people you can
accommodate changes
you welcome changes as we add more
features we want to maintain this
plug-ability as well
for all our features so you are happy
the team is happy
the customers are happy the business is
happy
and everyone benefit and profit from the
whole operation
and that's exactly how you're going to
achieve remarkable results as well
that's it okay that's it for this
lecture
we'll see you again next time bye y'all
see ya