Hello Mike, hey Caio so in this lecture
we're gonna finish the last details in
this application
and push it to the App Store Connect
okay
let's do it so before we publish this
application
there are a couple of things we need to
do first we don't have an icon
yet and if you don't have an icon
Apple will reject your binary exactly
so let's add an icon to the assets
catalog
okay let's run
now as you can see we have a nice
icon okay so let's commit
add app icon
and next I don't know if you noticed but
when we run the application
there's a transition from an empty
screen to the feed which is embedded in
a navigation controller
let's run it again right that's not a
problem
but if our launch screen matches
the style of this initial screen it
looks like the application loads faster
it's a better user experience exactly so
we can change the launch screen
to be as similar as possible to the
first screen
which is the feed embedded in the
navigation controller
so we can embed the launch screen
in a navigation controller as well
so when we run the app now looks like it
loads much faster because the launch
screen
is very similar to the first view
that's just a little touch you can do to
make your application look
better and faster it's a smoother
transition
I quite like it to be honest let's
commit
so embed launch screen
into a navigation controller for a
smoother
initial app transition
commit okay that's enough
but there's one more thing I would like
to do which is to remove the Main
storyboard
because we are not using it by default
when you create an application
you get this Main storyboard but all the
configuration
is happening in code
so if you don't need the Main storyboard
it's better not to have it there
exactly so there are a couple things we
need to do to remove the storyboard
yeah just deleting the file is not
enough
because if you try to run the
application now it crashes
exactly because this Main storyboard
is loaded automagically as part of the
application load
so we need to select here the app
project
the app target, go to general and first
of all you need to remove
the main interface, Main from the
application target
configuration and if you are using the
new iOS 13
SceneDelegate APIs you also need to
remove it
from the Info.plist in the Application
Scene Manifest
Scene Configuration, Application Session
Role
Storyboard Name just remove the row from
the configuration
okay and that should not crash the
application
because it's not going to try to load
the Main storyboard that doesn't exist
anymore
but as you can see the application
doesn't load anymore
it doesn't have a window it's all black
and that's because when you're loading
your initial screen from the Main
storyboard
it creates the window for you
automatically
but if you're doing it in code you need
to create your window in code
as well so here when we are going to
connect to a session
we need to create our window with the
window scene
which is the window scene we received
here okay let's run the application
again
and it still doesn't work because when
you create your own window
you also need to make it the key window
and you also need to make it visible
so why don't we test this behavior right
because
this could break our application if it
doesn't have the right setup
exactly so let's add a test
configure window is the method we are
going to invoke
sets window as key
and visible
okay so let's create here our window
let's create the system under test
the SceneDelegate let's set
the SceneDelegate window to be our
window
and let's call configure window and we
expect
the window to be the key window
and make sure that it is
not hidden so assert false window is
hidden
so expected window to be visible
alright let's run this test
both failed as they should okay
so SceneDelegate when we set up the
window we also need to make it
first of all make key let's run the test
again
okay the first assertion passed it is
key window now
but the second assertion that it is
visible is not passing so
makeKeyAndVisible
let's run the test again
passing fantastic let's run the
application again
and now everything works and we have
tests to guarantee that the window is
being configured
correctly without the Main storyboard
awesome let's commit
remove unnecessary Main storyboard
the initial setup happens in code
because we don't need the Main
storyboard but if you need it there's no
problem
just keep it there okay
one more thing I notice here is that the
second
test name mentions that it is testing
the scene will connect to session method
but we are actually testing the
configure window so we could rename it
to configure window to be more precise
yeah every time you see something in a
test and test name
you need to improve it just like your
code exactly
tests is also code and you need to keep
improving it
improving names refactoring just like
you would with your production code
so improve a test name
and now we are ready to deploy this
application
to the App Store Connect and then we can
choose to
send it to the App Store or send to Test
Flight testers
it could be customers stakeholders
friends, family
whoever you want awesome so
let's go to the App Store Connect
website
let's create a new application
in our case it's an iOS app so let's
select only iOS platform
let's give it a name Essential
App, language
English let's select the bundle ID
in our case it was generated by Xcode
that's why it has the xc
prefix but if you want you can create
your own bundle ID
it just need to be unique and needs to
match the bundle ID
that you set up in Xcode so for us
it's the EssentialAppCaseStudy bundle
ID
then you can set up an SKU whatever
makes sense for your application
for us just EssentialAppCaseStudy
and select a user access that makes
sense to your application for us
full access okay let's create the
application
they are going to fill all the
information privacy policy, URL
subtitle, the primary category, secondary
category
but we are interested in sending a build
for TestFlight
users so let's go to TestFlight
and let's add the missing information
here again you need to fill whatever
makes sense to your application
save it and that's it
now we need to upload a build as you can
see we have
no builds so let's do it let's go back
to Xcode
and the bundle identifier needs to match
the bundle identifier in the App Store
Connect
so it's EssentialAppCaseStudy
exactly so update app bundle ID
to match App Store Connect
make sure you select the Generic
iOS Device otherwise you won't be able
to generate an archive as you can see
archive is disabled unless you select
the Generic iOS Device or a real device
so let's select a generic one
and now we can generate an archive that
can be
uploaded to App Store Connect let's
archive
there it is we now have an archive that
we can distribute
to the App Store so select the archive
you would like to upload
and press Distribute App, App Store
Connect
upload
then you select the settings that makes
sense for your application
in this case we are using automatic
signing but if you have
manual signing you need to select
whatever makes sense to your application
make sure that everything is correct the
profile used for signing
the team selected, the bundle Identifier
entitlements and press upload
if everything's fine you get a
successful response
that's it and that's it
let's go back to the App Store Connect
refresh the page
there it is our build is now processing
fantastic it takes a couple of minutes
to process
let's reload again boom there it is
everything
worked so now we have a build that we
can either
send straight to the App Store to
customers
or we can send to TestFlight for a
group of people that can test the
application before we actually send it
to the App Store
so we can select a group of people or
individual testers to test that build
and once you're happy you ship it to
everyone in the App Store
fantastic that's great but it requires a
lot of manual work
exactly ideally this process should be
automated
and it can be automated just like we
have CI servers
for automating the build and testing of
the application
we can also automate the build and
deploy
to the App Store or to TestFlight so
whatever
build server you're using you should be
able to automate
this process for example every time
you push code to master it automatically
sends a build
to testers or to customers to
stakeholders
so you're constantly delivering value to
them
several times a day several times a week
they can see the new updates and they
can interact with it
and it's all automatic exactly
plus you're always ready to submit to
the App Store
you're always one click away from
submitting it
and that's the dream you should always
be ready to push
to production exactly that should be
just a business decision
for example after your stakeholders are
happy with a build
it should be a matter of pressing a
button to release in the App Store you
shouldn't have any ceremony
it should be super easy to send builds
to the App Store
it should be automated and it should
generate builds
several times a week several times a day
even so we always have a build ready to
be tested or pushed
to production and that's continuous
delivery you're continuously
delivering value several times
a day and again you can achieve that
with
any build server you're using yes you
can do it with
any build server you have maybe locally
or a remote server like Circle CI, Travis
CI
Bitrise so we're going to show you how
we did it
with GitHub Actions which is a free
solution
provided by GitHub, so on GitHub
we've created this .github folder
where you can set workflows for your
GitHub Actions
and to deploy an application you need
three things an Apple distribution
certificate
the provisioning profile and you need
export options for exporting your
archive
and there are tutorials for all of these
you just need to follow Apple's
documentation I'm going to set a link in
this lecture
but the important thing is that you
don't want to just upload
the certificate in the provisioning
profile as
plain text to GitHub those are secrets
so what we did we encrypted both of them
with GPG
so this is an encrypted blob that needs
to be decrypted before
used exactly so those are the assets we
need
to deploy our application the
certificate the provisioning profile
and export options
and then we set workflows
so we have the continuous integration
workflows that just build and test the
application
and we have a deploy workflow
just a YAML config file to tell GitHub
actions the steps
in your workflow automation so the
deploy automation
the way we set it up is that every time
there's a push to master every time
there's a new change to master
we're going to run this workflow that's
because
master is our main branch is our trunk
every time we merge to the main branch
we want to generate a build
and upload it to App Store Connect so we
can send it to TestFlight or deploy
to our customers but it depends on the
branching strategy you use
maybe you're going to choose every time
you push to a release branch
or to a develop branch whatever
branching strategy you use
you need to set it up here for us every
time we merge to master
you want to deploy a new build to the
App Store Connect
so every time we push you master we're
going to run
the build and deploy job
so it's going to run on a macOS image
and then we set the steps for the
workflow
first of all we need to check out the
repository
then we need to install the provisioning
profile
we need to decrypt it with our secret
key
that you can set up whatever build
server you're using
you have a space to add secrets
and after we decrypt it we can install
it
in the right folder then the same thing
we need to install
the keychain certificate we're going to
decrypt it
and follow a bunch of steps here to
install this certificate
in the image keychain then we're going
to select
the latest Xcode in our case it's
11.4.1
then we need to set the build number and
this needs to be a sequential
unique number every build needs to have
a unique number
otherwise Apple will reject it so we
just use the GitHub
run number and every build server have
something similar to this
then we build the archive for release
then we export the archive and we deploy
it to the App Store Connect simple as
that
that's it so whatever build server
you're using you can set up a
configuration
like this step by step so whatever
solution you're using
you can automate the deployment of your
applications
okay let's have a look at the workflow
in action
you can see the deploy workflow ran
once when we merged those changes to
master
and all steps succeeded so checkout
install the provisioning profile, install
the keychain certificate
selected the right Xcode, set the build
number
build the archive, export the IPA
and deploy to the App Store it all
worked
so if we go back to the App Store
Connect website now
boom there it is the build number 2
was uploaded automatically when we
merged
that change to master alright
now every time we merge to master we're
gonna automatically generate a build
that we can send to TestFlight or
straight to our customers
we are just a button away from releasing
the application all the time
and several times a day every time we
merge to master
we can send this build to stakeholders
they can test it
on their own phones, testers can test it
QA can test it
so your work is visible at all times
this is going to improve so much your
communication with everyone
in the business because instead of
building up anxiety
of them waiting for weeks, for months to
get a build
to test the application they get it
daily, several times a day, several times
a week
and when there is a build that they test
and they think it's
pretty good they're happy to ship you
just press a button
and it's out to the customers and this
is continuous delivery
you're always ready to ship you're just
a button away
from sending your application to prod to
customers
awesome this is gonna do it for this
lecture we'll see you again
next time bye y'all, see ya