Hello Mike, hey Caio
in this lecture you'll learn how you can
improve and simplify your code
with the standard Swift Result type to use
the standard Swift Result type
you need Swift 5 or above so let's start
by showing how to migrate your codebase
if you need to just by opening Xcode
10.2 or later
we already get warnings that show all
the necessary steps
we need to take to update to Swift 5.
make sure to select all the targets
ok no source changes necessary so let's
just press update
let's run all the tests in the CI scheme
because during the migration we want to
make sure that
all the targets are passing and all the
behavior stays the same
exactly okay all tests are passing let's
commit
migrate to Swift 5 no source changes
needed
next let's solve the warnings first of
all
let's enable the new recommended setting
base internationalization run all the
tests again
passing awesome let's commit
next the Swift compiler is generating a
warning for the redundant
internal declarations up to now we
declared explicit
internal scopes to make access control
clear to you
during the lectures however it's not
mandatory as the internal access control
is the default access control
exactly so from now on we will omit it
so let's do a global search for internal
and remove it
globally as you can see it's now gone
let's run the tests nothing should
change because that's the default value
alright test is passing and the internal
warnings are gone
let's commit remove redundant internal
access control declarations
next we have a couple of deprecated
initializers
as you can see the new initializer
doesn't require the named parameter
anymore
so we can just remove the bytes name in
both places
let's run the tests it's passing perfect
let's commit
no more warnings migration complete
awesome but since we are in this test
file I remember we use the reduce method
to remove
optionals from a dictionary since Swift
5 though
you can use the new compactMapValues
instead of
reducing to remove all optionals which
is a much simpler way
of doing it let's run the tests or
passing
let's commit
finally let's deal with the standard
Result type let's search for
custom Result types we have created and
refactor
those custom Result types one by one
okay
that seems like a good strategy first of
all we have the LoadFeed
Result which was the first Result type
we've created
it has a success case with an array of
FeedImages and a failure
with the Error protocol which is very
similar to the Swift
Result type as you can see the Swift
standard Result type
also has a success and failure where the
success
holds a Success generic value and the
failure
holds a Failure generic value where the
Failure
needs to conform to the Error protocol so
we can replace
the LoadFeedResult with a new result
type and
since we want to avoid breaking too much
of existing code we can transform
the LoadFeedResult enum into a type
alias
for a result holding the array of FeedImages
as the Success type and the Error
protocol for the Failure type
so that should do it so let's run the
tests
okay build succeeded and the tests are
passing with no
extra changes required fantastic let's
commit
so we place custom LoadFeedResult enum
with the standard
Swift Result another improvement we can
make now
is to nest the LoadFeedResult within
the FeedLoader protocol
since they are closely related and we
can simply call this
Result now because it's already scoped
within the FeedLoader
but since this result conflicts with the
standard type Result name
we can add the Swift module name to help
the compiler understand
this type declaration yeah I really like
this change from the client's point of
view
it now reads FeedLoader.Result which is
much more descriptive
exactly but this is a breaking change
and the compiler is going to help us
so LoadFeedResult is now
FeedLoader.Result
okay we are done with the FeedLoader
Result let's commit
next let's do the same for the HTTP
ClientResult
let's follow the same process let's make
it a typealias
over the Result type where the success
is a tuple with Data and HTTPURL
Response
okay and the failure is the Error
protocol okay this is a breaking change
and the compiler is going to help us
find where we need to fix the type
information
and here we just need to put the values
inside a tuple
and in the test target we need to do the
same
okay tests are passing we can also nest
the typealias inside the protocol we
can call it just Result
exactly let's build and run the tests
and solve any type information required
by the compiler
so in this case we just need to add a
dot
run the test again passing awesome
let's commit
now the last custom Result type is the
Retrieve
CachedFeedResult okay but we have
three cases here
instead of two so it doesn't match the
standard Swift Result type
so we could keep it as is it works
perfectly fine
however it would be good to keep
consistency throughout
the application by using the standard
Result type for representing the result
of an operation to do so we can break
down
this custom Result type into success and
failure
where the empty and found cases both
represent
success right so empty is a success case
since it denotes that the retrieval
succeeded
but there was nothing in the cache the
found case
also represents success but with a found
cache with the collection of LocalFeed
Items
and the cache timestamp so we have two
cases for success
which can be represented by an enum
CachedFeed for example exactly
now we have a case for success holding
the CachedFeed that can be empty or
found and the failure case
which represents the errors exactly
so now this matches the standard Result
type
which we can then transform into a type
alias of a Result
with the CachedFeed type as the success
type and Error
as the failure type of course this is a
breaking change
since we have new types so the compiler
is going to help us
solve the type errors so we still have
the found case but it's
wrapped inside a success case exactly
the same in here found and success
empty which can be simplified to just
success
the same here success found
and success
now when creating a Result type we need
to wrap it
in a success case
okay let's run the tests and the
compiler is going to help us
also solve type issues here which will
be to wrap
all the declarations into a success case
as well
and we do it off-camera to save you time
okay compiler errors solved let's run
the tests
it's passing awesome and again
we can move the RetrieveCachedFeed
Result
within the FeedStore protocol this time
since we have more than one
type of Result let's call this a
Retrieval
Result let's fix the type information
much more readable yeah I think so
run the test again it's passing
let's commit
now if you look at the structure of the
CachedFeed enum
it looks very similar to the standard
optional type
that represents none or the absence of a
value
or some as the presence of a value
which is exactly what we're doing here
empty as the absence of a cache
or found as the presence of a cache
so we can use the standard Optional type
to represent
this concept of having or not having a
CachedFeed
so we can even represent it with a
struct okay
so we don't need the empty case anymore
it's just a struct
holding the feed and a timestamp
which is public as it is created by
external
modules exactly and how can we represent
the absence
of a CachedFeed by making it
optional in the Result there you go so
you may have a feed or not but they are
both
representations of a successful
retrieval let's build and the compiler
is going to
guide us to solve the type errors so
instead of found
now we have some which is the
nomenclature on Optional for the
presence of a value
now when we create the Result type some
CachedFeed and instead of empty it's
now none
but we can even simplify in the presence
of a value we don't need to say some
the compiler can imply that that's great
let's run the tests
and solve the type errors there as well
and we'll do this off camera
to save you time okay let's run the
tests
all passing and alternatively this could
be
just a typealias on a tuple
feed and a timestamp
let's run the tests all passing and we
have a much simpler way of defining
our data models awesome let's commit
so let's carry on adding typealiases to
better define
the Result types and for the insertion
operation
we are using an optional Error so far to
represent the result
of the insert operation and the same for
the deletion operation
let's run the tests passing so let's
commit
okay so far we've represented these
operations
Results as optional Errors since they
don't have
values just a potential Error
however to make our code more composable
we can use the standard Result type as
well
exactly for operations that finish with
no success type
you can declare a Result type with a
success case of type
Void and an Error type for the failure
case
now they all represent Results with the
standard Result type
this way you can better convey your
intent in code
as this is a result of an operation and
at the same time
make your code more composable with
other APIs that also use a standard
Result type
so using standard types like Optional
and Result
make your code more composable with
other modules
that also use the standard types to
represent their data models
so now the compiler is going to guide us
to solve the
type errors and here there's another
Result type
that can be replaced with a Result Void
Error so it can be composed
so now when invoking the deleteCached
Feed method
you get a deletion result in the
callback closure
which you can then use a normal switch
case success
we run the success branch case failure
with an error we complete with a failure
with an error
okay and the same everywhere else
okay all type information has been fixed
let's run the tests
all passing let's commit so replace
occurrences of optional Error
for representing an operation success or
failure
with the Result type of Void for success
and Error
for failure now that all our APIs use a
standard Result type
we can improve and simplify some
implementation code
for example in the CoreDataFeedStore
we have many branches calling the
completion
callback and they create a type of arrow
code
when chained with the do catch blocks
with the standard Result type we can
simplify this code by having just
one completion and using the result
type catching initializer where you pass
a closure that may throw an error so we
don't need a do catch block
anymore you can just move the code
inside the do
catch block here we think the catching
closure
because when you throw an error inside
the catching closure
it automatically wraps it into a failure
case
of the Result type so there goes our
failure
completion exactly and we don't need to
invoke
the completion because it wraps returned
values
in a success case let's run the tests
fantastic moreover we can eliminate the
if else
statements by mapping the optional
return value
of defined method
let's run the test again all passing
and we can even omit the catching name
and the cache named parameter by using
the $0
exactly very nice let's run the
test again
this is much better there is no
branching in this code
exactly we just compose and chain the
operations
and a true demonstration of the power of
blazing fast unit tests we change the
whole implementation
and we are sure that the system still
works as it's supposed to
fantastic and we can do the same for the
other methods
let's do it quickly
let's run the test again all passing and
the code is much
nicer no branching awesome
let's commit simplify CoreDataFeed
Store
completion code with a new result APIs
you can do the same in the URLSession
HTTPClient
instead of three completions we can have
just one
yeah look at that much much better let's
run the test again
passing let's commit
and finally let's update our CI config
to
build and test with an image that
supports Swift 5.
let's commit awesome this is it for this
lecture
we'll see you all again next time bye
y'all, see ya